<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Logikē latreia the reasonablenesse of divine service : or non-conformity to common-prayer, proved not conformable to common reason : in answer to the contrary pretensions of H. D. in a late discourse concerning the interest of words in prayer and liturgies / by Ireneus Freeman ...</title>
            <author>Freeman, Ireneus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 261 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1576</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13436790</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13436790</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99541</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99541)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 464:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Logikē latreia the reasonablenesse of divine service : or non-conformity to common-prayer, proved not conformable to common reason : in answer to the contrary pretensions of H. D. in a late discourse concerning the interest of words in prayer and liturgies / by Ireneus Freeman ...</title>
                  <author>Freeman, Ireneus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 99 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Tho. Basset ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In reply to "A sober and temporate discourse concerning the interest of words in prayer" attributed to Henry Daubeny.</note>
                  <note>Title transliterated from Greek.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in University of Minnesota Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>H. D. --  (Henry Dawbeny). --  A sober and temporate discourse, concerning the interest of words in prayer.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99541:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99541:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99541:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99541:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> THE REASONABLENESSE OF Divine Service: OR Non-Conformity TO Common-prayer, PROVED, Not conformable <hi>to</hi> Common Reaſon.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer To the contrary pretenſions of <hi>H. D.</hi> in a late <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> concerning the intereſt of words in Prayer and <hi>Liturgies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By IRENEUS FREEMAN, M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Tho. Baſſet</hi> in St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church-yard in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:99541:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99541:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I deal in matters of this quality, would be interpreted by thoſe who know me, as a doing violence to my nature; ſince that theſe <hi>Controverſies</hi> have ſtill been very inſipid to the Guſt of my otherwiſe diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Genius.</hi> And I have alwayes pittied thoſe <hi>Salamanders</hi> that live in the flames of theſe fiery quarrels. So that in this undertaking <hi>I</hi> tread quite counter to my ſelf, and war with my own particular inclinations. And therefore my thus engaging againſt my <hi>intellectual Craſis,</hi> argues the ſtrength of the <hi>Motive,</hi> which I muſt confeſs to have ſuch power with we, that it can make me any thing, and change me beyond the fabled <hi>transforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of <hi>Magick</hi> and <hi>Inchantment.</hi> I would have no <hi>ſelf</hi> to hold me back, when the publick intereſt may receive any thing by my deſerting <hi>it.</hi> And methinks it is a diſgrace to humane Nature to be leſſe generous then <hi>Inanimates,</hi> in not quitting the intereſts of their <hi>private</hi> natures for the <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> advantage. Therefore that which hath inſpired my reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions to this <hi>collateral</hi> attempt, is a ſence that it may prove ſome way ſerviceable to the <hi>Publick.</hi> And in a general <hi>combuſtion</hi> it is every ones duty to bring what <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> he can to throw upon the <hi>Flames.</hi> What the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> have ſuffered from the <hi>Principles</hi> I have ſate down againſt, is a theam too <hi>ſad</hi> to be inſiſted on. It is part of a <hi>miſery</hi> to recount <hi>it.</hi> And what the ſame troubleſome and ſeditious <hi>dogmata</hi> are ſtill a doing, is of as eaſie as lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table obſervation. The <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> which hath done ſuch exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,
<pb facs="tcp:99541:4"/> is ſtill raging in our borders, and therefore there would be no ſuperfluity, if every man were a <hi>Phyſician.</hi> The <hi>Fathers</hi> danger taught <hi>ſpeech</hi> to the <hi>dumb</hi> Organs of the affectionate <hi>Son:</hi> And the diſtreſſes of our dear <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> ſhould animate the endeavours of her du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful <hi>children;</hi> and where abilities are <hi>wanting,</hi> even <hi>create</hi> them. My experience can vouch the power of this <hi>affection;</hi> and if in this diſcourſe I have ſpoke to purpoſe, I owe it to this my reſpectful <hi>paſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The deſign of this preſent <hi>Eſſay</hi> is to undeceive them, who are not fond of their own deluſion. And could I obtain an impartial peruſal from thoſe that are wedded to a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſwaſion, I ſhould not deſpair of diſabuſing them. But their ſtrong preſumptions that they are in the right, and their irreconcileable <hi>antipathy</hi> to the things I am a pleading for, will I doubt only canker them againſt the <hi>charitable at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempter,</hi> and occaſion thoſe bold cenſurers to conclude me in ſtate of <hi>damnation,</hi> for endeavouring to depretiate and ſhame their darling trifles. Therefore I confeſs, that as to thoſe reſolved <hi>confidents,</hi> I cannot but expect, that my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours ſhould prove fruſtraneous, ſince they will never caſt an eye, ſaving of contempt and ſcorn, upon any thing which makes not for their <hi>opinions,</hi> and tends not to the confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them in their beloved <hi>concluſions.</hi> But I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived better hopes of the judicious and more indifferent peruſers: and if I may hinder any ſuch from being abuſed, or diſentangle them from any former <hi>deceptions,</hi> I ſhall have no reaſon to complain of diſappointment or defeature in my <hi>intentions.</hi> Nor yet ſhall I be quite ſucceſleſs upon the former, the ſtubborn and confirmed <hi>Opinioniſts;</hi> ſince by this <hi>Reply</hi> I ſhall do ſomething in order to the removing of that vaunting complaint of theirs, <hi>That their Books are not anſwered,</hi> but that they muſt be beaten down by <hi>club-law,</hi> as they phraſe it. For they cannot reaſonably take
<pb facs="tcp:99541:4"/> it ill, that I have deferred the publication of it till now, ſince hitherto there have been great expectations from certain conferences, that the yoak, which diſſatisfies their tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, would be relaxated. But things ſtanding as they did when they put forth their Diſcourſe of Liturgies, I thought this publication would be <hi>now</hi> no more too ſoon then it is too late. Wherein I am not conſcious to my ſelf of having balkt their ſtrength, with whom I deal in any of my Replies; and am confident no careful <hi>examiner</hi> will find cauſe to charge me with any wilful <hi>ſubterfuges</hi> or <hi>evaſions.</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign not to impoſe on any man, but to convince him: nor have I need to ſhuffle in a cauſe which may be ſo eaſily and fairly defended. And as I have not ſought credit to my <hi>cauſe</hi> by impugning only the weakeſt grounds that its aſſailants have againſt it; ſo neither have I thought to help it, by paſsionate out-cryes againſt the contrary <hi>opinions,</hi> or ſcurrilous bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt their Patrons. The cauſe that needs ſuch aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſhall, I hope, never gain me its <hi>Advocate.</hi> If thoſe I deal with, find my <hi>retortions</hi> ſomething <hi>cutting,</hi> they muſt thank themſelves, who put the knife in my hands, by bringing Arguments againſt the practice of <hi>others,</hi> which naturally <hi>recoyl</hi> upon their <hi>own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It would be improper and impertinent to trouble the Reader here with much about my management of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince I have undertaken: Only I may take leave to intimate, that I have ſerved up this my <hi>Anſwer</hi> in a careleſs natural <hi>ſtile,</hi> only attending to the congruity and fitneſs of my expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, inſtead of comptneſs of phraſe and language, whence they might have taken occaſion to deal with me, as they did with the learned and florid <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Exeter, viz.</hi> ſhuffle off the edge of mine arguments and anſwers with a pretence, that they were but meer <hi>words</hi> and <hi>Rhetorick.</hi> They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not or will not ſee a <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that is ſet forth in any <hi>pomp</hi> or <hi>elegancy,</hi> which yet is ſomewhat ſtrange, that they
<pb facs="tcp:99541:5"/> ſhould ſee the leſſe for <hi>light</hi> and <hi>colours,</hi> or that <hi>illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> ſhould obſcure things. It were therefore better <hi>I</hi> ſhould be wanting to the guſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of nicer curioſities, then ſeem to be <hi>ſo</hi> to the cauſe I am defending. If boldneſs and preſumption be <hi>objected</hi> to me, for attempting a diſcourſe ſo highly made of by the party it comes from, and compoſed (as I hear from ſome of their own) by a <hi>Club</hi> of ſome of the ableſt Non-conformiſts, it will not be hard to return an anſwer, ſince they cannot well expect, that their fondneſs of their own productions ſhould be a reaſon why I ſhould revere or admire them. Be the Authors what they will, <hi>I</hi> have nothing to do with them under any better titles then <hi>H. D.</hi> not dealing properly with them but their Arguments; which <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſs <hi>I</hi> was ſo daring as to think my ſelf well enough provided to enter the liſts with, and therefore thought <hi>I</hi> might do well to prevent the diſturbance of a more able pen.</p>
            <p>And now, Reader, <hi>I</hi> had eaſed thee of this trouble, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted thy eye from attendance in the porch into the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe it ſelf; but that thou mayſt the better judge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>ſufficiency</hi> of the following Anſwer, <hi>I</hi> beg thy further notice of a few <hi>Advertiſements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My deſign is only to ſhew the weakneſs of thoſe <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> which are pretended to <hi>juſtifie thoſe Miniſters who forbear to uſe the Common-prayer,</hi> not that <hi>I</hi> may ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their perſons more odious and obnoxious, but rather that <hi>I</hi> might perſwade them to walk in the wayes of <hi>Peace,</hi> or at leaſt diſſwade others from following ſo bad an example up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch <hi>unconcluſive</hi> inducements, as the Book <hi>I</hi> oppoſe preſents them with. <hi>I</hi> ſay, my only end in this undertaking is <hi>Peace,</hi> and the fruits of <hi>Peace.</hi> For though they ſay page <hi>69.</hi> of that Book, that it poſeth them to prophecy how the reimpoſing of the Liturgy ſhould bring us to <hi>Peace;</hi> yet it needs not an <hi>Oedipus</hi> to aread, how ſubmisſion to thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
<pb facs="tcp:99541:5"/> ſhould conduce thereto; which is the only thing <hi>I</hi> drive at in this diſcourſe. Indeed they affirm again and again, that the Common-prayer is not <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> by <hi>Law:</hi> and therefore it would be requiſite to my purpoſe to prove ſuch an <hi>eſtabliſhment,</hi> were it not that they have ſaved me the labour by profesſing, that they would never the more <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> if it were <hi>eſtabliſhed.</hi> For theſe are their words; page <hi>60. If we thought we could uſe theſe forms without ſin, we ſhould never diſpute the Law in the caſe.</hi> So that the Queſtion betwixt them and me is to be ſtated thus, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ought to conform upon <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> that it were eſtabliſhed by Law. For the ſame reaſon they have alſo excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me from taking pains to diſprove, what they alledge againſt the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of <hi>Liturgies,</hi> in theſe words, page <hi>94 We have no great value for any Arguments they bring us meerly from antiquity, as to matters that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the worſhip of God; becauſe we think the Word of God a perfect and ſufficient rule in the caſe; and we want Vouchers to prove thoſe pretended pieces of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity which they produce,</hi> &amp;c. Laſtly, <hi>I</hi> meddle not with their Reply to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Exceters</hi> Conſiderations concerning the excellency of the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> becauſe if his Lordſhip thinks it worthy an Animadverſion, he will doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe make it with his own or ſome other more able hand then mine is. And beſides ſuch a preſumption in me would not have helped my cauſe in the way that I take to maintain it, who hold that a leſſe excellent Liturgy, when impoſed by lawful Authority, is rather to be uſed, then a more excellent me when ſtanding in oppoſition. So that all which <hi>I</hi> have to do, agreeably to my ſcope, is to maintain this Propoſition, <hi>That there is no reaſon to warrant any Miniſters for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance to uſe the Common-prayer, upon ſuppoſition that it is eſtabliſhed by Law.</hi> And now, Reader, judge without prejudice of their Reaſons, which are contained
<pb facs="tcp:99541:6"/> without any method in the eighth, ninth, tenth, eleventh, twelfth Chapters of the fore-mentioned Book, and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered up and down in other pages, the ſame over and over again: and therefore I deſerve pardon, if I am forced to repeat the ſame <hi>Anſwers,</hi> to the great tryal not only of the <hi>Readers</hi> Patience, but alſo of my <hi>own.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 13. line 7. for <hi>land</hi> r. <hi>hand:</hi> p. 33. l. 24. for <hi>they may not,</hi> r. <hi>may they not:</hi> p. 36. l. 35. for <hi>Periphaſis</hi> r. <hi>Periphraſis:</hi> p. 46. l. 11. for <hi>thought</hi> r. <hi>though:</hi> p. 49. l. 36. for <hi>his kind</hi> r. <hi>its kind:</hi> p. 58. l. 26. for <hi>are not ſo,</hi> r. <hi>are ſo:</hi> p. 81. l 24. for <hi>I know what</hi> r. <hi>I know not what:</hi> p. 82. l. 4. for <hi>examination</hi> r. <hi>exam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99541:6"/>
            <head>The Reaſonableneſs of Divine Service.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Miniſters are not diſcharged from conformity, by their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfaction as to the impoſing of any Forms <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally. That may be lawfully</hi> uſed, <hi>which is unlawfully</hi> impoſed; <hi>Proved by divers inſtances. That lawfull Authority may impoſe</hi> ſignificative Ceremonies <hi>in divine Worſhip; infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from their own Conceſſions. Yet it will not hence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that any but God, may inſtitute</hi> Sacraments. <hi>The right notion of</hi> Superſtition.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE title of the eighth Chapter begins thus, <hi>The firſt Reaſon of divers Miniſters not uſing the Common Prayer. Their diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction as to the impoſing of any Forms univerſally.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. Wherein lyes the reaſon of this conſequence, yea though the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent be put in more advantagious terms, for their purpoſe, then they have put it? <hi>No forms ought to be impoſed univerſally;</hi> Ergo, <hi>We ought not to uſe the Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> The moſt that can follow from thence, is but this; <hi>That the Common Prayer ought not to be univerſally impoſed.</hi> But they pretend to bring a Reaſon wherefore it ſhould not be <hi>uſed.</hi> But may be they think it all one to ſay, <hi>it ought not to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99541:7"/> be impoſed,</hi> and <hi>it ought not to be uſed.</hi> But how abſurd is ſuch a thought? Since I could inſtance in hundreds of things, which ought not to be <hi>commanded;</hi> and yet ought to be <hi>done,</hi> when commanded. Suppoſe the Magiſtrate command me to go three miles to Church, when there is as good a Miniſter in every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect within a mile: This command hinders the exerciſe of my devotion not a little, and therefore it ought not to have been <hi>impoſed:</hi> Yet for all that, it muſt be <hi>obeyed.</hi> If it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that every man is bound to take the courſe which tends moſt to his edification in it ſelf, though it be forbidden by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: and conſequently that in ſuch a caſe I ſhould go to the neareſt Church, and make uſe of <hi>extempore</hi> prayers, rather then preſcribed ones: I anſwer, that by this Rule every houſhold-ſervant ſhould leave all attendance on his Maſter on <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days,</hi> and go into his Cloſet; that way tending moſt directly in it ſelf to his edification. But the ſervant ſhould wiſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, <hi>If I diſobey my Maſter, that I may have a better opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and help for my devotion now; I ſhall be outed of his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and put into a condition attended with far more diſtractions at other times.</hi> And the wiſe Chriſtian ſubject will argue in like manner. <hi>If I diſobey the Magiſtrate in going to the next Church, or not uſing the Common Prayer; and many others do as I do: the Laws being expoſed to contempt, wars and confuſions will ariſe in the Kingdom: or, if the Laws are vindicated, I who break them muſt be under reſtraint: and both theſe wayes I ſhall have worſe advantages of edification afterward, for uſing thoſe which I thought abſolutely beſt; againſt the will of my Rulers.</hi> So then, though it were unlawfull to <hi>impoſe</hi> the uſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer; yet the <hi>uſe</hi> is not <hi>for that reaſon</hi> unlawful, but is notwithſtanding a neceſſary duty. And that ſimilitude they uſe <hi>page</hi> 39. runs on four legs on my Errand, as well as theirs. It is true, the Magiſtrate ſhould not make a Law, <hi>that ſound men muſt uſe a ſtaff, becauſe it is needful for lame men:</hi> But in caſe there ſhould be ſuch a Law, he that remembers <hi>[not for wrath, but conſcience ſake]</hi> will carry his ſtaff, and not content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with ſuffering the Mulct which the Statute determines. And therefore the Author, or Authors, of the book under debate, do very impertinently (to this ſubject) urge over and over the pretended ill conſequences of impoſing this book, as that it hath been the cauſe of ſeparations, the loſs of many learned and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99541:7"/> holy mens Miniſtry, <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 91. For if theſe things were grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (which no conſiderate man will grant) to have been the <hi>proper</hi> Products of the forementioned cauſe: Yet it is nothing to the Queſtion in hand, what have been the effects of <hi>impoſing</hi> the Liturgy; but rather, what have been the effects of <hi>uſing</hi> it. This anſwer (for ought any thing that I can Imagine in my moſt cloſe and anxious thoughts) is ſufficient to ſatisfie thoſe in this Queſtion, who do remain obſtinately unſatisfied about the lawfulneſs of impoſing the Liturgy univerſally. But I am not out of hope of proceeding a little further in my ſecond an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to convince ſome; even that the Magiſtrate (whether Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil or Eccleſiaſtical, I need not diſpute here) hath a power to impoſe a Liturgy; yea this Liturgy under queſtion, if it ſeems to him moſt conducible to the Publick Good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer</hi> 2. Therefore I ſhall begin my ſecond anſwer with thoſe things in the Liturgy, which uſually are moſt ſcrupled, and ſeem to be by thoſe I deal with <hi>pag.</hi> 88. in theſe words; though I ſuppoſe they are falſe printed, for they ſound oddly. <hi>Nor is it true that they have any Authority to appoint ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Ceremonies, where are ſenſible ſigns to affect the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> They tell us what particular Ceremonies they aim at under this notion, <hi>pag.</hi> 91. <hi>Sect.</hi> 14. <hi>The Surpli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, the Croſs, and kneeling at Sacrament are (we think) all.</hi> But I ſhall prove, that lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity have power to appoint ſuch <hi>ſignificative Ceremonies,</hi> by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging other inſtances of the ſame kind, [and bearing the ſame analogy in point of <hi>ſignificancy,</hi> and <hi>affecting the underſtanding</hi>] which I ſuppoſe themſelves allow. Therefore I ask them, whether the Magiſtrate hath not power to command us to be <hi>uncovered</hi> at the time of Prayer to God? This putting on the Hat, is a <hi>ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative Ceremony,</hi> profeſſing our Reverence, and <hi>affecteth the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> as much as thoſe fore-mentioned. If it be replied, that to pray covered is not <hi>decent,</hi> and therefore it may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, becauſe the Magiſtrate may make conſtitution<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> about <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency:</hi> I reply, that it is <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndecent</hi> only becauſe it <hi>ſignifies</hi> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e reverence; and by conſequence; the Magiſtrate may require <hi>other</hi> ſignificative Ceremonies, which he thinks neceſſary to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency,</hi> becauſe neceſſary to <hi>ſignifie</hi> due devotion. Whether they are really neceſſary or no, concerns not the Queſtion; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he really thinks them to be ſo: For his own conſcience muſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99541:8"/> guide him in his own Acts. If therefore he thinks it neceſſary to <hi>expreſs</hi> the ſeparation and higher order of the Prieſt from the People, that he ſhould wear a <hi>Surplis;</hi> whereby he may be put in mind of his duty both to God and the People, and they of their reſpect to God through him, as the Meſſenger of God; Or if the Magiſtrate thinks it neceſſary to expreſs our humble and thankfull acceptation of our Saviour, that we receive the Sacrament on our knees: or if he thinks it neceſſary to expreſs our obligation to God by Baptiſm, that we ſhould do homage by receiving and ſuffering ſome ſenſible Badge and Sign; it is not material whether theſe Ceremonies be indeed as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to thoſe ends (which come under the notion and name of <hi>decency</hi>) as he thinks them to be. Nothing can juſtly deny him this authority obliging the ſubject, except they be <hi>forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> by Gods Law, to be uſed; which whoſoever will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to prove, I am ready to anſwer him. But then the proof muſt not be (an uſually it is) that the Magiſtrate hath no power to command them; for then we ſhould only run in a Circle; but that they are unlawfull in themſelves to be uſed, as being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid by the Law of God. For it is clear from what I have ſaid, that he may as well command theſe as to pray bare-headed: if theſe be no more forbidden by God then that. If it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, that to be uncovered is <hi>commanded</hi> by the Apoſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> as a Ceremony which <hi>nature</hi> teacheth: I anſwer, that we are not to underſtand by it the <hi>abſolute nature</hi> of Man <hi>univerſally;</hi> but the <hi>conditional nature</hi> and <hi>Idiopathy</hi> of of ſuch Countrey-men, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> many times ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Breeding.</hi> Otherwiſe <hi>Nature</hi> would teach the <hi>Turks</hi> the ſame manners; who yet ſignifie their reſpects by keeping on their <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>bant.</hi> So that if it ſhould be <hi>enacted</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> that men ſhould keep on their Hats before Courts of Juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that the contrary ſhould be accounted an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front to the dignity of their Superiours: In ſuch caſe the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate might with the ſame equity make a Law, that we ſhould keep on our Hats in Prayer, to expreſs our Reverence. It may be further replied, that yet ſtill the putting on the Hat, or keeping it off, ſignifies no more in <hi>Gods worſhip</hi> then it doth in <hi>civil commerce:</hi> But the Croſs and Surplice ſignifie that in Gods worſhip, which they do not in civil commerce. To which I anſwer, though the <hi>Materials</hi> of theſe Ceremonies ſignifie not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99541:8"/> any where elſe what they do here; yet they may be apt ſigns to ſignifie, what they properly ſignifie here. As the flower <hi>de Luce</hi> ſignifies one thing on a ſign Poſt, and quite another in the Scucheon of <hi>France;</hi> and yet both <hi>naturally,</hi> as the word hath been expounded before, that is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. <hi>cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily.</hi> And in the Kings Coronation, there are many Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies uſed, which ſignifie quite another thing there from what they ſignifie, applyed in another caſe. But this will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear better <hi>(ad homines)</hi> by inſtancing in that high piece of Gods Worſhip, <hi>An Oath.</hi> The holding up the hand ſometimes ſignifies an intention to ſtrike, ſometimes other things: But in the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied a calling God to witneſs. The ſame may be ſaid of laying the Hand upon a Bible, and kiſſing the Book in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Oath.</p>
                  <p>From whence, if the ſcrupulous Miniſters are ſatisfied of the Magiſtrates Power to impoſe thoſe Ceremonies of an Oath; Me thinks it muſt needs follow, that he hath Power to impoſe <hi>ſignificative Ceremonies,</hi> and <hi>ſenſible ſigns affecting the underſtanding</hi> in the outward exerciſe of Divine Worſhip: And thoſe Quakers which refuſe to take ſuch an Oath, do act more evenly to their Principles; then thoſe great Divines, whoſe Scholars they are.</p>
                  <p>Indeed they bring ſome ſhew of a Reaſon in the place laſt cited <hi>pag.</hi> 88. for their denying, that Rulers have any authority to appoint ſignificative Ceremonies, and ſenſible ſigns to affect the underſtanding. Their Words are theſe: <hi>This is to give them Authority to inſtitute Sacraments. God hath appointed us Ordinances, where by ſenſible ſigns spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Myſteries are repreſented to us. Theſe are his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; we know no Authority men have to add to them, though they avoid the Popiſh Rock of conferring Grace, which we ſay no true Sacrament doth</hi> ex opere operato. But the anſwer is ready, <hi>viz.</hi> That this Argument makes as much againſt the Ceremonies annexed to a ſolemn Oath, as againſt any other ſignificant Ceremonies, <hi>quatenus ſignificant:</hi> But indeed, it makes againſt neither the one, nor the other. For to make a Sacrament (as the word is properly and ſtrictly taken) it is not enough, that there be a ſign repreſenting ſpiritual my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries. I doubt, the Authors ſcorn to learn out of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99541:9"/> Catechiſm in the Common Prayer-Book: elſe they might ſee there, that it muſt be ordained by Chriſt himſelf to be a <hi>means</hi> and a <hi>pledge.</hi> How ever, that may convince them that the impoſers of thoſe Ceremonies, againſt which they are ſo querulous, never intended them to be <hi>Sacraments:</hi> for, they never ſay, that they were ordained by Chriſt himſelf to be pledges and means. But I hope they have a better value for Mr. <hi>Perkins:</hi> and I am ſure, when I was a School-boy, I learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of him, that a Sacrament is not only a ſign to repreſent, but alſo a ſeal to confirm, and conſequently implies a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitution. Humane Authority may appoint our <hi>ſeals,</hi> by which we have our engagements to God confirmed; as the Croſs after Baptiſm: but they cannot make <hi>Gods</hi> ſeals, by which his promiſes may be confirmed to us (for that is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to him;) and therefore they can make no new Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But though they can make no new <hi>ſeals;</hi> yet they may make new <hi>ſigns</hi> without making a Sacrament; Yea, and new ſeals on our part, though not on Gods. It is wont to be objected, What place can be then left for Superſtition, if men may add new Ordinances which God hath not declared to be neceſſary? To which I anſwer, that Superſtition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not in uſing theſe things, as <hi>helps</hi> to Worſhip; which are only not commanded by God, but withall not forbidden: But in uſing them as neceſſary <hi>pieces</hi> of Religion <hi>ſanctified</hi> by divine inſtitution, when they are not. And ſo there may be as much Superſtition in <hi>ſitting</hi> at the Sacrament, as in <hi>kneeling;</hi> in wearing <hi>other</hi> Garments, as a <hi>Surplis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99541:9"/>
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Text</hi> Deut. 12.32. <hi>doth not forbid all humane inventions in</hi> Gods Worſhip <hi>any more then in</hi> Civil Government. <hi>It condemns as much the approved practice of</hi> David <hi>and</hi> Salomon, <hi>and our preſent diſuſe of the</hi> Ceremonial Law. <hi>The ſeal of the</hi> Canon, Rev. 22. <hi>conſidered, as to this matter.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>I Have heard many more ſuch exceptions made againſt theſe <hi>humane inventions,</hi> as they call them: But I remember I am not now writing a Treatiſe, but anſwering a Book; and ſhall only anſwer the objection, which the <hi>Authors</hi> make from that Scripture which hath the greateſt appearance of patronage to their cauſe, of any I know of in the Bible. It is Deut. 12.32. <hi>What thing ſoever I command you, obſerve to do it: thou ſhalt not add thereto, nor diminiſh from it.</hi> This they cite to their purpoſe in the Queſtion under conſideration, with this <hi>Gloſs</hi> pag. 100. <hi>By this Text certainly all humane inventions in the worſhip of God are forbidden.</hi> But <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is an Argument themſelves much cry down: Therefore let us take the Liberty they give us, to examine their interpretation by the Rule of Right Reaſon; by which it will eaſily appear, that their <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> truth is a <hi>certain</hi> falſhood. For (1.) If this Scripture forbids all humane inventions in Gods Worſhip; then all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inventions in the Civil Government are forbidden alſo. The Conſequent is falſe by their own confeſſion, unleſs they will deny that the <hi>Act of Indempnity</hi> is either an <hi>Humane Invention,</hi> or a <hi>Lawful Act: Ergo,</hi> the Antecedent is falſe alſo. I prove the Conſequence thus: Thoſe words, which are applyed <hi>both</hi> to the commands of God about his Worſhip, and to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God about the Civil Policy; do <hi>as much</hi> forbid hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inventions in Civil Policy, as in the worſhip of God. But theſe words <hi>[Thou ſhalt not add thereto, nor diminiſh from it]</hi> though in the twelfth of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> they are indeed applyed to the commands of God concerning his own Worſhip; yet in other places they are applyed to all his commandments in general. <hi>Ergo,</hi> They do no more forbid humane inventions in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, then in Civil Policy. The Minor is clear from Deut. 4.1, 2. <hi>Now therefore Hearken O</hi> Iſrael <hi>unto the Statutes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99541:10"/> and unto the Judgements, which I teach you, for to do them You ſhall not add to the word that I command you, neither ſhall you diminiſh ought, from it.</hi> Now the Laws made to regulate <hi>Civil</hi> commerce, and <hi>Judicial</hi> proceedings, were ſome of thoſe <hi>Statutes and Judgements,</hi> to which all additions are forbid: And therefore if ſuch a Prohibition forbids all humane inventions in the Worſhip of God; it muſt needs forbid humane inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Civil Government, which I hope thoſe I oppoſe, are not ſo wild as to aſſert. (2.) We find good and holy men (notwithſtanding this Prohibition) ſetting their own <hi>Prudence</hi> a work to invent new things in the Worſhip of God: which may well ſerve, as an Argument <hi>ad homines,</hi> to convince thoſe, which place ſo much in <hi>Examples</hi> as uſually the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts</hi> do. But that it may be the more eaſily and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally ſuccesful; I ſhall further demonſtrate, that theſe examples were approved by God alſo. We have an inſtance, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. <hi>David</hi> purpoſed to build God an houſe. The Reaſon which grounded this Purpoſe, was no command of God; but meerly <hi>Prudential,</hi> ver. 2. <hi>The King ſaid to</hi> Nathan <hi>the Prophet; See now I dwell in an houſe of Cedar, but the Ark of the Lord dwelleth within Curtains.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> approveth the Motion in the next words, <hi>Go do all that is in thy Heart, for the Lord is with thee.</hi> And though afterward God by <hi>Nathan</hi> ſtopped the <hi>execution;</hi> yet it is evident from the divine Oracle, that he liked the <hi>Intention:</hi> as he took pleaſure in the readineſs of <hi>Abrahams</hi> mind to offer <hi>Iſaac,</hi> though he would not have him be actua ly ſlain. This divine approbation of <hi>Davids</hi> purpoſe appears from Gods <hi>promiſe</hi> made thereupon, <hi>to build</hi> David <hi>an houſe, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo doth his Son <hi>Salomon comment</hi> upon the foreſaid Oracle in his prayer at the dedication of the Temple, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.18. <hi>The Lord ſaid to</hi> David <hi>my Father, Whereas it was in thy Heart to build an houſe to my Name: thou didſt well that it was in thy Heart. Nevertheleſs thou ſhalt not build the Houſe, but thy Son.</hi> If it be ſaid, that <hi>David</hi> had a particular command for it by divine and <hi>extraordinary</hi> Revelation, beyond the Dictates of his ſanctified Reaſon: This is ſaid clearly <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> Book: yea, and <hi>againſt</hi> Book. For thus God anſwereth <hi>David,</hi> 1 Chron. 17.6. <hi>Spake I a word to any of the Judges of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>ſaying Why have ye not built me an houſe of Cedars?</hi> And beſides, if God commanded <hi>David</hi> before; why did he forbid
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99541:10"/> him afterward? For though God did forbid that to <hi>Abraham,</hi> which he had firſt commanded him: Yet the two caſes (as to our purpoſe) are not alike in many reſpects; which I could inſtance, and ſhall if there be need. It remaineth therefore, that there was no Divine direction given to <hi>David</hi> concerning this, beſide the light of his own Reaſon, the <hi>Candle of the Lord;</hi> the commands of which are the commands of God: But that I inſiſt not on here. God never commanded any where in the Levitical Law (to my beſt Remembrance) that a Temple ſhould be built in future Ages. I confeſſe I read more then once that when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhould be ſettled in their inheritance, there ſhould be a <hi>ſtated place</hi> in ſome of the Tribes, where God would be worſhipped, and where he would place his Name. But that might be by ſettling the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> there, without an <hi>houſe</hi> of Wood and Stone. In like manner <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> though indeed God had ſaid he ſhould build the Temple, yet ſtayeth not for a command from God about the form, the meaſure, the materials, and many other adjuncts of the ſame: though all theſe things were <hi>determined</hi> by God himſelf in the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and not left to <hi>Humane Prudence.</hi> Neither doth <hi>Salomon</hi> in theſe and many other Points keep to the <hi>Pattern</hi> of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> but follows his <hi>own</hi> Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Accordingly at the <hi>Dedication</hi> he kept a Feaſt [and it was an <hi>holy</hi> Feaſt, For it was kept <hi>before the Lord God,</hi> 1 Kings 8.65.] <hi>ſeaven dayes and ſeven dayes, even fourteen dayes:</hi> a Feaſt, that was never commanded nor kept before; and therefore by the <hi>reaſonings</hi> of theſe men a more <hi>monſtrous</hi> and abominably <hi>anomalous</hi> holy-day then <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> it ſelf. Other <hi>inductions</hi> might be made; and ſhall be when there is occaſion, if this doth not ſuffice to evince, that the forecited Prohibition <hi>[Thou ſhalt not add thereto]</hi> doth not forbid all humane Inventions in the Worſhip of God. (3.) The <hi>Text</hi> under conſideration ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not add to [it] nor diminiſh from [it.]</hi> The Pronoun Relative [it] doth plainly refer to the Law delivered by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; whether Moral, Political, or Ceremonial. And if this Prohibition binds us in the <hi>ſenſe</hi> which they affix unto it, I ſee not how we can avoid, but we muſt turn <hi>Jews.</hi> If it be replyed, that the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> Laws are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated by the coming of Chriſt, and therefore we may
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99541:11"/> do things which are not by them enjoyned, and leave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done things that are; but yet that there remains the ſame <hi>analogy</hi> and <hi>Common Reaſon</hi> in reſpect of the Precepts of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> I anſwer, that the <hi>Proportion</hi> and <hi>Common Reaſon</hi> is not the ſame in our caſe, till it be proved that God hath by Revelation <hi>determined</hi> all things in his Worſhip in the ſayings of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> which are upon <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,</hi> as perfectly as he did in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> wherein not ſo much as the <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uffers</hi> and other ſuch <hi>Punctilio's</hi> are pretermitted. It is uſually urged, that the ſame <hi>Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which now we diſpute off, doth <hi>ſeal</hi> up the whole <hi>Canon</hi> of Scripture; <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. where Saint <hi>John</hi> concludes, <hi>If any man add to theſe things, God ſhall add to him the Plagues, &amp;c.</hi> But if theſe words in the latitude of their <hi>meaning</hi> are not to be <hi>reſtrained</hi> to the Book of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> (which yet is moſt probable) but <hi>extended</hi> to the <hi>whole</hi> Body of Scripture; Yet they are not to be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as forbidding thoſe actions in Gods Worſhip, that are not <hi>preſcribed</hi> in the Bible. For there are <hi>other</hi> precepts in the Bible, beſide <hi>thoſe</hi> which are Directive of Gods <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> as about <hi>Good husbandry</hi> and <hi>Good huswifry</hi> in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs.</hi> And therefore <hi>theſe</hi> Words in the end of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> prohibiting with an <hi>equall</hi> peremptorineſs <hi>any</hi> additions to <hi>any</hi> Parts of the Bible; they muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn humane inventions in <hi>good Husbandry,</hi> as much as in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God: and Mr. <hi>Hartlib</hi> will be found <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly</hi> affected at the Tribunal of theſe <hi>Expoſitors.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99541:11"/>
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>By the Miniſters ſenſe of the Text we are obliged to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the</hi> Political <hi>Laws of</hi> Moſes. <hi>The Anſwer</hi> [<hi>that we are</hi> ſo <hi>to the</hi> Reaſon <hi>of them</hi>] <hi>retorted. The things meant in that Text are ſuch, as were an</hi> abomination <hi>to God</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedently. <hi>Their ſenſe of the words not only</hi> abſurd, <hi>but</hi> exotick.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p n="4">(4.) IT was as much unlawfull to <hi>add</hi> to the <hi>Political</hi> Laws of the Jewiſh State, as to the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Moral;</hi> or to <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh</hi> from them. And yet [as theſe men underſtand the Words, <hi>add,</hi> and <hi>diminiſh</hi>] we do continually <hi>add</hi> to them, and <hi>dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> from them; and they blame us not. For when a Thief is <hi>hanged,</hi> inſtead of making the aſſigned <hi>reſtitution,</hi> here is an <hi>addition:</hi> and when the <hi>Dam</hi> is taken with her <hi>Young ones,</hi> or an houſe made without <hi>Battlements,</hi> or a Rebellious Son not <hi>ſtoned</hi> to Death, here is a <hi>diminution.</hi> The <hi>Fifth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narcy men</hi> do more exactly live <hi>up</hi> (or rather <hi>down</hi>) to their Principles, then they who taught them. I cannot ſee, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the forementioned reaſons we are bound by the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Laws of <hi>Moſes.</hi> If it be ſaid, ſo we are ſo far as the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of the command remains; I anſwer, that in ſuch caſes it is clear that the <hi>command</hi> doth not oblige us, but the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of the command; and the ſame <hi>Reaſon</hi> would oblige as much when there is no command: which is all I contend for, that <hi>human Reaſon</hi> may invent <hi>new conſtitutions</hi> about the commerce of Men; and <hi>conſequently</hi> about the Worſhip of God with a <hi>non-obſtante</hi> to the Text alledged. By theſe four Reaſons it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to any <hi>unprejudiced</hi> and <hi>conſiderate</hi> Reader, that theſe Words <hi>[Thou ſhalt not add to it]</hi> do not ſignifie <hi>[There ſhall be no humane Inventions in the Worſhip of God;]</hi> Yea, although this ſhould be the moſt <hi>literal</hi> and <hi>obvious</hi> ſenſe of the words. The Reaſon is, becauſe of thoſe many plain contradictions and groſs abſurdities, that would neceſſarily be conſequent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; as I have already inſtanced. I might add, that there were <hi>new</hi> and difficult caſes ſometimes <hi>contingent,</hi> in which the Judges could not proceed by the <hi>ſtated</hi> Rules of Law; but were to make their addreſs to Perſons appointed by God, and to <hi>ſtand</hi> to their ſentence. Moreover if <hi>[Thou ſhalt not add to it]</hi> did ſignifie in the place quoted <hi>[Thou ſhalt not do, what
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99541:12"/> is not commanded];</hi> yet the context maketh it appear, that thoſe things were <hi>meant</hi> that were an <hi>abomination</hi> to God <hi>antecedent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to the giving of his Law, or at leaſt by their <hi>contrariety</hi> to his Law. It doth not appear that thoſe things were at all meant, which are an <hi>abomination only</hi> becauſe they are <hi>not commanded</hi> by his Law (if there be any ſuch things, as thoſe I deal with <hi>ſuppoſe.</hi>) To ſpeak more clearly, if it may be; The Text forbids the <hi>adding</hi> of ſuch things that are an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Lord, not becauſe they were <hi>not preſcribed</hi> in the Law, but becauſe they were <hi>condemned</hi> by the Law, or were <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnable</hi> before the giving of the Law. This will be evident, if we conſider the words immediately preceding, Deut. 12.30 31. <hi>Enquire not ſaying, How did theſe Nations ſerve their Gods? Even ſo will I do likewiſe. Thou ſhalt not do ſo to the Lord thy God: For every abomination to the Lord, which he hateth, have they done to their Gods,</hi> And then it follows, <hi>Whatſoever thing I command, obſerve to do it; thou ſhalt not add thereto, nor diminiſh from it.</hi> Now it is granted, that <hi>ſuch</hi> things are not to be <hi>added</hi> in Gods Worſhip (no nor <hi>any where elſe</hi>) by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Invention, which are an abomination to the Lord in their own <hi>nature,</hi> or by being <hi>contrary</hi> to ſome Divine poſitive Law, and <hi>not meerly</hi> by being <hi>not preſcribed</hi> in the Law; Such as <hi>burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Children in the fire,</hi> the inſtance of the Text: For <hi>that</hi> is the Reaſon given, wherefore the Hebrews ſhould not do as the <hi>Gentiles</hi> did without Gods command; becauſe the Gentiles did ſuch <hi>abominations.</hi> I confeſs the words alſo do <hi>implicitly</hi> and by the mediation of a <hi>Rational Inference</hi> forbid the doing of ſuch things as are not an <hi>abomination,</hi> out of any <hi>emulation</hi> or <hi>mimical</hi> deſire to be <hi>like</hi> the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> Becauſe the doing of ſuch things, as are no <hi>abomination,</hi> out of ſuch a <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> would <hi>naturally</hi> tempt and <hi>eaſily</hi> lead the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to imitate the Heathens in ſuch things <hi>alſo</hi> which are an <hi>abomination.</hi> But to do thoſe things which the Gentiles did in the Worſhip of God, not out of any <hi>value</hi> and <hi>authority</hi> given to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, whoſe <hi>Modes</hi> they be; but becauſe of any <hi>goodneſs</hi> or <hi>uſefulneſs</hi> apprehended by <hi>Reaſon</hi> in the things <hi>themſelves:</hi> This I deny to be abſolutely forbidden to the Hebrews by vertue of <hi>this</hi> Text, as hath been made to appear by the Example of <hi>David</hi> in building a Temple after the <hi>manner</hi> of the Heathens, much leſs are we <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> under any ſuch prohibition. But
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99541:12"/> ſo far as this Scripture toucheth the doing of ſuch things in Gods Worſhip, as the Idolaters did, it ſhall be conſidered <hi>afterward</hi> with others of the like nature, which the Authors cite in their <hi>appendix</hi> to their <hi>Second Reaſon.</hi> The reſult of what hath been ſaid is this: that if the ſenſe which they give of the Words were the moſt <hi>literal, unconſtrained,</hi> and <hi>next</hi> at I and; Yet being ſo abſurd [as I have proved it to be] it ought to be rejected. But now I go a ſtep higher. (5.) This ſenſe, which they faſten to them <hi>[Thou ſhalt not add to it,</hi> i. e. <hi>There ſhall be no humane Inventions in Gods Worſhip]</hi> is very <hi>exotick</hi> and <hi>far</hi> fetched. The Maſter bids his ſervant to be at home at <hi>one</hi> a clock: The ſervant is at home both at <hi>one,</hi> and at <hi>ſix:</hi> being not <hi>otherwiſe</hi> forbid to be at home at <hi>ſix.</hi> Doth the ſervant <hi>add</hi> to his Maſters <hi>words,</hi> becauſe he doth ſomething <hi>more</hi> then his Maſter bade him? No, except he either <hi>ſayes</hi> or <hi>thinks,</hi> that his Maſter bade him to be at home at <hi>both</hi> thoſe hours; <hi>Then</hi> indeed he <hi>adds</hi> to his <hi>Words.</hi> To apply this <hi>analogous</hi> inſtance to one of the Points under debate, being <hi>applicable</hi> to them all: Chriſt hath commanded us to <hi>baptize in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi> The Miniſter <hi>doth ſo:</hi> as <hi>alſo</hi> he doth afterwards ſign the Party with the ſign of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> in token that he ſhall not be aſhamed to confeſs the faith of Chriſt crucified, and manfully to fight under his banner, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth the Miniſter here <hi>add</hi> to the <hi>Words</hi> of Chriſt? No, except he either <hi>ſayes</hi> or <hi>thinks</hi> that Chriſt hath bid him do <hi>both</hi> (I mean by a <hi>Particular</hi> command; for in <hi>general</hi> he hath as the caſe may be, and is in <hi>England;</hi> ſince he hath commanded us, to <hi>obey thoſe that are over us in the Lord, and ſubmit our ſelves:) then</hi> indeed he <hi>adds</hi> to the <hi>words</hi> of Chriſt, and not elſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he makes Chriſt to <hi>ſay more</hi> then he <hi>ſaid.</hi> And this was the fault of the Scribes and Phariſees, that they did teach for <hi>divine</hi> doctrines the traditions of <hi>men;</hi> clayming <hi>that Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> to their own words or thoſe of the Elders, which is only due to the Words of God. Theſe things, which I have alledged, being conſidered, I willingly expoſe my ſelf to be <hi>derided</hi> after the Biſhop of <hi>Exceter</hi> in pag. 89. of their Book; for holding, <hi>that the Power of Lawfull Rulers to inſtitute ſuch Ceremonies, is a principle to death to be aſſerted.</hi> For if the Laws of the <hi>Land</hi> grant ſuch a power, <hi>God</hi> hath nowhere forbad it. And this were to dye a <hi>Martyr</hi> to <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which is not ſo ſmall a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99541:13"/> part of <hi>Religion,</hi> as ſome make it: and ſo their <hi>loud</hi> laughter <hi>eccho's</hi> back upon <hi>themſelves.</hi> I have ſtayed thus long upon their Reaſon, <hi>as</hi> it is <hi>worded</hi> in the <hi>contents</hi> of the eighth chapter; becauſe I ſuppoſe they would ſet the beſt foot formoſt: and becauſe I do not find it [in terms of the ſame import] to be the ſubject of the chapter it <hi>ſelf;</hi> as will appear by the <hi>Particulars</hi> of that chapter, which I now come to examine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Miniſters</hi> firſt Reaſon <hi>againſt</hi> conformity, viz. [<hi>that it is not clear to them to be lawfull for all perſons at all times to limit themſelves by</hi> Forms] <hi>examined.</hi> (1.) <hi>We are to obey the Magiſtrate in ſome things whoſe lawfulneſs we are not clear in.</hi> (2.) <hi>The Liturgy doth not limit all men at all times.</hi> (3.) <hi>There is a difference betwixt limiting a mans</hi> ſelf, <hi>and being</hi> limited. <hi>That a man may limit himſelf, proved by their own words.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THey begin that which they <hi>call</hi> their firſt Reaſon, thus. <hi>It is not clear to us, that it is lawfull for all Perſons, and at all times, to limit themſelves by any ſtinted Forms of Prayer.</hi> This ſtands in the <hi>Place</hi> of an <hi>Argument;</hi> and therefore requires an <hi>anſwer,</hi> if a man could but divine whereabouts the <hi>Vis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guendi</hi> lies in it. Let us ſearch it <hi>all over</hi> according to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb,</hi> which bids us look where it is <hi>not,</hi> as well as where it <hi>is.</hi> When they ſay <hi>[It is not clear to us]</hi> they muſt mean, if they will <hi>ſhape</hi> their Argument for their preſent uſe, <hi>That the Magiſtrate is not to be obeyed, except in ſuch things whoſe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs is clear to us.</hi> And when they ſay <hi>[At all times]</hi> their words cannot amount to a Reaſon proper for the caſe, unleſs they ſuppoſe, <hi>that the Common prayer cannot be uſed without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting themſelves at all times by ſome ſtinted Forms of Prayer.</hi> And when they ſay <hi>[Limit themſelves]</hi> their words have no ſhew of an Argument to their purpoſe, except it be implyed, <hi>that it is all one in the Preſent caſe for a perſon to limit himſelf, or to be limited by the Magiſtrate.</hi> For if either that, which is not <hi>clearly to us</hi> lawfull, may and ought to be done when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: or the uſing of the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> doth not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99541:13"/> infer a mans limiting himſelf by ſtinted forms <hi>at all times;</hi> or it be not all one <hi>to limit himſelf,</hi> and <hi>to be limited</hi> by the Magiſtrate: if either of theſe things be ſo, and confeſſed to be ſo by the <hi>Authors;</hi> then it is manifeſt, that the words un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der examination have not the <hi>face</hi> of an <hi>Argument</hi> in their <hi>own</hi> eyes. Therefore, that we may put it into the <hi>beſt</hi> Poſture of Strength; we muſt needs ſuppoſe, that it <hi>implyes</hi> the truth of the three <hi>mentioned</hi> Poſitions: all which will be found too light. (1.) The lightneſs of the <hi>firſt</hi> I demonſtrate thus. The Lawfulneſs of an action is not <hi>clear</hi> to that man who doubteth of the Lawfulneſs: not being <hi>certain</hi> that the action is lawfull, nor yet certain that it is unlawfull. But yet <hi>ſuch</hi> a man is bound to do that action, when it is commanded by the Magiſtrate. The Reaſon is, becauſe it is <hi>certain</hi> the Magiſtrate is to be obeyed, commanding Lawfull things: but it is <hi>uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> whether the thing commanded be unlawfull. From whence it follows, that the Perſon ſo doubting, ſins more hainouſly in not doing that action, then in doing it. And ſince he muſt needs <hi>venture</hi> one of the two wayes, he ſhould chooſe to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the <hi>ſafer.</hi> Now it is ſafer to <hi>obey</hi> doubtingly, then to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey</hi> doubtingly. For if the action be lawfull; the <hi>omitting</hi> of it [beſides the injury done to the Magiſtrate] is of evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to the <hi>publick</hi> by the violation of the Laws: But if it be unlawfull, the bad influence of the <hi>action</hi> is much more <hi>private.</hi> The Authors will give me occaſion afterward to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume this caſe; and therefore now I diſmiſs it with with a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that excellent Caſuiſt Dr. <hi>Sanderſon</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln,</hi> who hath fully reſolved this Queſtion in his fourth Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Ad Clerum. Surely, when things hang thus even, if the weight of Authority will not caſt the Scale either way; we may well ſuppoſe that either the Authority is made very light, or elſe there is a great fault in the Beam.</hi> (2.) Neither is the ſecond <hi>Theſis</hi> any whit ſounder, which muſt be ſuppoſed to make good their Argument, viz. <hi>that the uſe of the Common Prayer doth infer a limiting themſelves to ſtinted Forms of Prayer at all times.</hi> I cannot find any ſuch limitation in the Liturgy, nor in the Act which authoriſeth the ſame: But if the Miniſter uſeth it at the times appointed, he is left to his Liberty to pray otherwiſe at other times; if not in publick, at leaſt in private. (3.) Of the ſame validity is their Third Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99541:14"/> 
                     <hi>That it is all one for a man ſo to limit himſelf, or to be limited by the Magiſtrate.</hi> For how can an <hi>Action</hi> and a <hi>Paſſion</hi> fall under the ſame <hi>Category?</hi> It is lawfull to any one to be <hi>injured</hi> (to put the caſe to their beſt advantage;) and yet it is not lawfull to him to injure <hi>himſelf.</hi> Even ſo, if it were not lawfull for a man to limit <hi>himſelf</hi> to ſtinted Forms; Yet it might be lawfull to him to <hi>be limited.</hi> Indeed, if it were a thing unlawfull in it <hi>ſelf,</hi> and to be done in <hi>no caſe;</hi> their Reaſon would hold: becauſe the Magiſtrate cannot limit us, that is, we ought not to be limited by him, where ſubmiſſion to ſuch limitations is unlawfull. But that is not granted, and is under preſent diſputation. They themſelves grant in the next words, that thoſe which have not the gift, may help themſelves by forms. Now that which is lawfull in <hi>any caſe</hi> that may fall out, is not unlawfull in it <hi>ſelf.</hi> And why is not the Magiſtrates Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition as conſiderable a <hi>caſe,</hi> as want of a Gift? <hi>Id poſſumus quod jure poſſumus.</hi> There is a <hi>Civel</hi> Faculty and Licence, as well as a Natural one: And <hi>both</hi> are required in Perſons under Government, to the doing of an Action well. Doth the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring of a <hi>Gift</hi> make that unlawfull, which was lawfull before in <hi>every</hi> caſe? I know in <hi>ſome</hi> caſes it doth; becauſe God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth <hi>that</hi> of him who hath a gift, which he doth not of others. But if the caſe under queſtion be <hi>ſuch,</hi> the Authors ſhould ſhew where God hath <hi>commanded</hi> thoſe that have the Gift, <hi>alway</hi> to pray <hi>ex tempore:</hi> and not argue <hi>meerly</hi> from the <hi>Gift</hi> it ſelf. For it is moſt certain, that it is moſt lawfull not to do <hi>many</hi> things, which a man hath a <hi>Gift</hi> to do. Otherwiſe, a man that hath a Gift to drink his Beer <hi>cold,</hi> ſinneth in drinking it <hi>warm,</hi> though preſcribed by the <hi>Phyſitian:</hi> And a School-boy, that can make a ſpeech <hi>extempore</hi> to ſalute a ſtranger, ſinneth in taking <hi>time,</hi> and conſulting his <hi>Phraſiology</hi> at the injunction of the <hi>Schoolmaſter.</hi> Beſides, who ſhall <hi>judge</hi> of the ſufficiency of the Gift? The Phyſitian, or the Patient? The Maſter, or the Scholer? The Magiſtrate, or the Subject? The Authors grant in their <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> diſcourſe about the uſe of Words in Prayer, that many a <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> Chriſtian hath an excellent degree of this <hi>extempore</hi> vein: By <hi>their</hi> Reaſon he ſhould uſe it in the <hi>Publick,</hi> and at the time appointed for the Common Prayer; for <hi>that</hi> uſe of it is <hi>only</hi> reſtrained by the Liturgy. If the <hi>non-ordination</hi> of the private man be pretended to diverſifie his caſe, from that of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99541:14"/> I reply, That thoſe which be <hi>ordained,</hi> are <hi>ordained</hi> to exerciſe their gifts in a <hi>Lawfull</hi> way only, and not <hi>contrary</hi> to the Rules preſcribed them by their Superiours: as an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity Orator is choſen to uſe his <hi>Rhetorical Gift,</hi> but not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the will of the Univerſity, if they make known their will to him; and if they will have him at ſome times to put into his Letter the very <hi>words,</hi> which they <hi>dictate</hi> to him, he is bound to do it though he be ordained to exerciſe his Gift.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Some things premiſed to the anſwer of their Argument from a mans obligation to</hi> uſe <hi>his</hi> gift. <hi>The</hi> (1.) <hi>Anſwer, A man may</hi> uſe <hi>his</hi> gift <hi>otherwayes, both</hi> (1.) <hi>In Gods Service, and</hi> (2.) <hi>Out of it.</hi> (2.) <hi>A man is not bound to uſe his gift, when the uſe of it would hinder another. It is no ſin when hindered by Providence; applyed to the preſent caſe. A double reaſon, why</hi> Forms <hi>of</hi> Sermons <hi>might not as well be impoſed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>AND now way is made to anſwer the Reaſon they bring in the next words: wherefore a Miniſter, that hath the Gift of <hi>extempore</hi> Prayer, is bound to uſe it in Publick. It is in theſe words; <hi>Where God hath given any that Gift, we conceive it is a manifeſtation of the Spirit given him to profit others by; and that he is defective to his duty, that doth not uſe it to this end.</hi> They preſs the ſame Argument in other terms, pag. 28. of their Book thus, <hi>The reſtraining of Chriſtians, eſpecially of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, in the exerciſe of the gift of Prayer in the publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the Church, looks like that quenching of the Spirit, which is forbid to all men by the Apoſtle; and the choaking the coveting of the beſt gifts, which is commanded all Chriſtians. For to what purpoſe ſhould thoſe Talents be deſired, which man hath Authority to command to be laid up in a Napkin?</hi> Before I give my anſwer to this Argument, it will be <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of ſome expreſſions of <hi>Moment</hi> in the <hi>laſt clauſe,</hi> which are not in the <hi>Firſt.</hi> For there they ſpeak of reſtraining not only <hi>Miniſters,</hi> but other <hi>Chriſtians</hi> from the uſe of the gift of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in <hi>publick Aſſemblies.</hi> So it ſeems they would have <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99541:15"/> make <hi>extempore</hi> prayers in the Church: For <hi>otherwiſe</hi> their gift is no more reſtrained by joyning with the Common Prayer, then with the Miniſters <hi>extempore</hi> prayer. But I hope better things of thoſe I deal with, from ſome <hi>Prints</hi> of Learning they have left upon their diſcourſe; and therefore let that go, as a ſlip of their Pen, rather then Error of their Mind. Again, they ſpeak here of an <hi>active</hi> reſtraining, and not of a <hi>Paſſive:</hi> But I have noted already, that to reſtrain others, is quite of another Reaſon from being reſtrained by others: as to impriſon, differs from being impriſoned. Again they ſay, that it is to no purpoſe to deſire ſuch a gift, which the Magiſtrate hath power to command to be laid up in a Napkin. But this is contrary to experience, if they keep to the Queſtion of <hi>Publick</hi> reſtraints; For many a man would deſire Learning for the uſe of his own ſoul, though he ſhould be reſtrained from teaching others: and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, the ſcience of Medicine. The Gifts of ſundry Artificers are not to be exerciſed <hi>freely,</hi> but in <hi>ſome</hi> places and Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and under ſuch and ſuch <hi>limitations</hi> of the Magiſtrate: and yet theſe gifts are deſireable notwithſtanding. I confeſs, the Gift they ſpeak of, is not <hi>ſo much</hi> to be deſired by <hi>publick</hi> Officers, when the <hi>Publick</hi> uſe is forbidden, as it would and ought to be <hi>otherwiſe:</hi> But in this caſe, the <hi>remiſſion</hi> of their deſires is no fault of theirs (if it be any fault at all) but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe who have taken away the <hi>Reaſon</hi> which ſhould <hi>intend</hi> the ſaid deſires. So much for that, which is <hi>emphatical</hi> in the words <hi>laſt</hi> quoted above what is in the <hi>firſt.</hi> I now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to anſwer the Argument <hi>common</hi> to them <hi>both.</hi> The ſumm is this, <hi>That he, who hath the Gift of</hi> extempore <hi>Prayer, if he uſeth it not in publick, doth quench the Spirit, and is defective to his duty: ſeeing the ſaid gift is a manifeſtation of the Spirit given to profit others by.</hi> To this Argument, I anſwer, (1.) That the <hi>ſame</hi> gift may ſerve to <hi>ſeveral</hi> uſes; and he that uſeth it to <hi>one,</hi> is in ſome caſes excuſed, eſpecially if he be hindered by Lawfull Authority to uſe it in <hi>another.</hi> Take their own confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion pag. 78. <hi>There are an hundred things that are the Gifts of God; of which yet there is no uſe in the Worſhip of God.</hi> And again, <hi>Is there no way to ſerve God with the uſe of his Gift, but to uſe it in his worſhip?</hi> I confeſs they ſpeak of the Gift of <hi>ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and an hundred more: but I ſay, their words, are applicable to the Gift of <hi>extempore</hi> praying in Publick. It may be put to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99541:15"/> another uſe: both <hi>in</hi> the Worſhip of God, and <hi>out</hi> of it. (1.) In the Worſhip of God. Becauſe the ſame faculty which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables a man to utter a <hi>good Prayer</hi> to God, enables him alſo to make a <hi>good exhortation</hi> to the People. He that can confeſs ſin in ſuch a method and way, as to ſtir up contrition in thoſe that joyn with him, can alſo aggravate ſin to his hearers, to the ſame end in a Sermon. He that can back his <hi>Petitions</hi> with forcible and Rhetorical Arguments [not to affect God, but men,] can uſe the ſame arguments in a popular addreſs to encourage the faith of his Auditors. He that hath a good gift of diſplaying and advancing the Love and gifts of God in his <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> may uſe the ſame <hi>Mediums</hi> to excite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame Dvine Love in the People. They that become Publick Readers of Divinity in the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> though they uſe not their gifts to thoſe ends to which they might be uſed in a <hi>Countrey Church,</hi> yet cannot be ſaid to <hi>quench the Spirit,</hi> becauſe they uſe them to other ends to which alſo they have an utility. (2.) The Gift of Prayer may be put to other uſes <hi>out</hi> of the Worſhip of God alſo. Otherwiſe thoſe <hi>Lay-men,</hi> that have it, did highly ſin that they are not Miniſters. But this is their excuſe, that the <hi>ſame</hi> gift is of uſe in their <hi>ſecular</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; even as the <hi>ſame</hi> Learning, which helps a Miniſter to interpret the <hi>Scripture,</hi> helps the Philoſopher to expound the Text of <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> The Authors themſelves ſay in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their book, that he that is able [ſuppoſing his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Philoſophical</hi> and <hi>Political</hi> notions] to make a good ſpeech upon thoſe Themes; is alſo able (ſuppoſing the like knowledge of <hi>Theological</hi> ſubjects) to make a good <hi>Prayer</hi> to God. From whence may be reciprocally gathered, that he that hath the gift of making <hi>Prayers,</hi> is by the ſame gift en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to make <hi>Orations:</hi> And if he uſeth it <hi>one</hi> way for the Publick profit, he is not guilty of hiding his Talent in a Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, though he uſeth it not the <hi>other</hi> way. My ſecond Anſwer follows. (2.) That man, who uſeth not a gift, ſinneth not, when the uſing of it would hinder the uſe of another. And this excuſeth Miniſters that they do not <hi>pray</hi> without end; but afford ſome time for the gift of <hi>Preaching,</hi> yea, and for the gift of <hi>reading</hi> too. Yea, without this, moſt men would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, except they come into the Church, and make pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers there. For in that they do not ſo, it is manifeſt they uſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99541:16"/> not this Gift: And that they have it, or ought to have it, muſt needs be confeſſed by the Authors, ſince, <hi>pag.</hi> 7. they make it to conſiſt in <hi>Meditation</hi> and <hi>Speech,</hi> with Gods ordinary bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon <hi>Induſtry.</hi> Now <hi>every</hi> man hath the power of <hi>medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti n,</hi> moſt men of ſpeech: And, if the Authors Reaſon be good, every man is bound to join induſtry, that ſo he may make Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the publick Aſſemblies. But he is not bound to this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath other gifts to exerciſe, and one cannot do all:
<q>Tu ſupplex ora, tu protege, tu<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> labora.</q> To apply this anſwer, If a Miniſter that hath the Gift of <hi>extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> prayer, cannot uſe it without hindring the exerciſe of his preaching gift, he is diſcharged from the uſe of the former, that he may continue the uſe of the Latter. So that if the Laws ſay, He that uſeth his gift of praying, ſhall not uſe his gift of preaching, but lie in Priſon, or worſe; it is manifeſt that it is better to uſe but <hi>one</hi> of thoſe gifts, then by uſing them <hi>both,</hi> to be ſuffered the uſe of <hi>neither.</hi> (3.) The Authors confeſs in the Place now under examination, that in caſe <hi>the exerciſe of this Gift be hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by providence,</hi> then it may be <hi>not uſed:</hi> But when the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate forbids it, it is hindered by providence. The confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is more plain againſt themſelves, pag. 57. <hi>We dare leave our Miniſtry, if Authority command.</hi> What, dare you leave the uſe of <hi>all</hi> your Miniſterial gifts <hi>at once;</hi> and yet not leave the uſe of <hi>one</hi> of them, when the diſcontinuance of the uſe of <hi>one</hi> may prove the continuance of the uſe of <hi>all!</hi> Put another caſe, A Miniſter hath no Living, and no body will lend him his Pulpit: How doth he uſe his gift in Publick? If it be ſaid, he <hi>cannot;</hi> it is true: though he hath a natural Power to uſurp another mans Pulpit, yet he cannot do it of Right. Why? Becauſe the Laws forbid it. For were it not for humane Laws, a ſtranger might uſe his gift in any Church, as well as the Parochial Miniſter. So then the Reſult is this, He <hi>cannot</hi> uſe his gift, becauſe the Laws for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him; and becauſe he <hi>cannot,</hi> therefore he is excuſed. In like manner he <hi>cannot</hi> uſe his gift of prayer in his own Church, who is forbid by the Laws; and becaſe he <hi>cannot,</hi> he is guiltleſs, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this objection drawn from the uſe and end of the gift.</p>
                  <p>They go on in the ſame page thus, <hi>We are yet to learn that it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99541:16"/> is not as lawfull to impoſe Forms of Sermons upon Miniſters, as forms of Prayer: Both of them are lamentable reſtraints put upon the Gifts of God beſtowed on his Miniſters.</hi> From which words cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will gather, That the Authors of this Book were none of the contrivers or approvers of the <hi>Directory:</hi> For theſe <hi>lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſtraints</hi> both of Prayers and Sermons are to be found there. But I cannot conceive them ſo <hi>unlearned,</hi> as to be yet to learn, why Forms of Sermons ſhould not be impoſed as well as forms of Prayer. A mans <hi>Mother wit</hi> without the help of much learning will prompt him eaſily with two Reaſons. (1.) Becauſe in the Sermon the Miniſter ſpeaks what he thinks is the Truth; and if it appear otherwiſe, they may reject it. But in prayer the Miniſter in the name of the people (for he ſaith not <hi>I</hi> but <hi>We</hi>] preſenteth deſires to God, which ſometimes happen to be quite contrary to the deſires of ſome of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yea of all the People: it may poſſibly fall out, that the people can joyn with him not in one expreſſion: whereby it comes to paſs both that the Miniſters prayer is a falſhood, and that the people being in a praying poſture, do make a kind of profeſſion that they ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to thoſe Petitions, which their ſouls abominate, which makes it appear, why there is more reaſon the people ſhould know before hand what ſhall be <hi>prayed,</hi> then what ſhall be <hi>preached:</hi> which fore-knowledge is the effect of <hi>Forms.</hi> (2.) Becauſe the Miniſter in his preaching is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, confirm, and apply to his people all the Articles of Faith, as ſhall be occaſion; a work which will require many dayes, if not years. It would be endleſs to compriſe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of all Sermons in forms: But we pray for the ſame things continually: and therefore the directory ſaw reaſon to put down the ſenſe and Matter of Prayer, though not of Sermons. But this is ſo eccentrical to the Queſtion, I am ſorry I have ſaid ſo much of it. For if it were granted, that both forms of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Sermons were miſerable reſtraints; Yet the gifts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny an honeſt Priſoner have been under miſerable Reſtraints, and yet he never the leſs honeſt for that.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:99541:17"/>
                  <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Another of their Arguments</hi> [<hi>That a man muſt pray with the greateſt</hi> intention <hi>and</hi> fervour: <hi>which is abated by</hi> Forms] <hi>anſwered. No man is bound to a greater</hi> intention, <hi>then may be procured by</hi> lawfull <hi>means. In ſome caſes a man may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully do that, which naturally will remit his</hi> fervour. <hi>Their own experience proves not, that a man may not be as</hi> fervent <hi>with a</hi> form, <hi>as without it. This kind of</hi> Fervour <hi>argues not the</hi> excellency <hi>of thoſe Prayers, in which it is</hi> moſt <hi>procured; It being often the Reſult of meer</hi> natural <hi>and</hi> animal <hi>forces.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>I Proceed to the next words, becauſe they have ſome <hi>ſhew</hi> of an Argument. The <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition whereof is this, <hi>We are ſure it is the unqueſtionable duty of every one that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, to do it with the higheſt intention of mind imaginable, and with the greateſt fervency of Spirit: And that it is not lawfull for any man in Prayer to allow himſelf in any thing, which may either divert his mind from the moſt fixed contemplation of God, or intention upon his duty, or which may any way cool the Heat and Fervency of his Spirit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer to this Propoſition by a <hi>diſtinction</hi> thus. True, Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man is bound to pray with the <hi>higheſt</hi> intention of Mind, and with the <hi>greateſt</hi> fervency of Spirit, that can be obtained by the uſe of <hi>juſt</hi> means: But no man is to uſe <hi>unjuſt</hi> means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that <hi>intention</hi> and <hi>fervency.</hi> And again, True, it is not lawfull for any man to allow himſelf in any thing that may hinder the foreſaid <hi>intention</hi> and <hi>fervency;</hi> if the phraſe <hi>[allow]</hi> ſignifies only to <hi>approve</hi> and <hi>like</hi> ſuch an impediment, or ſuch a condition as is neceſſarily expoſed to it: But if <hi>[allowing]</hi> ſignifies <hi>not accuſing</hi> himſelf, or the <hi>vindication</hi> of himſelf from the accuſations of others that impute ſin to him for praying while he labours under ſuch an impediment: then I ſay, a man may <hi>allow</hi> himſelf in ſomething that may hinder the <hi>intention</hi> of his mind, and <hi>fervency</hi> of his ſpirit in Prayer. If He, or they, that made this book, take their Propoſition in that ſenſe, wherein I <hi>grant</hi> it, it is nothing to the purpoſe: For a man may uſe the Common Prayer, and yet <hi>wiſh</hi> he might be at his Liberty if the Magiſtrate thought good. Therefore the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99541:17"/> muſt needs be taken in the ſenſe wherein I <hi>deny</hi> it: and the Reaſon of my denyal is evident from the forementioned Inſtance. He that is forbid by the Magiſtrate to go to the next Church, and therefore is neceſſitated to go to one more remote, muſt needs be more indiſpoſed to Prayer by his long journey (except ſome men of a <hi>temper</hi> by themſelves:) ſo that he ſhall not perform that duty with ſo <hi>high</hi> an Intention of mind, or with ſo <hi>great</hi> a fervency of Spirit, as might probably be experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced, in caſe he came into the Church leſs weary, and weather-beaten. But yet ſuch a man may lawfully go to the <hi>furtheſt</hi> Church, and pray there: though theſe hinderances of <hi>intention</hi> and <hi>fervour</hi> be conſequent thereupon. The Reaſon is, Becauſe they are <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and not <hi>voluntary:</hi> He wiſheth the caſe were otherwiſe with him: but, as things ſtand, if he ſhould go to the next Church contrary to the Magiſtrates prohibition, he ſhould ſin; and Evil is not to be done, that good may come of it: eſpecially, when a <hi>greater</hi> evil would come of it then the good aimed at, as it is in this caſe. And conſequently he may <hi>allow</hi> himſelf, that is, not accuſe himſelf for praying under ſuch clogs and <hi>remora's</hi> of his devotion. By the ſame Reaſon, though it were granted that the uſe of the Common Prayer did hinder that height of Intention and fervour of ſpirit they ſpeak off; yet, the not uſing it being forbid by the Magiſtrate, a man may uſe it and <hi>allow</hi> himſelf in the uſe. For it is clear, that theſe incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences render it only <hi>inexpedient,</hi> but not <hi>unlawfull.</hi> Indeed <hi>p.</hi> 90. they urge, that things which (though otherwiſe lawfull) are inexpedient, ought not to be done. I ſay ſo too, if a man be left to the liberty of action: and be not otherwiſe reſtrained by a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> or <hi>Political</hi> neceſſity. For if the <hi>Law</hi> reſtrains a man from that which otherwiſe were <hi>more</hi> expedient: then that which was <hi>more</hi> expedient, becomes <hi>leſs</hi> expedient: Not only becauſe it is made unlawfull, but alſo becauſe in ſuch a caſe (all things conſidered) it hath no tendency or inſtrumentality to that end whereto it was conducible before, but rather to the contrary. Such Actions as before the Prohibition would have a good effect, after the prohibition will have a bad one: ſuppoſing that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the prohibition they were meerly and purely <hi>lawfull</hi> and <hi>expedient,</hi> and not alſo otherwiſe <hi>neceſſary,</hi> which only are the ſubject of the preſent debate. To bring down my Anſwer again to the <hi>Hypotheſis:</hi> If it ſhould be granted, that <hi>extempore</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:99541:18"/> Prayers are <hi>moſt</hi> expedient to procure the higheſt intention and greateſt fervency in Prayer; Yet, being forbid by the Law, they are <hi>moſt</hi> inexpedient to ſuch an end, all things conſidered, and that for the Reaſon I have already propounded, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe if this violation of the Law eſcape that penal animadverſion, which is due to it by the Law; then <hi>Seditions</hi> and <hi>Wars</hi> muſt needs enſue thereupon, which rough weather is no fit ſeaſon for the fruits of Righteouſneſs, which are ſown in <hi>peace:</hi> But if the Authority of the Law be aſſerted by exemplary puniſhments; then the tranſgreſſours in the caſe muſt loſe the publick exerciſe of their Miniſtry; which will be much more incommodious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient to the foreſaid intention and fervour in publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſince they will be ſuffered to pray none in publick at all. The <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition being thus proved either falſe, or imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent; falſe in that ſenſe I take it in, and impertinent in any other: Their Argument muſt needs fall without any more ado, ſince no Argument can ſtand on one Legg. But much more, if the <hi>Minor</hi> alſo be found exceeding doubtfull, as will be found, when we have rehearſed it in its terms, which are theſe; <hi>We cannot be induced to believe that any one can poſſibly ſo keep his ſoul fixed upon God, or ſo intent upon God, while he reads a Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as whiles he ſpeaks it from his own conception.</hi> To which I anſwer, That he who rationally believes any thing impoſſible in the <hi>ſeries</hi> of <hi>moral</hi> effects, where temper, education, cuſtom, and the influence of private affections doth ſo commonly intend and remit the <hi>Power</hi> of the Agent, muſt have more to propound then the meer <hi>experience</hi> of the <hi>Non-event.</hi> But the producers of this Argument plead nothing to prove it <hi>not poſſible,</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>experience;</hi> and that not <hi>univerſal,</hi> but their <hi>own:</hi> not daring to deny, but that others may <hi>experience</hi> the contrary, as may be ſeen in their next words. <hi>We find by experience (not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine poſitively of the frame of other perſons ſpirits) a great difference in the intention and fervency of our ſpirits, when our words in prayer are directed and determined by the inward heat, fervency and affection of our hearts, from what is, when our words are determined for us by other men; yea by our ſelves before the time of Prayer.</hi> Thus the Authors ſay for themſelves: But if others may be admitted to tell their Experiences, they will ſay the quite contrary for themſelves. And though the Authors find it thus, as they expreſs; Yet, may be, the intention and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99541:18"/> fervour is ſuch as argueth not the <hi>excellency</hi> of <hi>ex tempore</hi> Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers above others, being no <hi>excellent</hi> ſymptom it ſelf; but poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly being the reſult of the meer natural and animal forces, or worſe, as will appear by five Inſtances I ſhall immediately pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce; and if the Authors impartially ſearch themſelves, they may poſſibly find a ſixth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VII.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Five</hi> ſorry <hi>cauſes aſſign'd, wherefore ſome men may be more</hi> fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>in</hi> extempore <hi>Prayers then in</hi> Forms. (1.) <hi>An</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy <hi>againſt the one, and a perſwaſion that the other is a mark of</hi> Grace. 2. <hi>The</hi> Novelty <hi>which extemporary Prayers give ſcope for.</hi> (3.) <hi>Nature is more intent in the exerciſe of</hi> gifts <hi>then of</hi> Graces. (4.) Self-love, <hi>mens natural affection to their</hi> own <hi>Inventions, and impatience of Reſtraints.</hi> (5.) <hi>In</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore <hi>Prayers there is room for</hi> Oſtentation <hi>of</hi> Parts, <hi>and (as ſome will interpret it) of divine</hi> experiences. <hi>Two other cauſes of this</hi> Fervour.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p n="1">(1.) SOme men by their education have received an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy againſt forms, having been taught that to pray by a Form is no prayer; and on the contrary, it is a ſign of grace to pray without one. This opinion hath ſo prevailed, that many men have gained a great name and repute of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, meerly by their prayers, among ſome well-meaning, but ſimple people, who undertook to be as skilful as the tryers, who could <hi>taſte</hi> mens <hi>ſpirits</hi> by their tones and phraſes. Now it is no wonder, that he can have but little intention or fervour in reading a form of Prayer, who hath a deep rooted antipathy againſt it; as he will but coldly recite a Poem, who nauſeates it. He may well be ſtruck <hi>cold</hi> in reading a Form, who either believes he ſins in doing it, or ſcruples whether he ſin or no. And on the other hand no marvel, though he be intent and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in making an extempore Prayer, who judgeth in any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſincerity of his heart, either by the <hi>copia verborum,</hi> which ſome call <hi>enlargements;</hi> or by the ſudden and eaſie ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of pertinent places of Scripture, or experience, to ſerve as <hi>arguments</hi> in his Petitions. But that thoſe which have the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99541:19"/> gift, do too much thus judge of their grace by it, is evident, in that often, if they be ſtraitened, they let down their criſt, and queſtion their eſtate; though before they had a full <hi>plerophory</hi> bred in them by ſome precedent enlargements, and though they are conſcious to themſelves of no <hi>new</hi> ſin, or neglect, that might have altered the caſe. (2.) Some men may be more intent and fervent in <hi>extempore Prayers;</hi> becauſe there is ſo much place for <hi>novelty,</hi> which is ſo taking with the nature of mans mind. This is ſo prevalent, that ſome have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that whereas at one time a Scripture hath been <hi>ſet on their hearts</hi> in prayer, to the powerful actuation and accen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their ſpirits, and hath continued in proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble force for ſome time; yet by degrees it grows <hi>ſtale</hi> and out of date: So that when the ſame Scripture-expreſſion is uſed by them (though not induſtriouſly, but fortuitouſly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtudy) it hath loſt its ſting and Energy; it hath no more ſavour then the old <hi>Mumpſimus</hi> of Common-Prayer to their variable <hi>Guſto.</hi> And then a new phraſe comes upon the ſtage, and acts its part with like vigour for a time, and <hi>Exit;</hi> till at length by difuſe the old one hath recovered its edge again. I know ſome will ſolve this <hi>Phenomenon,</hi> by ſuppoſing the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the <hi>Spirits</hi> impreſſions, ſometimes bringing one expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion into the mind, and working it on the affections, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times another. But <hi>Entia non ſunt multiplicanda ſine neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate;</hi> there is no neceſſity to aſſign a <hi>Metaphyſical</hi> cauſe for ſuch an accident, as we ſee obviouſly effected by the powers of <hi>Nature.</hi> For Schollars experience the <hi>ſame</hi> thing in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, where the Spirit cannot be pretended, beginning to read or meditate on a <hi>new</hi> ſubject with great <hi>intention</hi> and <hi>fervency,</hi> but ſoon calmed, and ready to lay it aſide, till the diverſion of a new one hath made the old one new again. (3.) Nature it ſelf is apt to be more intent and fervent in the exerciſe of a <hi>Gift</hi> then in the exerciſe of a <hi>Grace;</hi> and therefore where there is place for the exerciſe of <hi>both,</hi> there may probably be more intention and fervour, then where there is place only to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe <hi>grace:</hi> And in this caſe the <hi>leſs</hi> intention is as acceptable to God as the <hi>greater:</hi> For the <hi>over-plus</hi> may ariſe from the <hi>gift,</hi> and not from the <hi>grace:</hi> whereas the Lord delighteth not in the <hi>legs of a man,</hi> nor in his wit and tongue neither; but his delight is in them that <hi>fear</hi> him. To apply this anſwer, He
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99541:19"/> that reads the Common-Prayer, exerciſeth no <hi>gift</hi> in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of that which is exerciſed in <hi>extempore Prayes;</hi> all that is left him to do, is, to exerciſe <hi>Grace,</hi> as faith, love, humility, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: But the other exerciſeth his memory, fancy, invention, an harder piece of judgement, beſides method. Now ſince we are moſt ſtupid to the beſt and moſt ſpiritual duties; and had rather read a book where our parts and gifts are exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, then a <hi>plain</hi> one (though more <hi>practical</hi>) where the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Grace is more <hi>purely</hi> and <hi>ſingly</hi> required: it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that <hi>caeteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> paribus,</hi> there will be more intention and heat in the uſe of <hi>extempore</hi> Prayer, which ſets ſo many <hi>gifts</hi> a work, then if the ſame man ſhould uſe the Common-prayer, which employs little elſe then his <hi>graces.</hi> And yet this overplus of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and heat is hardly a better ſign to the perſon in whom it is, that he or his Prayer is any whit more acceptable to God, then the intention and heat which a ſchool-boy finds in uſing his invention, and making his verſes, above that which he finds in reading an Author. For invention takes up the ſoul, be it in what ſubject it will. And this brings me to a fourth Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, wherefore ſome men may be more intent and fervent in <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers, then in the Common-prayer. (4.) Men are <hi>naturally</hi> more affected with their own inventions, then with thoſe of others; and therefore <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers may more affect them then preſcribed forms, upon no better an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count then that of <hi>ſelf-love.</hi> May be ſome have experienced, that they can better joyn with <hi>others</hi> in an <hi>extempore</hi> Prayer, then in a Form: but that may proceed from the <hi>firſt</hi> Reaſon, and moreover from this I ſhall now name; That it is natural to be intent and fervent in hearing others to exerciſe their parts notably; and it is no more then we find in reading or hearing any piece of <hi>Wit.</hi> But the Authors have profeſſed, that <hi>they</hi> come not under this Reaſon, being not ſo much affected with premeditated forms of their own: therefore becauſe it reacheth not <hi>them,</hi> though it doth others, I will not account it a <hi>fourth</hi> Reaſon, but ſubſtitute another, which, for ought I know, may agree to them. It is <hi>natural</hi> to the mind of man to be impatient of reſtraint, and love to be at its own liberty; whence it comes to paſſe, that a plauſible fancy doth more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail then a ſevere and ſullen Argument; as Doctor <hi>Reynolds,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> hath excellently noted, in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99541:20"/> of <hi>the Paſſions and Faculties of the Soul,</hi> cap. 4. Now men uſing their own liberty in <hi>extempore Prayers,</hi> but being limited and tyed up by Forms, they may be more intent and fervent in the former then in the latter, upon no better principle then that which is moſt predominant in the <hi>moſt</hi> corrupt men, which are the <hi>moſt</hi> independent, and ſay, <hi>Let us break their bonds aſunder, and caſt their cords from us.</hi> (5.) In unpremedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated Prayers there is far greater room, and ſcope, and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for <hi>oſtentation</hi> and <hi>vain glory</hi> in the diſcovery of mens parts and gifts; yea (as ſome hearers will interpret) of their graces and divine experiences. And what can fleſh and blood be more intent and earneſt about, then ſuch an employment? And that the intention and fervour of many in their Prayers proceeds from this Reaſon, is evident from hence, in that when they pray before others, they will weep and make other ſuch ſigns of intention and fervour; but it is not ſo when others pray before them. I have now mentioned the five Reaſons I promiſed, which may probably cauſe the overplus of intention and fervour in theſe men, while they uſe <hi>extempore Prayers,</hi> above what they find in uſing of Forms. I ſay not only <hi>poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</hi> but <hi>probably.</hi> For ſeeing the <hi>ſelf-ſame</hi> things are prayed for in the <hi>Letany,</hi> which can be the matter of the longeſt <hi>extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> Prayer, though not in that novelty, variety, and elegancy of phraſe, if the heat and intention they ſpeak of did <hi>purely</hi> proceed from the ſtrength of their deſire to the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, it would be equal in both caſes. But ſince it is not equal, it muſt needs proceed from ſome other cauſe, and probably from one or all thoſe I have aſſigned, ſince it is known that they are apt in their own nature to produce ſuch an <hi>inequality,</hi> It might be further conſidered, that ſome perſons, having entertained ſome <hi>private</hi> opinions of their own, are engaged by them to pray for ſuch things, which the Prayers of the Church do not beg of God, but rather the contrary; as it was in the late wars, when the late King thought one Reaſon of diſliking the Common-prayer was, that there were ſo many Petitions put up for him. I ſhall only add a Reaſon, which relates more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and eſpecially to the <hi>fervency</hi> ſpoken of, then to the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> of mind: And it is this, when a man doth ſtrongly bend his wit in ſtudy (moſt of all in <hi>invention</hi>) he feels a ſenſible heat in his body, inſomuch that I have known ſome to put a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99541:20"/> napkin dipped in cold water on their heads. Any man (I think) may experience, that in ſuch an employment he doth not <hi>breath</hi> ſo freely and frequently as ordinarily he doth; which will be moſt apparent to ſuch as take Tobacco; even as a man holds his breath when he is about with all his might to ſtrike a blow. And this obſtruction of the breath alone is ſufficient to effect an extraordinary fervency in the blood and ſpirits. Beſides, when a man is not only to <hi>invent,</hi> but to invent as <hi>faſt</hi> as the Auditors expect he ſhould <hi>utter:</hi> in caſe matter comes not faſt enough, he will be apt to <hi>draw out</hi> his laſt words to the great ſtraining of his body, and to make up the defect of <hi>matter</hi> with more then ordinary earneſtneſſe in the <hi>delivery.</hi> Like him, whoſe notions being <hi>out</hi> before the glaſſe, lifted up his voyce the higher, to make amends for the frivolouſneſſe of that which he produced; of whom one of the hearers ſaid, <hi>This Miniſter will be hot in ſpight of his matter.</hi> Now this kind of fervency, being only the tumult of the bodily ſpirits, is not much to be reckoned of, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending much upon age, temper, and the weather it ſelf: The aged and grown Chriſtian hath the leaſt of it, whoſe devotion, in reſpect of ſtilneſſe and quietneſſe, comes nearer to that of the ſoul in ſtate of ſeparation. The <hi>baſeneſſe</hi> of this kind of <hi>fervour</hi> is excellently diſplayed by that holy and learned Doctor <hi>Henry More,</hi> in his divine Poem of the <hi>Life of the Soul,</hi> in the deſcription of <hi>Glaucis.</hi> And if any man would be better informed of the <hi>naturall</hi> Reaſons of ſuch heats and fervours, let him conſult Doctor <hi>Caſaubon</hi> of <hi>Enthuſiaſme.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99541:21"/>
                  <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Miniſters Reaſon, why unpremeditated Prayers beget</hi> inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>anſwered. The Mind is not abſtracted from all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Objects in them. The advantage of the Prints and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters in a Book, in order to the eaſie bringing of the</hi> Idea's <hi>into the head. The diſadvantages to the</hi> Hearers <hi>by</hi> extempore <hi>Prayers. The</hi> Soul <hi>dictates to the</hi> Tongue <hi>in</hi> Forms.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>I Would not willingly paſſe over any thing in the Book which I oppoſe, that hath any ſhew of Patronage to the cauſe maintained therein, and am careful to anſwer every allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under that head to which it doth moſt properly appertain. And therefore remembring, that <hi>page</hi> 28. this Reaſon is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, wherefore the mind may be more intent in unpreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated Prayers, <hi>viz. Becauſe the Soul is more abſtracted from all created objects, then it can be while a great piece of the work is to look on the Book to ſee what to ſay next:</hi> I think this the moſt proper place for a reply. My Anſwer is this. Every man that is an expert reader (eſpecially in reading that, which he hath read often, in a fair print) doth probably find, that he heeds the characters little, or not at all, but minds the ſenſe, or ſomething elſe. Nor is the Soul neceſſarily more <hi>abſtracted from all created objects</hi> in <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers, then it may be in reading a Prayer out of a Book. The <hi>created objects,</hi> which are met with in a Book, are the Prints and Characters in the Book: But he that prayes without book (eſpecially with <hi>vocal</hi> prayer) muſt needs look upon the like <hi>prints</hi> and <hi>ſtamps</hi> made in the <hi>Brain:</hi> or whatſoever things the <hi>ſpecies</hi> are, without which a man can neither ſpeak nor think, they muſt needs be <hi>created objects;</hi> The very <hi>Idea</hi> of a God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Creature</hi> in the opinion of all that are not <hi>Plato</hi>'s Schollers, as I ſuppoſe the Authors are not. And the <hi>legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſignes</hi> in the Book do ſerve to bring the <hi>inward phantaſmes</hi> more readily into actual view, and to marſhall them with leſſe labour, diverſion, and diſturbance. That which they ſay next, <hi>We do believe this may be experienced by any perſons ſpeaking to a man for his life,</hi> comes not at all into my Creed.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99541:21"/> But whatever advantages <hi>extempore</hi> prayers have to fix and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the ſpirit of the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> that which he ſhould moſt aim at in Publick, is to affect his hearers. And thoſe things which moſt affect him, do many times leaſt affect them, not being able to underſtand what he doth underſtand, nor to follow him at the firſt hearing through a long-winded ſentence. He that <hi>writes never</hi> ſo deliberately and ſlowly, in the review ſees cauſe to alter many things for <hi>perſpicuity</hi> ſake; and much more may a ſudden <hi>Speaker</hi> labour under ſuch obſcurity, ſince an <hi>Hearer</hi> hath not that time and other advantages of finding out the ſenſe which a <hi>Reader</hi> hath. Therefore the main thing to be conſidered, is, not the Miniſters own experience of what altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he finds in <hi>himſelf</hi> by theſe two ways of Praying; but which is beſt for the <hi>People.</hi> They give their Opinion upon that Queſtion in theſe words; <hi>Nor can we believe that any Miniſter praying in any form, uſeth ſo rational and experimented a means to affect his hearers hearts, as he that uſeth none. As in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is a certain lively efficacy of the voice, which every hearer diſcerneth more in the Miniſters ſpeaking</hi> ex animo, <hi>then from his reading a Sermon.</hi> I know not what others diſcern: I ſhould think <hi>extempore</hi> Sermons made by the moſt able Preachers, much inferior to the preprared ones of much worſe Preachers. I have been more affected with a Sermon <hi>read,</hi> then <hi>remembred:</hi> And when the Miniſter reads his Sermon, I expect a good one. But let us ſee the Reaſon why they believe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. <hi>Becauſe the Speaker himſelf is diſcernibly not ſo much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in reading as in ſpeaking.</hi> To make up this Reaſon, it muſt be ſuppoſed, that he who appears affected <hi>himſelf</hi> in ſpeaking, is moſt likely to affect <hi>others:</hi> which is true, if other advantages be <hi>equal,</hi> as if he be as clear as rational, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe perſwaſive, but not elſe, except among men but a ſmall degree above bruits, who are more convinced by a ſtrained voice then a ſober Reaſon, and take every knock on the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit for an Argument. Beſides I have known ſome as <hi>diſcernibly affected</hi> in reading the Common-Prayer, as others are in their <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers. However, I think it not much worth a Miniſters labour to raiſe <hi>ſuch</hi> affections in his People, that are not founded upon the truth and reaſon of what he aſſerts; but only on the boldneſſe, confidence, and eagerneſs of the Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I wiſh ſome courſe might be taken to prevent ſuch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99541:22"/> rather then promote them: For ſuch Perſons that are ſo eaſily <hi>paſſive</hi> under a loud voice, or other Symptoms of the the Speakers affection, will hardly be able to withſtand the aſſaults of a <hi>bawling</hi> Quaker: whereas a wiſe man is ſo far from being affected with a noiſe without Reaſon, or with Reaſon for the noiſes ſake (for it is all one); that nothing is more nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to him, then to hear that ſtoutly inculcated which is but weakly demonſtrated. The Authors add but one more Note upon this Point of the <hi>expediency</hi> of <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers: and it is this in the Chapter under animadverſion, Sect. 4. <hi>Speaking is an immediate act of the tongue, but commanded by the ſoul; The tongue is but the ſouls Organ, by which it exerciſeth that Power which God hath given it, and it cannot be ſo well performed, as when the ſoul that directs, performs its work by dictating imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly to it. So that much of the life and ſpirit of Prayer is loſt in praying by forms.</hi> How comes this <hi>concluſion</hi> in, when there was no ſuch thing as <hi>[forms]</hi> in the <hi>Premiſſes?</hi> I have but one ſhift to underſtand the Argument; and that is by ſuppoſing that the ſoul performs not its work by dictating immediatly to the tongue in forms, which is ſo plain a falfity that I am loth to ſuppoſe it. And I cannot imagine what moved theſe men to aſſert it, unleſs it be this, that the words which a man utters in uſing a form are dictated by a Book. That is true, by the Book <hi>mediatly,</hi> but not <hi>immtdiatly,</hi> as they ſay. The Words are firſt in the Book, but they are conceived by the ſoul, and thence dictated before they be uttered by the tongue. Indeed after much ſtudy for their meaning, I fancy at length, that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a greater <hi>Emphaſis</hi> in the word <hi>[directs]</hi> then I was aware of. If ſo, poſſibly this may be their import; That the ſame perſon who contrives the form of a Prayer, is moſt likely to utter it to the beſt advantage: which would be true, if he could contrive as well while he ſpeaks as before he ſpeaks, (becauſe himſelf beſt knows the weight of his own words) but not elſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99541:22"/>
                  <head>SECT. IX.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The fifth branch of their firſt Argument,</hi> viz. [<hi>'Tis</hi> diſputable <hi>whether it be lawful, ſince there is no</hi> precept <hi>or</hi> preſident <hi>for it in the</hi> word] <hi>anſwered,</hi> (1.) Diſputable <hi>actions are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, when commanded.</hi> (2.) <hi>Few Actions are</hi> indiſputable; Non-conformity <hi>is not.</hi> (3.) <hi>We may do what we have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther precept nor example for.</hi> (4.) <hi>There are</hi> General <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands for the uſe of Forms: and</hi> Particular <hi>are not neceſſary; proved from the Miniſters</hi> own <hi>words and deeds.</hi> (5.) <hi>There are</hi> Particular <hi>commands and examples of Forms in Scripture. Their Objection,</hi> [<hi>that the</hi> Liturgy <hi>is not fitted to their</hi> neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities] <hi>anſwered. Three Reaſons for the reſtraining of thoſe in ſome caſes who can pray otherwiſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>I proceed now to the fifth and laſt branch of their firſt reaſon, contained in the eigth chapter of their book. The Paragraph begins thus; <hi>Nay laſtly (to add no more), if there were nothing elſe in the caſe, we ſhould think it very diſputable, whether it be lawful for us in the publick worſhip of God, eſpecially as to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentous acts and parts of it, to do that for which we have no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in the Word, no Preſident or example.</hi> To which objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I have ready no leſſe then <hi>four</hi> anſwers, and the Reader may take which he pleaſeth; for that which will not ſatisfie one man, will another.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt, What though the lawfulneſs of ſuch actions be <hi>diſputable?</hi> they may not therefore be done, when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded? I have proved the contrary, <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. Beſides what I ſaid there, I add now another conſideration. Such is the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the principles which men go by, that there are but few actions that are not <hi>diſputable.</hi> By this Reaſon the Authors have confuted their own non-conformity. For its certainly a a <hi>diſputable</hi> point: ſince many <hi>good</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> men have actually diſputed it to the ſatisfaction of many Readers of the ſame ſtamp; and their Arguments have never been anſwered by their Adverſaries. For all they write, is no anſwer, till they undertake <hi>Hookers Eccleſiaſtical Polity</hi> in the full body, and Dr. <hi>Sanderſons</hi> Sermons with the <hi>Prefaces</hi> thereof.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99541:23"/>2. Secondly, I have already proved, that it is lawful in the publick worſhip of God, yea in the momentous acts and parts thereof, to do that which we have no command, Preſident, or example for in Scripture; as in an <hi>Oath,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thirdly, There is a <hi>General</hi> command for forms of prayer when they are impoſed by the Magiſtrate. For we are enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Scripture to obey our Rulers, when they command ſuch things as Gods word nowhere forbids; and ſuch things are <hi>Forms</hi> in our Caſe. As for a <hi>particular</hi> command or example in Scripture, it is not requiſite by the <hi>Authors</hi> own conceſſions, which they make both in their <hi>deeds</hi> and <hi>words.</hi> For if you obſerve their deeds, they praiſe God in preſcribed forms made by <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rnhold;</hi> whereas <hi>Praiſe</hi> being a part of <hi>Prayer,</hi> there is the ſame Reaſon for <hi>extempore</hi> Hymns as <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore</hi> Petitions. Again, when they viſit the ſick, they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint him not with <hi>Oil:</hi> And yet they ſhall be ſo far from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing a <hi>command</hi> for ſuch a viſitation in Scripture, that they ſhall find the contrary in Saint <hi>James.</hi> If they ſay there is not the ſame Reaſon for that <hi>annointing</hi> now, which was then; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Neither is there the ſame Reaſon for <hi>unpremeditated</hi> prayers now as was then: For now forms are commanded by the Rulers; but according to the Authors opinion, they were not then. But becauſe it is uſual with men to ſay one thing and do another, condemning themſelves in that which they allow; May be this giving of the Queſtion which we find in their <hi>deeds,</hi> will ſeem to be of leſs weight: ſee therefore how they grant it in their <hi>words</hi> too, <hi>Pag.</hi> 73. <hi>Sect.</hi> 9. where they give more then I ask at this time. For I contend only for the lawfulneſs of <hi>doing</hi> things which are not particularly commanded; but there they grant the lawfulneſs of <hi>impoſing</hi> ſuch things: <hi>freely allowing the Magiſtrate a Power to command us to keep the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and commandments of God, and beſides that to do three things</hi> (1.) <hi>To command as in the circumſtances relating to divine Worſhip, to do thoſe things which are generally commanded in the word of God.</hi> Now a Form of Prayer is doubtleſs but a <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of Prayer; and I have proved, that if the Magiſtrate thinks them convenient, Forms are <hi>generally</hi> commanded in Scripture. (2.) <hi>To appoint time and place.</hi> Now, if he can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point a <hi>time</hi> which he thinks moſt convenient, though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would be leſs convenient; and ſo of <hi>place:</hi> I would fain
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99541:23"/> know a reaſon why he may not appoint a <hi>Form,</hi> which he thinks moſt expedient, though poſſibly otherwiſe it would be leſſe expedient. And to appoint to begin at ſuch a time, or to end at ſuch a time, is as really a limitation of the Spirit as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point a Form. (3.) <hi>To appoint ſuch circumſtances, without which the worſhip of God, in the judgement of ordinary reaſon muſt be indecently and diſorderly performed.</hi> Now this <hi>ordinary Reaſon</hi> which they ſpeak of, muſt be either the reaſon of the Magiſtrate, or the reaſon of the people, or both, or neither of them, but that reaſon which is <hi>beſt,</hi> whether of the one or the other. If they mean the reaſon of the people, then the ſenſe is, that the Magiſtrate hath power to appoint ſuch things as the <hi>ſubjects</hi> judge reaſonable, and we thank them for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: if both, we thank them for as much: if they mean that reaſon which is beſt, without reſtraining it to any ſubject; I reply, That reaſon in the <hi>Idea</hi> doth nothing, but only as it is <hi>ſome bodies</hi> reaſon. The <hi>beſt</hi> reaſon hath influence on no mans actions any further then it is apprehended as <hi>beſt.</hi> And except the Magiſtate hath power to command what he apprehendeth moſt agreeable to the <hi>beſt</hi> reaſon; he muſt command what the ſubjects apprehend ſo, or elſe he muſt command nothing at all. Therefore it remaineth, that the reaſon which is to judge what is undecent, is the reaſon of the Magiſtrate; and if he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ſuch things as be undecent, ſo that they be not otherwiſe unlawful, the people muſt ſubmit by the <hi>Authors</hi> own conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Fourthly, There are <hi>particular</hi> commands and examples in Scripture for forms of Prayer. For <hi>Davids Pſalms</hi> are <hi>Prayers:</hi> many of them conſiſt more of Petitions then of Thankſgivings; and ſome of them are expreſly called ſo in their Titles. Yet he appoints theſe Prayers to be uttered by others: <hi>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ting</hi> the perſons that officiate, not only in the ſenſe and matter, but in the phraſe and form; yea not only in the tune but tone, preſcribing the <hi>inſtruments</hi> wherewith they are to be ſung. Indeed the Authors take notice of this Inſtance, and gather from it a clean contrary concluſion. <hi>We cannot but think that the holy Pſalmiſts variety of Prayers (none of which, as to words and phraſes, agre</hi> per omnia <hi>with another) ſheuld rather teach us, when we go to God in prayer, that we ſhould rather take unto us words</hi> de novo, <hi>as God ſhall put them into
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99541:24"/> our hearts,</hi> &amp;c. Mark the argumentation: the fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Prayers were to be prayed over and over again in the ſame words; <hi>Ergo,</hi> we ſhould in every Prayer take words <hi>de novo.</hi> Indeed the <hi>variety</hi> they ſpeak of, ſhews that they did not uſe only <hi>one</hi> form of prayer; but the Liturgy is ſo far from confining us to one, that the greateſt offence that ſome take at it, is that there are ſo many Prayers for the ſame things in divers phraſes. Thus ſome will be pleaſed neither full nor faſting, I might add to this Inſtance of <hi>Davids Pſalms</hi> another in the Propnet <hi>Hoſea,</hi> chap. 14. v. 2. <hi>Take with you words, and turn unto the Lord, and ſay unto him,</hi> &amp;c. and another in <hi>Joel</hi> 2.17. <hi>Let the Prieſts, the Miniſters of the Lord, weep between the porch and the Altar; and let them ſay, Spare thy people, O Lord,</hi> &amp;c. It is frivolous to object, that this is the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>Directory;</hi> themſelves, I believe, laugh at ſuch a conceit in the <hi>Antinomians;</hi> Yea they argue for their <hi>own</hi> purpoſe from the variety of phraſe in theſe Prayers, as hath been noted. But if any require a new Teſtament example or command, we <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably</hi> have both, I am <hi>ſure</hi> one. For, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.24. we have a <hi>preſident,</hi> which in probability without any ſtretching will come home to our caſe. For we find there a whole company of the Primitive Chriſtans in conſort with the Apoſtles themſelves, <hi>lifting up their voyce with one accord, and ſaying</hi> a Prayer, which is there regiſtered in its terms. If it be ſaid, that the form was not compoſed before-hand, but that they all lighted upon the ſame words by <hi>inſpiration;</hi> this is more then any man knows; however it will juſtifie the joyning of <hi>voyces</hi> as well as <hi>hearts</hi> in prayer. Beſide this probable example, we have a particular precept for the uſe of one form, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.2. <hi>When you pray, ſay, Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. as will better appear in its proper place, where I ſhall cite their own words in the 55. page of their book, <hi>We doubt not but we may uſe it in the form:</hi> For b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this Reaſon of theirs under conſideration, they might not uſe it, except they had a command for it in the Word of God.</p>
                  <p>The next thing to be obſerved, is that <hi>Periphaſis</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they would diſparge the uſe of Forms, calling it a <hi>borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of words from others, hardly fitted to their hearts or preſent neceſſities.</hi> Whether the Liturgy be fitted to their hearts, I cannot tell, becauſe I know not their hearts. But if their hearts be as they ſhould be, the Prayers there cannot but be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99541:24"/> to their hearts; the matter of the petitions being only ſuch things as every Engliſhman ſhould deſire. But if they would have every man utter that in prayer, which is ſet upon his own heart (as the phraſe is) whether reaſonably or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonably, there would be mad work. And I wonder how the ſaid Prayers ſhould not be fitted to their <hi>neceſſities,</hi> ſince they ask all good things. Indeed ſome men have more neceſſities then others, and the Liturgy will not fit them; which no doubt did much help to bring it into diſcredit, becauſe it would not ſerve on faſt-dayes in the late wars, to beg thoſe victories, which were accounted the one thing <hi>neceſſary</hi> by ſome men. And yet were it granted that it did not fit the heart and neceſſities of the Miniſter, ſo well as a Prayer of his own invention; yet poſſibly it may better fit the peoples; and a Miniſter is to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate both his Prayers and Sermons rather to his peoples hearts and neceſſities then his own. For (unleſſe he be like one of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Prieſts) if he ſhould preach upon thoſe points which ſometimes are moſt material to be preſſed on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and in that way which is moſt effectual and prevalent upon his own more learned Soul, it would have but ſmall ſucceſſe among the moſt of his hearers.</p>
                  <p>They conclude the Chapter to this purpoſe in many words, too long to be here inſerted: <hi>That if ſtinted forms be allowed for ſome that canne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> pray otherwiſe, yet it is not lawful, much leſſe neceſſary, for their ſakes to reſtrain the abilities of thoſe others that can.</hi> As for the <hi>lawfulneſſe</hi> of reſtraining a gift, when ſuch a reſtraint is judged uſeful, I have proved it before. As for the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of it to ſome end intended, it will appear in three caſes. (1.) In caſe <hi>uniformity</hi> is aimed at. If the Captain will have his Souldiers keep their ranks, he muſt forbid the ſound to out-march the lame. (2.) In caſe liberty grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſome to do that which they have a gift for, will provoke others which have it not, to imitate them beyond their ability. Thus the way to make <hi>mean</hi> men not to wear <hi>gold lace</hi> to the empoveriſhing of their eſtates, is for <hi>great</hi> men to leave it of. And thus the way to keep weak Miniſters from <hi>extemporiſing</hi> beyond their power, is for more able men to uſe the Common-prayer. For if the denyal of liberty to ſome who have the gift for the ſakes of thoſe their brethren which have it not, be to cut the man fit for the bed; the granting ſuch a liberty
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99541:25"/> will be to <hi>ſtretch</hi> a man fit for the bed, that I may retort the Authors ſimilitude. Now ſince both will needs lie together, it is more equitable that the tall man pull up his legs, then that the low man be put on the Rack. (3.) In caſe liberty given to an Officer to do ſomething he hath a gift for, and the denial of that liberty to another Officer of the ſame ſociety, which hath no ſuch ability, but cannot be ſpared any more then the former, would make the weaker Officer contemptible and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, eſpecially if he be the weaker only in that particular, but the ſtronger in others. In <hi>our</hi> caſe, one Miniſter having ſpent more time in hearing the Sermons and Prayers of others, or brought up from his childhood to make his Prayers himſelf, or living among people which applaud <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers, and ſo excite his invention, hath got the knack of ſuch Prayers; but by this reaſon is not ſo well ſtudied, ſo ſolid, and judicious, nor ſo able to contrive a diſcourſe upon premeditation: Another having been taught from his childhood to pray by a book, and afterward having exerciſed himſelf alone in reading and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating of deep points, rather then abroad in hearing popular harangues, prayers and preachments; or laſtly, living among a people which are more affected and edified by the prayers of the Church, and ſo giving no encouragement to labour for the <hi>extempore</hi> faculty, comes to have but little of it; yet is as needful an Officer as the other, more able to oppoſe gain-ſayers, to regulate Church affairs, and to make a ſpeech to the people on any occcaſion, if you give him time to contrive, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to memory what he hath ſo contrived. Should this <hi>lattter</hi> Miniſter be rendered <hi>contemptible,</hi> and ſo far uſeleſſe in his place, by anothers liberty to uſe his <hi>extempore gift?</hi> But that the <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> by this means is in danger to become <hi>contemptible</hi> among ſilly and ſelf-conceited people, is plain by experience, and aſſerted many times by the Authors in their book: And much more would it be ſo, if he ſhould be publickly prohibited, and others allowed. And ſo much for the Authors firſt Reaſon in their eighth Chapter, which is levelled againſt <hi>ſtinted forms in general.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99541:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Miniſters</hi> ſecond Reaſon [<hi>that theſe</hi> Forms <hi>have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed by having been uſed in an Idolatrous ſervice</hi>] <hi>eventila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. A man may do that about and in the worſhip of God, which hath been done in an</hi> Idolatrous <hi>worſhip, proved. The groſs Idolatry of certain Non-conformiſts, pollutes not their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary expreſſions.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ninth Chapter contain their ſecond Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which goes on ſuppoſition, that it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to uſe <hi>ſome forms</hi> of Prayer, but denies it of the Engliſh <hi>Liturgy.</hi> It is <hi>drawn</hi> (as the Title of the Chapter tells us) <hi>from the diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs of the lawfulneſs of uſing any forms of humane compoſure, formerly defiled by uſe in an Idolatrous ſervice, conjoyned with the ſcandal of many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ariſing upon that account.</hi> But that I may not conceal the ſtrength of their Argument, but bring it into view in the full body, before I oppoſe it; I ſhall put it down firſt as it is word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not only in the title, but in the Chapter it ſelf. Their termes are theſe; <hi>We cannot but have ſome doubts, whether it be lawfull for us in the worſhip of God, by an act of ours, to offer up any thing to God (of meer humane compoſition) which hath been once of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in an Idolatrous ſervice, eſpecially when our Brethren ſay unto us, This hath been ſo offered. That the worſhip of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is idolatrous, we hope no ſober Proteſtant will deny: Their veneration of Images, adoration of the Euchariſt, invocation of the Saints, are all idolatrous. Some of theſe are done as oft as their Maſs-book is uſed; ſo that their worſhip,</hi> toties quoties, <hi>as it is performed is idolatrous, though not in every
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99541:26"/> part, yet in the complex.</hi> To make up the Argument, it muſt be ſuppoſed, that ſome of the Prayers in the Liturgy are taken out or the Maſs-book; which may be true for ought I know, and therefore I ſhall anſwer on that ſuppoſition. (1.) I wonder wherefore that <hi>Parentheſis</hi> is cram'd in <hi>[of meer humane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition].</hi> For when they come to give an inſtance out of Scripture, they make it in <hi>Fleſh</hi> offered to Idols. Now I never heard that fleſh was of meer humane compoſition. If the Authors have an art to make fleſh by meer humane power, they have more then the <hi>Tranſubſtantiating</hi> Maſſe-Prieſt pretends to, and would do well to teach it the world againſt a Famine. (2.) They ſay only, that they <hi>have ſome doubts</hi> about the Queſtion; but I have proved already that a meer <hi>doubt</hi> is to be over-born by the certain in junctions of lawful Authority. And beſides that which here they doubt, themſelves affirm elſewhere, if they know the meaning of their own words. As page 63. <hi>The reverend Perſons, which had an hand in compoſing the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, did worthily in their Generation.</hi> I wonder how they can be ſaid to do worthily in impoſing this Liturgy, if it be unlawful, unleſſe they mean only, that they did not all out ſo wickedly as their Predeceſſors, which impoſed the Maſſe: But by that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he that murders a <hi>ſtranger,</hi> doth worthily, becauſe others murder their <hi>Parents.</hi> The ſame confeſſion is made by them page 65. <hi>Certainly thoſe firſt Reformers did like wiſe and pious men.</hi> It is true, they put in, <hi>With reſpect to their age.</hi> But is it the part of a wiſe and pious man <hi>in any age,</hi> to impoſe ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as are unlawful? Again in the ſame page, <hi>Their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was excellent as to thoſe times.</hi> So it ſeems by what they ſay in both places, that it is a piece of an excellent judgement in ſome times to command men to ſin. But (3.) To let this paſſe, and proceed to the main ſtrength of their Reaſon. Their <hi>Criticiſme</hi> about the term <hi>[to offer]</hi> ſhall be conſidered in its place. In the mean time I will ſuppoſe the ſenſe of their words to be this, That a man may not do ſuch things relating to the worſhip of God, as means, inſtruments, modes, or formes, which have been ſo done in an idolatrous worſhip, <hi>i. e.</hi> a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip whereof ſome parts are idolatrouſly performed. This I deny, and I give inſtances of my denyal. The love of money is idolatry; and the covetous actions done out of love to it, and to procure its aſſiſtance, are not only mixed with idolatrous
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99541:26"/> actions, (as in the preſent caſe) but themſelves are idolatrous, Yet we may do ſuch actions to teſtifie our reſpects to God and to win his preſence; at covetous men do out of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to <hi>Mammon,</hi> and to procure his preſence. That is, we may faſt, we may watch, we may go to Church as duly as they to the Exchange; we may think of God, and talk of him, as they do of their money, we may ſay, that he anſwereth all things; we may lay out upon charitable works, as they do on a good bargain. Yea (to prevent an Objection) theſe things we might do if God did never command them. For what can be ſaid againſt them? Are they not good? have they not a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural tendency to expreſſe our love to God, and to procure his gracious preſence with us? What though theſe actions were done to a falſe God, to whom they were not due? may they not be done to a true God, to whom they are due? And for the <hi>Ferm</hi> of thoſe actions, we may uſe that which we think beſt, though uſed by the ſaid Idolaters; as to faſt from dinner, or ſupper, to riſe early, or go to bed late, to lay out our ſtock in alms, in money, or mony worth. In like manner, look what actions the Glutton doth in the ſervice of his god, which is his belly, many of the like actions we may do in the ſervice of the true God. Again, there be others which do not indeed worſhip the true God <hi>before</hi> an Image, as the Papiſts, but they worſhip an Image it ſelf of their own framing, and that a moſt deformed one, and not ſo like God at a piece of bread, wood, or ſtone, or a glorified Saint, the objects of Popiſh worſhip. The God of ſome men is a cruel, unnatural thing, like <hi>Saturn,</hi> who devoured his own children; only herein more ugly, that he begets them on purpoſe to devoure them. The God of others, yea of many the ſame, is a fond thing like <hi>Cupid,</hi> taking no notice of the ſins of his darlings. The God of others, yea of many the ſame, is a wicked thing, infallibly neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by his Decree, and powerfully inſtigating them by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the lewdeſt actions. The God of others, yea of many the ſame, is a falſe thing, making great and precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, but maintaining an infinite malice and hatred in his heart. Now theſe Idolaters (the groſſeſt that ever I read of) have many times pretty phraſes in their Prayers: yet ſome, who would bring the like Argument with the Authors againſt the Liturgy, are ſo far from abominating thoſe phraſes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99541:27"/> upon this account, that they affect them; they are worn thred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare in every Pulpit;
<q>Notior in coelis fabula nulla fuit.</q> And I doubt not, but it is very lawful to uſe ſome of thoſe forms of words in prayer to the true God, which theſe Idolaters uſe to their falſe Gods. Ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> I beleive theſe men do not think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Idolaters; no more do the Papiſts: But ſuppoſing the opinions of them both, that which they both do, is conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially idolatrous; They both do diſown the idolatry which is conſequent upon their doctrines; but they both maintain their own opinions which infer the idolatry. The worſt opinion, which the Papiſts are ſaid to hold in reference to idolatry, is, that Bread is God, and therefore to be worſhipped: And the others are ſaid to hold, that ſomething worſe then the moſt courſe or mouldy bread, is God, and therefore to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. And in truth the Papiſts opinion, and conſequently their practice thereupon, is much more tolerable of the two: For they cannot have an higher opinion of the bread, then of the humane nature of Chriſt in the <hi>concrete,</hi> which (though God he predicated of it by vertue of the hypoſtatical union, yet) is but a means to bring us to God, that God may be all in all, and therefore cannot <hi>terminate</hi> our worſhip. But now the worſhip of the others is <hi>terminated</hi> ultimately and laſtly upon that monſtrous Image, which they call God. Which things, and many more that might be alledged, being conſidered, I cannot much wonder, that though the worſhip of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> be cryed down as idolatrous and ſuperſtitions, yet ſome give this Reaſon, wherefore their judgements cannot ſide with the oppoſite party, namely, becauſe of the <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> and <hi>ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> which abounds among them: For that it is among ſome of them, I am as confident as I am that it is among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99541:27"/>
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>By their Reaſon the</hi> Scriptures <hi>would be defiled; and the Papiſts might pollute the moſt</hi> darling <hi>phraſes of unprepared Prayers. The</hi> Lords Prayer <hi>as much polluted by Idolaters as the</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer. <hi>Such Prayers as are not</hi> contrary <hi>to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, are as incapable of defilement as the Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſuch are thoſe of the Liturgy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THey next go about to anſwer an Objection againſt this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of theirs, which they quote from Doctor <hi>Cauſabon</hi> on the <hi>Lords Prayer:</hi> Their words are theſe; <hi>We are not ſo ſilly us to think that the holy Scriptures (dictated by the Spirit of God) or any thing elſe of purely divine inſtitution is capable of corruptions, and therefore cannot but with ſome laughter read the Argumentations of them, who argue, that if we reject the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy becauſe the idolatrous Papiſts uſed it, we muſt alſo refuſe the Scriptures and the Lords Prayer. Theſe are but toyes to blind common people,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The holy Scriptures are uncapable of pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by any idolatrous ſervice.</hi> By this it appears, that it is not the meer uſing of a form of words in an idolatrous ſervice, which makes it unlawful to be uſed in the ſervice of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Authors except the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> otherwiſe they know, <hi>A quatenus ad de omni valeret conſequentia.</hi> I ſay (if a man may underſtand their mind by their words) they mean not, that ſuch an <hi>uſe</hi> renders it unlawful; but that <hi>corruption</hi> and <hi>pollution</hi> which is contracted by ſuch an uſe to phraſes of humane invention, though not to <hi>Scripture</hi> phraſes. And now they had done their work, if they had but proved, that a true propoſition, if not in Scripture, is polluted by uſing it in idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſervices any more, then a propoſition of like truth in Scripture; or that Churches, Bels, Fonts, Pews, praying with a book, and preaching without book, are any more polluted by ſuch an uſage, then the Lords Prayer, Baptiſme, or the Euchariſt. It will (I believe) be beyond their power to prove ſuch a vaſt difference between things of <hi>divine inſtitution</hi> and humane. I am ſure, that though the Temple was of <hi>divine inſtitution,</hi> yet it might have been defiled by bringing an Idol into it, much more then the cart could, on which the Idol was brought, which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99541:28"/> could pretend to no more divine inſtitution then that of the <hi>wheelwright.</hi> In like manner, if a man ſhould take the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wine of the Communion, carry it into the Ale-houſe, &amp; there make himſelf drunk with it, the wine which is of divine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is (one would think more, but at leaſt) as much polluted by the ſaid drunkenneſſe, as the Ale-houſe can be, yea as much as other wine not conſecrated could be. In ſome caſes things of divine Inſtitution are ſo far from being priviledged from pollution above things of humane inſtitution, that indeed the priviledge lies more on the other ſide, as the pureſt white is capable of moſt fouling; and as that which pollutes a Miniſter, pollutes not another man. The Authors ſhould have told us what they mean by that <hi>pollution of words and phraſes</hi> which they ſay is effected by uſing them in an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous ſervice, though they were otherwiſe never ſo good. Do they mean ſuch a pollution as is deſcribed in the Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Law? No ſure: For they never read there, that he who hath ſpoken any words uſed by Idolaters in their worſhip, ſhould waſh his tongue, and be unclean till the Even. What pollution is it then, that by a kind of <hi>Theomagical</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion is contracted by good words and ſentences from the Idolatrous ſervices wherein they were uſed: when in the mean time the words of Scripture, having been in the ſame infected houſe, eſcape ſound, entire, and untainted? Indeed if words be <hi>abuſed</hi> to a bad end, or if they ſhould chance to be forbid to be uſed to ſome perſons by a <hi>poſitive</hi> command, in both theſe caſes I could allow to call them figuratively <hi>corrupted</hi> and <hi>pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> But this pollution is no ſuch pollution as makes the uſe of thoſe words unlawful to all perſons. For the Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are ſometimes thus polluted both theſe ways. Its as certain that they are ſometimes abuſed to a bad end, as that they may be uſed to an excellent end: And the Authors themſelves tell us, <hi>pag.</hi> 67. that <hi>[Baali]</hi> was a name applied to the true God by himſelf, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.5. Yet this word was polluted by abuſing it to a bad end, and by a poſitive command not to uſe it, Hoſ. 2.16. <hi>Thou ſhalt call me no more</hi> Baali; ſo that forms of Scripture are capable of corruption and pollution, as well as forms of humane invention: and therefore the Authors diſtinction hinders not the Argument, which they thought to have avoided by it from returning again upon them in its
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99541:28"/> full ſtrength. If they mean ſome other kind of pollution, which I cannt conjecture; a kind by it ſelf, which contrary to the method and courſe of its fellows chuſeth not to infect the moſt refined and delicate, but rather the more groſs and feculent conſtitutions: I can ſay nothing of it till they tell me what that ſtrange pollution is. For my part, I can at preſent imagine no other pollutions, which words that are true and good, are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, beſides thoſe which I have named; to which the phraſes of Scripture have been ſhewn obnoxious as well as others. I know good ſpeeches have been rendered nauſeous by a bad ſpeaker; and therefore they have been ſometimes put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a good mans mouth to make them more acceptable: But the diſliking of good ſayings when uttered by bad men, is not grounded upon reaſon but weakneſs. For in truth they are worthy of the more acceptation upon that account, as when the Devil confeſſed our Saviour; ſince that is a moſt evident truth which extorts a confeſſion from the Adverſarie. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what the Apoſtle ſaith. That <hi>to the pure all things are pure;</hi> and <hi>Every creature of God is good, and nothing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed.</hi> The Papiſts might if they would, ſpoil all the quaint and trite phraſes of <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers, if <hi>their</hi> uſe of them ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them <hi>impure,</hi> and to be <hi>refuſed.</hi> If when the Authors ſay that words are polluted, they mean only that they are <hi>rendred unlawful to be uſed;</hi> then they beg the Queſtion in their <hi>Reaſon,</hi> diſpute in a circle, and their Argument runs round: The Liturgy may not be uſed, becauſe it is polluted, <hi>i. e.</hi> becauſe it may not be uſed. Therefore I conceive, that they mean ſuch a pollution as I have granted competible to words: But then they are out in affirming that <hi>Scripture</hi> cannot be ſo polluted. And the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> wil come into the ſame condemnation, which is by name exempted by them from the ſaid pollution. Yea, though it were granted that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture could not be polluted, yet the uſe of the Lords Prayer as a Form of <hi>words,</hi> and not meerly of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> would be pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their Reaſon. For though the Lords Prayer be a part of Scripture, yet ſince they will not grant that it was appointed by the Scripture to be uſed as a Form of words in Prayer, it muſt needs follow by their Reaſon that we may not uſe it as a Form, becauſe the Papiſts did ſo. For though the form of words be not polluted, yet the uſe of them as a form of Prayer
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99541:29"/> muſt be polluted according to their opinions, as much as the ſign of the croſs. Again (that I may overthrow their Reply to Dr. <hi>Cauſabon</hi> another way) ſince the deceit which lurks in generals, is diſcovered in particulars, let us put a caſe. The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſaith, <hi>God is rich to all that call upon him.</hi> If the Maſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book had this Prayer, <hi>Be thou Lord, rich to all that call upon thee,</hi> I ask whether this Prayer be polluted by being in the Maſs book. When they ſay it is polluted, I muſt deal with them another way: in the mean time let us charitably ſuppoſe that they are not ſo abſurd, but will grant that this prayer is <hi>not</hi> polluted, thought it were in the Maſs book; and that their Reaſon is, becauſe this prayer conſiſts of Scripture Phraſe. This anſwer being ſuppoſed, I reply thus: Indeed ſome of the <hi>ſingle terms</hi> of the Propoſition are in the Scripture I quoted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; But the words ſo put together in this <hi>form</hi> are not. For in Scripture the Verb ſubſtantive is of the <hi>Indicative</hi> Mood, in the prayer of the <hi>Imperative;</hi> In the Scripture it is of the <hi>third</hi> Perſon, in the Prayer of the <hi>ſecond.</hi> Now if the Maſs-book defiles not a ſentence, in which the ſingle words (which are the Elements of a ſentence) are ſo joyned together as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in Scripture; why ſhould any man imagine that the Maſs-book can defile a word, wherein the Syllables and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (which are the Elements of a word) are ſo put together as they are nowhere in Scripture? Beſides, if they ſay it is ſufficient to keep a Petition from the pollution of the Maſs, that the words be Scripture-words, though found together no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in Scripture in that form of conſtruction wherein they ſtand in the Petition; I anſwer, that in ſaying ſo they juſtifie the Liturgy. For I do not think, there is a prayer there, the ſingle terms whereof (and ſometimes whole enunciations) are not to be found in Scripture, excepting when ſome particular Perſons or Offices are prayed for: And yet ſure a man might pray for the ſaid perſons and offices by the ſame names, though they were ſo termed in the Maſs book. Once more, This Petition <hi>[Forgive us our treſpaſſes]</hi> is Scripture; not only in the ſimple terms, but alſo in the form of the Propoſition: and therefore if there be any ſentences which can eſcape the profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Maſs-book, this muſt be one by their Reaſon. But I challenge any man to give a ſatisfactory Reaſon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Propoſition cannot be polluted, by the Maſs-book
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99541:29"/> as eaſily as any of theſe I ſhall name: <hi>[Let our iniquities be pardoned by thee]</hi> or, <hi>[acquit us from the guilt of our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions]</hi> or, <hi>condemn us not for our ſins]</hi> or any other the like, which ſpeak the ſame ſenſe, though they be not found word for word in Scripture. I conclude therefore, ſince the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors confeſs that the Scriptures cannot be polluted by mens uſing them in an Idolatrous ſervice; and ſince I have proved that ſuch Prayers whoſe ſenſe keeps an harmony with that of Scripture, are as uncapable of pollution as the Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: if it be but further granted, that the Prayers of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy in their <hi>ſenſe</hi> do agree with the Scriptures (which I here affirm, and ſhall make good when called thereto) it muſt needs follow that the prayers of the Liturgy remain unpolluted, though they had been uſed in an Idolatrous worſhip, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently may be lawfully uſed in the ſervice of the true God, which will further appear in the next Section.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Miniſters Reaſon its unlawful to uſe</hi> Churches <hi>for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip, built in time of Popery. The impertinency of their Anſwer,</hi> that Churches are not offered up to God. <hi>Churches are</hi> offered <hi>as truly as</hi> Words. <hi>Yea upon their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Churches may be put to no uſe at all, proved by the caſe of</hi> Meats <hi>offered to</hi> Idols.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>I Have ſhewed how ill they can juſtifie the uſe of <hi>Scripture</hi>-phraſes themſelves in prayer, if that phraſes of <hi>humane</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition are ſo polluted by the Papiſts uſe of them, that a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant may not uſe them. The ſame may be eaſily demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated concerning the uſe of ſuch <hi>Churches</hi> as were dedicated in the Raign of Popery, and then uſed not only in the <hi>pure parts</hi> of that worſhip which the Authors by the Verdict of a moſt partial <hi>Synecdoche</hi> call idolatrous in the <hi>complex</hi> (which yet is the worſt that they ſay againſt the Liturgy) but even in the very <hi>Idolatrous parts</hi> themſelves, yea ſome of them in the celebration of the Ethnick Myſteries before Chriſtianity viſited our Iland. Let us hear now how they can uſe theſe Churches in the reformed worſhip of the true God, while they ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the grounds they have laid down in this Chapter. That
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:99541:30"/> which they ſay upon this point, is word for word as followeth. <hi>Their Anſwer is ſilly, who tell us, that then we muſt uſe none of our Churches. When we offer up Churches to God by any rational act, we will conſider of this frivolous anſwer; which indeed may concern them which dream of an holineſs in them by reaſon of dedication or the like: It concerns not us, which only uſe them as convenient places, in which we meet to ſerve God,</hi> &amp;c. The ſum of this anſwer is clearly this, that the Authors do not <hi>offer</hi> Churches to God, as they ſhould do words if they uſed the Common-prayer; and that they account no <hi>holineſs</hi> to be in Churches, as they account in the words wherewith they utter their Prayers. And ſo the Anſwer implies alſo, that what things have been offered in idolatrous worſhip, may be <hi>uſed</hi> in right worſhip, but not <hi>offered</hi> to God. But I wonder how the <hi>words</hi> that are uſed in vocal Prayer, are offered to God any more then <hi>Churches.</hi> It is our affections, and more directly our deſires, that are offered to God in Prayer: The words are only means and inſtruments to ſignifie theſe deſires before men, or to excite them to concur in the ſame deſires. And the fitteſt and beſt words are but the fitteſt and beſt means and inſtruments; and ſo the words are rather the <hi>cenſers</hi> then the <hi>incenſe.</hi> If we can be ſaid properly to offer words to God, we muſt offer him the <hi>Air;</hi> or elſe we only offer a bodily quality without the ſubject, a meer articulate motion of the Air. But if words are ſaid to be offered, becauſe they are means and inſtruments uſed about the offering; then Churches may be ſaid to be offered too, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing likewiſe fit means and inſtruments to the ſame purpoſe, though another way. For doth not the builder of Churches ſignifie his deſire, that God may be worſhipped? And is not a Church, when built, a means to unite many in the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires? And is not the moſt fit and convenient Church the moſt fit and convenient means, as I ſaid before of words? And why are not Churches <hi>holy,</hi> as much as phraſes and forms of words that are uſed in prayer? Is not holineſſe a ſeparation from a common uſe to a ſacred and religious uſe? And are not Churches as much ſet apart for prayer as words be? If not, the more is the pity and ſhame. But whether the Authors <hi>dedicate, offer,</hi> or place any <hi>holineſs</hi> in Churches, or no, it is nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (though they think the Argument concerns not them till they do): For whoſoever ſhall conſider their ſecond Reaſon
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99541:30"/> (as it is explained, paralleld, and proved in this Chapter) will eaſily diſcern that by that by that Reaſon it is unlawful for them not only to offer, dedicate, or place holineſſe in them, but even to make uſe of them to thoſe ends, for which they have a fitneſſe, either of their own nature, or by inſtitution; ſo that they may not pray or preach in them, yea they may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them into ſtables, or priſons, which the Authors make more tolerable then to dedicate them to God. Now that their reaſon forbids them as much to make a <hi>common</hi> and <hi>natural</hi> uſe of Churches, as <hi>ſacred,</hi> it appears by that caſe put by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which they imagine to be <hi>parallel</hi> to theirs. He reſolves that the meat which a man was told was offered to Idols, ſhould not be eaten. The Authors think the Analogy of his determination makes it unlawful to pray to God with ſuch forms of words that were uſed in an idolatrous ſervice. Their Oppoſites to drive them from this abſurdity, put another caſe (as like to the firſt as the ſecond is, and more too) and ſay, that by the ſame reaſon it were unlawful to uſe Churches that have been uſed in an idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſervice. The Authors reply, that the ſecond and third caſe are not alike: for they <hi>offer</hi> words in prayer, but they do not <hi>offer</hi> Churches to God. Now let it be granted them, that the third caſe is not like the ſecond; that is not material; Is not the third as like the firſt as the ſecond is? Yea the caſe of <hi>Churches</hi> is more like to the caſe of <hi>meats offered to Idols</hi> (which is the firſt and ruling caſe put by Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) then the caſe of the Liturgy is. They ſay the proportion fails, becauſe they offer <hi>words</hi> to God, but not <hi>Churches.</hi> Let it be granted; Yet on which ſide doth the proportion fail? Not in the caſe of <hi>Churches,</hi> but of <hi>words.</hi> The Authors ſay, they <hi>offer</hi> words to God: and therefore what hath that caſe to do with Saint <hi>Pauls?</hi> in which it is not queſtioned, whether meat offered to Idols might be <hi>offered to God,</hi> but whether it might be <hi>naturally</hi> and <hi>commonly</hi> uſed and <hi>eaten</hi> for a mans <hi>dinner.</hi> But now the caſe of Churches is more exactly like to that of St. <hi>Pauls:</hi> For he ſpeaks not of offering meat to God, but of uſing it accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his kind; and therefore by the Authors reaſon it ſhould forbid not only the offering of the ſaid Churches to God, but the uſing them according to their kind. Therefore it is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to diſpute, whether Churches are offered to God, by the <hi>Authors,</hi> as much as Prayers: We are only to conſider, whether
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99541:31"/> Churches were offered to God by the ſaid <hi>Idolaters</hi> as much as Prayers, that is, the words uſed in prayer. And we ſhall find, that Churches were more conſecrated to God, by the ſaid ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous worſhippers, then the words of their Prayers. For they accounted it ſacriledge to take away the leaſt part of a <hi>Church,</hi> and to divert it to a common uſe; but themſelves uſed many of thoſe words about their common buſineſſes, which they uſed in their Prayers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Another conſideration of theirs,</hi> viz. [<hi>That we might provide other forms not uſed by <hi>Idolaters</hi>] anſwered. The miſchiefs of an</hi> affected <hi>running from the</hi> Papiſts. <hi>What diſtinguiſheth a true</hi> Catholick <hi>from a Papiſt: Not phraſes, tones, habits, and geſture; but a greater Humility, Charity, and</hi> Freedom <hi>of ſpirit. No reaſon but a man may offer the ſame to God, which had been offered to an</hi> Idol.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>IN the two immediately foregoing Sections I have made it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that while the Authors labour to extricate themſelves out of the ſtringent nooſes of their Oppoſites retortion, they have only more intricatly involved and entangled themſelves. It is time now to proceed in my animadverſions to the next <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph</hi> of their Chapter under debate, in which they explain their fore-cited Reaſon in other words, and enlarge it with one conſideration not hinted by them before, <hi>viz:</hi> that there be other forms of prayer to be had beſide thoſe uſed by Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Their words are theſe exactly; <hi>Prayer is a piece of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-ſacrifice, and by a Rational act of our ſouls to be offered to God. Now whether it be lawful for us, when the earth is the Lords and the fulneſs thereof, whereas God hath given us an abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to ſpeak words in another form, to take-thoſe very forms, and to offer them up to God in true Goſpel-worſhip, which have been offered in an idolatrous ſervice (though the matter of thoſe forms be not idolatrous) is to us a great doubt, nor can we be ſatisfied in the lawfulneſs of it.</hi> This affectation of uſing diverſity of phraſe from the Papiſts, I never ſaw pleaded for before, but have often obſerved to be practiſed to my ſorrow. For ſome men
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99541:31"/> labouring to get far enough from the Papiſts in their <hi>Dialect,</hi> have ſpoken like Turks in point of mans <hi>will,</hi> and like <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> and <hi>Libertines</hi> in point of good <hi>works.</hi> But the true <hi>Catholick</hi> Chriſtian can approve a good ſaying, whoever be the ſpeaker, and will behave himſelf to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> to the <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans;</hi> who, though he was a <hi>Stoick,</hi> confeſſeth he borrowed many things from <hi>Epicurus,</hi> and gives this reaſon, becauſe he could call truth his own, though he found it in the enemies camp, and under the enemies colours. The true <hi>Shibboleth,</hi> which muſt diſtinguiſh a true <hi>Catholick</hi> from a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and all other <hi>Hereticks,</hi> is not words and phraſes, tones, countenances, habits, and geſtures, by which characters Popery is uſually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined and diſtinguiſhed among us; but it is a greater Humility, Charity and <hi>Freedom</hi> of ſpirit. And that the Papiſts and other Hereticks may ſee that we differ from them, and place the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of our Religion in theſe excellent, uncontrovertible, and moſt material points; I with with all my heart, that our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and phraſe were as like to theirs, as truly and lawfully may be, provided we ſtill retain our Chriſtian liberty of vary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from them. For if the words and forms of prayer, which they uſe, be in themſelves true and good, it is not their uſing them which can make them unlawful, notwithſtanding what I have newly quoted to the contrary. For what though prayer be a piece of <hi>Goſpel ſacrifice,</hi> &amp;c.? ſo are our bodies, ſo are our eſtates, and both to be <hi>offered to God by a rational act of our ſouls.</hi> Suppoſe then that my right knee hath bowed to an Idol, upon my converſion muſt not I bow to the true God with that knee, ſeeing I have another, but only with my left? Surely I ſhould uſe that knee to chuſe in Gods worſhip, which had been defiled in the ſervice of Idols. Again in point of <hi>Alms,</hi> which is no leſſe <hi>a piece of Goſpel-ſacrifice to be offered to God by a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal act of our ſouls,</hi> then prayer is; may not a man give that money to the poor, which he knoweth hath been offered to a falſe God, or to the true God in an idolatrous ſervice? When the Temples of the Pagans were in many places demoliſhed, might not the Emperour as well, yea much better, have given the gold and ſilver, that was found there conſecrated to Idols, unto the poor, then have employed it about the uſe of his Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace or the affairs of State? But ſince I ſee this Reaſon on foot, I leſſe wonder, that thoſe who had the Revenues of the Church
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99541:32"/> ſo long in their hands, did ſo little good with them. May be they thought that they had been offered to an Idol before, and therefore ought not to be given to the true God, but to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Nehuſhtan,</hi> and condemned to the baſe ſervice of their belly. I ſhall conclude my notes on the laſt quoted paſſage with one more Inſtance of common practice, which I hope the Authors themſelves allow of, though it be <hi>vertually</hi> condemned by the Reaſon which they alledge. Who the Authors of the Book are, I know not, nor what their way is. But I am ſure others of their mind in point of non-conformity, will uſe ſome ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of the Common-prayer in their <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers, as, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat Gods ſervice is perfect freedom,</hi> and the like. Now if a whole Prayer be defiled by the Papiſts uſe of it, every part of it muſt be ſo defiled. If they ſay, that they uſe no Sentences in their prayers, which have been uſed by Idolaters in theirs, excepting ſuch as are agreeable to the Scriptures; I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them to ſhew what ſentence of a Prayer in the Liturgy is not agreeable to the Scriptures; and when they have ſhewn that, I yield them the cauſe. But their preſent reaſon argues againſt the lawfulneſſe of uſing ſuch forms of words, which themſelves confeſſe are for the matter of them true and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Scriptures.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Their Argument from</hi> 1 Cor. 10. <hi>about Meats offered to Idols anſwered. Several Reaſons why</hi> Forms <hi>of prayer can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be liable to thoſe pollutions, which</hi> thoſe meats <hi>were.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THeſe confeſſed abſurdities following from their aſſertion, let us now ſee upon what grounds it is built; to which end I ſhall here tranſcribe their next words. <hi>The ground of our ſcruple is in that known Text,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. <hi>where the Apoſtle treateth concerning the lawfulneſſe of eating meats that had been once offered to Idols. He determines as to a double caſe.</hi> (1.) <hi>That it is not lawful to eat ſuch meats in an Idols Temple.</hi> (2.) <hi>In caſe it be ſold in the ſhambles, and we know it not, he determines that we may buy and eat it. But in caſe our Brother ſaith unto us, This hath been offered to an Idol; he ſaith, eat it not: ſo that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99541:32"/> our Brothers ſcandal upon ſuch a foundation is to be avoided by us. He gives the Reaſon, becauſe there is other meat to eat. The earth is the Lords and the fulneſſe thereof.</hi> Here they interweave an Argument from ſcandal with that they have been ſo long upon, drawn from the unlawfulneſſe of offering that to God, which had been offered to Idols. I ſhall conſider the caſe of ſcandal by it ſelf in the next Chapter. For they are two Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, though the Authors obſerving (its likely) the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of each of them, confound them together in theſe words. But I ſhall diſtinguiſh them in my anſwer; ſince if neither of them is of force ſingly, they cannot be of force conjunctly. For if the Common-prayer may not be uſed becauſe it hath been polluted by the known uſe of it in an idolatrous ſervice (as they have ſpent a whole leaf to prove already, without menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning ſcandal) then it were a ſin to uſe it, though no man took offence at it; and to come afterward with the conſideration of ſcandal, doth not help on the proof that it is a ſin, but only makes it a double one.</p>
                  <p>And again on the other hand, if there were more and more weighty ſcandal taken at the uſe of the Common-prayer, then at the non-uſe, in ſuch a caſe a man were bound not to uſe it (ſuppoſing it were everywhit as indifferent, as the chuſing a piece of meat in the ſhambles) though it had never been uſed in an idolatrous ſervice. And indeed it doth not appear to me that the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>Eat not,</hi> meerly to avoid ſcandal. For I doubt whether the caſe would not have been the ſame, if the perſon had ſeen it offered to Idols himſelf, or if not a brother, but an Infidel had told him; or if he had bought it in a diſguiſe, that no body knew of it. I am ſure the Apoſtle argues from a more intrinſecal Topick then the ſcandal of the ſpectator, <hi>viz.</hi> that by eating meats offered to Idols they were in danger <hi>to have fellowſhip with devils; ſince thoſe that eat of the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are partakers of the Altar.</hi> Indeed the men I deal with ſeem to reſtrain thoſe words to eating <hi>in the Idols Temple;</hi> but I know not upon what Reaſon; for whoſoever ſhall read the eighth Chapter, ſhall find that the Apoſtle makes eating the ſaid fleſh in the Idols Temple to be no worſe then eating it in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, houſe at an invitation; for there is no worſe ſaid of the one then of the other. By this which hath been ſaid, the Reader will eaſily, ſee a way made to the diſcovery of a wide difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99541:33"/> the caſe of <hi>fleſh</hi> offered to Idols and the <hi>Liturgy;</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he be one of thoſe which are wont to blaſpheme it with the Nick-name of <hi>Porridge.</hi> When it is proved that the Common Prayer is fleſh offered to Devils, and ſo brings us into danger of having fellowſhip with devils, then ſomthing is done to make good the Reaſon, and not till then. The moſt which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ſay to this purpoſe, is in the next words; <hi>For our part, we are not able to fathom a Reaſon why a form of words fitted up for uſe in prayer, ſhould not be liable to the ſame corruption and pollution, which a diſh of meat fitted for natural uſe is.</hi> But I can quickly tell them more reaſons then one, wherefore ſome diſhes of meat (namely ſuch as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, offered to Idols) ſhould be more polluted, as they word it. I mean more unlawful to be uſed then ſome forms of words can be, and in particular thoſe which are in the Liturgy, notwithſtanding the fore-mentioned uſe of them in time of Popery. (1.) The ſaid Fleſh was offered to an Idol; but the prayers of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy were offered to the true God, while uſed by the Papiſts. For the God to whom they prayed, hath the ſame Attributes with the God which we pray to. What though they think that bread in the Sacrament is turned into the fleſh of Chriſt, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently hypoſtatically united to the Godhead! I do not believe that they think the bread is God. And they have a Scripture, which if taken litterally, would warrant their adoration of the bread; which the Pagans have not for their Idols. However none of the prayers in the Liturgy were made to this breaden God. If it be ſaid, that though the prayers were not made to an Idol, yet the putting up of theſe prayers was joyned with other acts of Idolatrous worſhip; I anſwer that ſtill they have not left the caſe in the ſame ſtate with that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tteats of: For thoſe meats were offered to <hi>falſe</hi> Gods. Therefore to make the caſes alike, we muſt ſuppoſe the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens to offer fleſh to a falſe God; and at the ſame Aſſembly, either before or after, to offer other fleſh to the true God. The Queſtion is, whether it were not lawful to eat the one, though not the other? I muſt ſee the one forbid as clearly as the other, before I can doubt of the difference. I might add, that if the Papiſts apprehend the Bread to be God, or if they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it with divine worſhip, yet they do not apprehend it to be <hi>Mars,</hi> or <hi>Venus,</hi> or other falſe gods, neither do they <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend</hi>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99541:33"/> to worſhip any ſuch God; but they intend to worſhip the true God, the ſame whom the Proteſtants worſhip: But the meats which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, were offered to other Gods then that which the Chriſtians worſhip. The Scripture ſaith they worſhipped <hi>Devils;</hi> and that they did <hi>intentionally,</hi> calling them by that name themſelves. And this is one, and that no inconſiderable alteration of the caſe. (2.) The Apoſtle only forbids the eating of the ſame <hi>numerical</hi> fleſh which was offered to Idols, not the ſame <hi>ſpecifically.</hi> Though fleſh was offered to Idols, yet a man might eat fleſh; and though Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton or Beef was offered to Idols, yet a man might eat Mutton or Beef, ſo that it were not that ſame <hi>individual</hi> Fleſh, Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton or Beef that was offered to Idols. But now the words, ſentences and orations which are in the Common prayer-book, are not the ſame <hi>numerically</hi> with thoſe in the Maſſe-book. Latine and Engliſh differ certainly as much as Male and Female, if not as green and blew. Therefore when a Miniſter reads the Liturgy, he doth not ſpeak one word which is <hi>numerically</hi> the ſame with thoſe which the Popiſh Prieſt ſpeaks while he ſays Maſſe. As to inſtance, The Proteſtant Reader ſays <hi>[Grant us thy peace]:</hi> But the Popiſh Reader offers not theſe words to God in his Idolatrous ſervice. May be he ſaith, <hi>Da nobis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem tuam.</hi> But the word <hi>[Dae]</hi> is not the ſame <hi>numerically</hi> with the word <hi>[Grant]:</hi> Yea, the Ear diſcerns as great a difference between them, as the Eye doth between red and yellow. The <hi>Genus</hi> of every word ſpoken is a <hi>ſound;</hi> and if the ſound be not the ſame, the <hi>word</hi> is not the ſame. Nay if the Popiſh Prieſt ſhould read in Engliſh, <hi>grant us thy peace:</hi> the ſound which he makes, is not the ſame <hi>numerically</hi> with that which the proteſtant makes. For the ſame numericall accident cannot be in two ſubjects. And there is another plain alteration of the caſe. (3.) By eating meats offered to devils, the <hi>Corinthians</hi> would be in danger of having fellowſhip with Devils, as the Apoſtle ſaith, and may be ſeen in the writings of thoſe that relate the Pagan rites and Ceremonies in their myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and how the Devils were attracted by them. Thus to this day thoſe which uſe charms, amulets, or the like, do many times come under the power of the Devil in their bodies or eſtates; and are ſaid by Divines to make an <hi>implicite,</hi> though not an explicite <hi>contract</hi> with him. But no ſuch danger of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99541:34"/> having fellowſhip with Devils, can be pretended in uſing thoſe words in our prayers to God, which were uſed to the ſame God, though in a ſervice performed to the ſame God after a falſe manner: ſuppoſing that the ſaid words are otherwiſe true and good, which my Opponents do them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſuppoſe in this argument; And there is a third alteration of the caſe. (4.) The Authors give this Reaſon wherefore meats offered to Idols might not be eaten, as may be ſeen in their words cited already, viz. <hi>becauſe there was other meat to eat; The earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof:</hi> which implies that it was lawful to eat ſuch meats, in caſe <hi>none other could be had.</hi> Now this is our caſe in reſpect of the Liturgy, ſuppoſing it to be eſtabliſhed by Law. At ſuch times as are appointed for the uſe of the Liturgy, there are no other prayers <hi>to be had.</hi> I know, a man hath a natural power to put up other prayers: and ſo, if a <hi>Corinthian</hi> could by buying, or begging, or other lawful means procure no meat, but what had been offered to Idols; yet he had a natural power to <hi>ſteal</hi> ſome. But doubtleſſe he ſhould rather eat meat offered to Idols, then take thoſe meats which were another mans propriety by the Laws of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and conſequently ſuch as he had no right to. And doubtleſſe an Engliſh Miniſter ſhould rather uſe the prayers of the Liturgy, though they had been offered in an idolatrous ſervice, then thoſe which the Laws of <hi>England</hi> forbid him to meddle with at ſuch a time: But that ſo many do otherwiſe, it may well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the ſweetneſſe of <hi>ſtollen</hi> waters. But beſides this reſtraint of the Laws which allow us no other words to uſe, moſt men are further reſtrained by the nature of the thing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they have ready at hand as rich a <hi>Sylva</hi> of <hi>Synonimous</hi> words, as there is a variety of <hi>meats</hi> in natures <hi>cornucopia.</hi> For a man can hardly put up a petition without uſing ſome words that are uſed in the <hi>Maſs.</hi> And ſo by this Reaſon we ſhould not pray at at all with vocal prayer. I might bring the Authors to another abſurdity by arguing that their Reaſon makes it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to uſe the <hi>Creed</hi> as a publick profeſſion of Faith, ſince the Papiſts uſe it, and the Authors will not allow it to be of the Apoſtles making: But I fear they will <hi>grant</hi> the abſurdity, and therefore I dare not tempt them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99541:34"/>
                  <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Scripttures that they bring, which forbade the Jews to uſe ſuch words, geſtures, and actions, as</hi> Idolaters <hi>did, ſignifie nothing to their purpoſe. Their Argument from</hi> Hoſ. 2.15, 16. <hi>and</hi> Zech. 13.2. <hi>conſidered. Popiſh</hi> Idolatry <hi>is but an improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the</hi> Non-conformiſts <hi>principles. Their Pretence [that</hi> conformity <hi>is a ſtep to</hi> Popery] <hi>confuted and returned upon themſelves, who cannot confute a</hi> Papiſt <hi>but by quitting their</hi> own <hi>Principles.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>I Have now produced the Miniſters <hi>ſecond Reaſon</hi> with all the forces which they have aſſigned for its defence in their ninth chapter; and have I think, manifeſted the very ſtrength of it to be weakneſſe. But they come up with a reſerve in the <hi>Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript,</hi> where they cite multitudes of Scriptures which forbid the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to uſe ſuch words, geſtures and actions that Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters did: as to wear Linſie-woolſie garments, to let cattel en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender with a diverſe kind, to ſow a field with mingled ſeed, to call God by the name of <hi>Baali.</hi> But I ſuppoſe the Authors can lawfully do theſe things themſelves: Therefore I ask them, if theſe Prohibitions bind us <hi>Engliſhmen?</hi> If they ſay they do, let them give a Reaſon why they tranſgreſſe them, and it will ſerve their brethren. If they ſay that ſuch prohibitions bind us not to forbear the actions which are named there <hi>in terminis,</hi> but other actions of the <hi>like Reaſon</hi> as having been done by Idolaters, as uſing the forms of prayer that were uſed by the Papiſts; then they make themſelves ridiculous. For how can a Law be ſuppoſed to forbid <hi>only</hi> thoſe things which are <hi>not</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, becauſe they bear analogy and proportion to the things which <hi>are</hi> named, when the things themſelves which are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>expreſsly</hi> in the Law, are not forbidden? If they interpret thoſe prohibitions as forbidding us to do ſuch things as Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters did, not in civil uſages, but only in divine worſhip (as ſomewhere they make the diſtinction); then we are to labour in all words, actions, and geſtures, in which we are left to our Liberty, to go contrary to the ſaid Idolaters: and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if they have the Sacrament at Noon, we ſhould have it at Midnight; if they worſhip toward the Eaſt, we ſhould worſhip
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99541:35"/> toward the Weſt (as the Authors ſay the Jews were commanded to do for the ſame Reaſon); if their Churches ſtand Eaſt and Weſt, ours ſhould be ſituate North and South; if they preach out of a Pulpit, we ſhould preach out of a pew; if their heads are bare in prayers, ours ſhould be covered; if their Communion-table ſtands in the chancel, ours ſhould ſtand in the bell-fry. In all which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, I believe, the Authors themſelves think it not unlawful to be like the Papiſts; ſo that I wonder what they mean to quote ſo many Texts, forbidding the Jews to be like the Idolaters not only in ſuch circumſtances of Worſhip as I have named, but even in ſome punctilio's much more trivial and inconſiderable, and ſome of them not at all concerning the Worſhip of God, as <hi>ſowing a Field with two ſorts of ſeed.</hi> There is more ſhew of ſtrength in a <hi>Marginal</hi> note, which they put down, <hi>pag.</hi> 97. in theſe words. <hi>Note that both in</hi> Hoſ. 2.15, 16. <hi>and in</hi> Zech. 13.2. <hi>two Texts plainly relating to the times of the Goſpel, God forbids all mention of Idolatry, and declares his will, that it ſhould not be ſo much as remembred. Now we cannot ſee how we ſhould obey thoſe precepts in keeping their very rites, modes and methods of Worſhip.</hi> But I would fain know a Reaſon why they break theſe Precepts (or rather Prophecies) by uſing ſuch Rites and Modes of Worſhip as Idolaters have uſed, (ſo that no Idolatry be committed in the uſing of them) any more then by remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring and uſing the names of falſe gods, which are the things ſpecified in both thoſe Texts: which certes are not ſo to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, that Saint <hi>Luke</hi> may not be found a tranſgreſſor in putting down the names of <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> in the Bible it ſelf; or (if he be priviledged by inſpiration) that the Authors may not condemn their Brethren, that in the cauſe of Non-conformity, have ſometimes left reading the Scriptures to their <hi>Pariſhioners,</hi> to read <hi>Ovids Metamorphoſis</hi> to their <hi>Scholars.</hi> I can conceive how Saint <hi>Luke</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Schoolmaſters</hi> may be ſaid to mention and remember the name of Idols: but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine how I remember the name of Idols by ſaying <hi>O God, the Father of heaven, have mercy on us!</hi> or any other prayer of the Liturgy. Thoſe who in their Books, Sermons, yea and in their very Prayers, tell the people that the ſaid forms are taken out of the Maſſe-book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, which for my part, I profeſſe to be more then I know; theſe are they which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99541:35"/> keep up the names of Idols: The greateſt part of the people would not think of them, but that their Miniſters are their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Remembrancers. The ſame may be ſaid of the uſual names of the moneths, and dayes of the week, which do include the names of heatheniſh Gods and Goddeſſes, which ſome have taken much pains to ſhew and preſſe for the credit of Mr. <hi>Jeſſe</hi>'s Almanack: But his Almanack would be needleſſe except theſe things were firſt preſſed by ſuch tinkerly Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, who make work, that ſo they may mend it. For who thinks of <hi>Venus</hi> when he mentions <hi>Friday,</hi> though <hi>Frea</hi> ſignifie the ſame? And who thinks of keeping a Feaſt to <hi>Saturn,</hi> when he celebrates the Nativity of our Saviour; or of honouring <hi>Flora</hi> in a <hi>May pole?</hi> None, I dare ſay, or but very few, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting ſuch as have been endroctrinated by the ſaid <hi>Reformers:</hi> No more then a man means to ſwear by <hi>Hercules,</hi> when he ſaith or writeth <hi>Mehercule;</hi> which I am ſure I have met with in Theological diſcourſes made by Authors, never ſuſpected of any good inclination to Popery or other Idolatry. In like manner, who thinks of the Lady of <hi>Loretto,</hi> or other Popiſh Idols, in reading of the Liturgy? Only the diſcourſe I oppoſe, is the direct way to effect that, which they pretend to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
                  <p>I have argued all this while upon the Authors ſuppoſition, <hi>That the worſhip of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>in the whole complex is idolatrous.</hi> But they might more properly ſay, that a buſhel filled half with wheat and half with rye, is a buſhel of wheat, or that a Sermon is nonſentical in the whole complex, if ſome few phraſes of it be non-ſenſe; or that a Tranſlation is erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous in the whole complex, if there be ſome few <hi>Errata's</hi> in it. Whoſoever faith a <hi>Blackamore</hi> is white ih the whole complex, according to my Criticks, tels a lye, though he be white in his teeth. I might alſo add, that the Papiſts in the groſſeſt part of their idolatry, in adoration of the bread, are juſtified by a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, which the Non-conformiſts (or moſt of them) do main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; and their idolatry is but the lawful emprovement of this Principle; <hi>viz. That Reaſon is not to judge what points are to be received as articles of faith, and what not.</hi> For this principle being ſuppoſed, there is no warrant to interpret thoſe words figuratively, <hi>This is my body,</hi> ſince all the warrant which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, is, that the literal ſenſe is repugnant to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:99541:36"/> pronounceth it abſolutely impoſſible that one body ſhould be in two places at once. But according to this Hypotheſis of the excluſion of reaſon from the judgement ſeat, the Papiſt might reply, <hi>Indeed my reaſon tels me that it is impoſſible, but the Scripture ſaith, This is my body; and therefore I ought not to mince the words at the command of reaſon, which hath nothing to do in matters of faith. Indeed the Scripture ſaith, the Body of Chriſt is in heaven; but I believe it is on earth too at the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt. Nothing but Reaſon gain-ſayes, and ſhe hath nothing to do to judge in the caſe.</hi> What can a man that goes on this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, reply to the ſo much condemned Idolater? Out of his own mouth he is confuted: He laid down the doctrine, and the other makes the natural and genuine uſe. Thoſe therefore which hold this principle, cannot judge the action of the Papiſts in adoring the Bread to be idolatrous without ſelf-contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and if they will act according to their light, this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Reaſon ſignifies nothing to them though it may to others.</p>
                  <p>I cannot conclude my notes on their ſecond Reaſon without reflecting upon another, extracted from the ſame Topick; and by what they have ſaid upon this Reaſon, rendered more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditable to the unwary and half obſerving Reader. For they have ſprinkled in ſeveral pages of their book many ſhrewd hints, as if the Liturgy uſhered in the Maſſe, and conformity were a ſtep toward Popery. As page 67. <hi>We know that thoſe Miniſters and people, who are moſt zealous againſt Popery, are moſt averſe to this Liturgy.</hi> But a <hi>zeal</hi> for any cauſe, except it be bridled by diſcretion, and attended with an equal pace of ſtrength, is not the way to protect it, but to betray it. We ſaw lately, that the States-men which were moſt <hi>zealous</hi> for the <hi>good old Cauſe,</hi> loſt it; and the King had not better friends then his moſt implacable enemies. <hi>Fury</hi> is as bad in a Champion as <hi>torpour;</hi> it is an even temperature of wiſdom and valour which doth the execution: A <hi>ſober</hi> Proteſtant, though he rageth leſſe, ſhall prevail more on a Papiſt then a mad <hi>Fanatick.</hi> The greateſt part of the <hi>zeal</hi> againſt Popery, which is found among the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> is like that of one <hi>frantick,</hi> who wounds himſelf while he would ſtrike his foe. They are mad againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> but they cannot tell why; they cannot confute it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out condemning themſelves, as I could prove in many Inſtances.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99541:36"/> This unguided <hi>zeal</hi> will be ſure to run far enough from Popery, and ſo runs into it; as he that ſails round the Globe, the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he goes, after he is half way, the nearer he approacheth to the place from whence he ſet out. Thus the Quakers, a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part of the Non-conformiſts, rayled at Popery till they began to be taken for Jeſuites, or their diſciples. I have heard of ſeveral Papiſts that have turned Proteſtants by the reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of men <hi>zealous</hi> for the Liturgy: But I profeſſe unfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I never heard of one that of late years was won by any Non-conformiſt, excepting by Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> And I believe he would have been as unſucceſsful as others, but that he goes upon more moderate principles. Me thinks the example of Doctor <hi>Coſens,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> once moſt ſuſpected of Popery for his <hi>zeal</hi> for the Liturgy, and yet exerciſing a no leſſe couragious then conſiderate <hi>zeal</hi> againſt Popery in the time of his exile; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, I ſay, this example alone were ſufficient, not only to ſtop the mouth of calumny in this particular, but to non-plus jealouſie it ſelf. I confeſſe in ſome things the Conformiſts come nearer to the Papiſts then others; but it is as Souldiers make their approaches to the enemy to <hi>fight</hi> with him, and are therefore many times thought to <hi>fall</hi> away; but when they return with their ſpoils, captives, and <hi>Trophees,</hi> none is ſo hard-faced as to maintain the ſuſpition. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf, it is known, hath not only been ſuſpected, but verily believed to be a Papiſt, and that by ſome <hi>Rabbi's,</hi> meerly for his conceding ſome Poſitions to the Papiſts, which no reaſonable and juſt man can deny them; whereby he hath done more to the ſhaking of the very foundations of the Papal Sea, then all the Non-conformiſts that ever mannaged the Controverſie, which I ever heard of. But I have ſo much to ſay upon this ſubject, that it would require a Book by it ſelf: Doctor <hi>Sanderſon</hi> in both his Prefaces to his Sermons hath ſhewed, how much ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is done to the Pope by the Non-conformiſts in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particulars; where the Reader may be ſatisfied concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the falſeneſſe of that which they affirm page 109. <hi>That there is nothing of more tendency to confirm the Papiſts in their way of worſhip, then for them to ſee us keep much the ſame.</hi> Indeed they may be confirmed in the good parts of their worſhip by ſeeing us do the ſame, and all the better; it is better they were <hi>Papiſts</hi> then <hi>Atheiſts:</hi> But how can they be
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99541:37"/> confirmed in the <hi>bad</hi> parts of their worſhip, by ſeeing us to uſe the good, and refuſe the bad? They are rather confirmed by ſuch as refuſe the <hi>whole:</hi> For then they will think <hi>all</hi> to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed out of humour, ſince <hi>ſome apparently</hi> is; and that we have no more reaſon againſt the bad then againſt the good, ſince we carry our ſelves with the ſame averſation to both. So that the experiment they relate in the ſame page, <hi>How ſome forreign Papiſts, liſtening at the doors, where they have heard Service read and ſung, cryed out, This is the ſame with ours:</hi> This experiment, I ſay, is for the <hi>credit</hi> of the Liturgy, as more facilitating the Papiſts coming over to us, and being a more eaſie ſtride then <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers. The Authors tell me very good news, and I am heartily glad to hear, that the Papiſts begin to like that ſervice which heretofore they perſecuted with fire and faggot. And ſo much for the Miniſters ſecond Reaſon, contained in their ninth Chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:99541:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Their</hi> third reaſon <hi>from</hi> ſcandal, <hi>conſidered.</hi> (1.) <hi>No ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall hath any foundation</hi> in re. (2.) <hi>No ſcandal is</hi> allow'd <hi>in Scripture.</hi> (3.) <hi>It is but</hi> juggling <hi>for thoſe to plead</hi> ſcandal, <hi>who hold the things</hi> unlawful. <hi>Or</hi> (4.) <hi>who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour not to convince the ſcandalized of their errour, but do themſelves moſt confirm them in it.</hi> (5.) <hi>The command of Authority out-weighs ſcandal, and alters the caſe from that in St.</hi> Pauls <hi>dayes.</hi> (6.) <hi>Their Argument ſtands charged equally againſt the</hi> Directory <hi>as the</hi> Liturgy.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THe Authors finding their Reaſon, drawn from <hi>the uſage of the Liturgy in times of Popery,</hi> to be too light, and the other taken from the <hi>ſcandal of Brethren that are offended therewith,</hi> to be no more ſolid and weighty, have ſophiſtically joyned them both in one in the ninth Chapter, that their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent might be as much cumbered in the defence of his cauſe, as a man that fights with two at once. For one Anſwer will not ſerve for theſe two Arguments, which they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded together. But I have manifeſted already that they are two diſtinct Arguments, ſince neither of them is rendered more accompliſhed for the purpoſe by the acceſſion of its fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; and the Authors themſelves acknowledge the diſtinction, as by the many words they ſpend to prove the unlawfulneſſe of offering that to God, which hath been offered in an idolatrous ſervice (without mentioning the caſe of ſcandal) ſo alſo in the Title of their <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> where they plainly ſay, that the latter is <hi>another</hi> Reaſon from the former.: Therefore having anſwered the former, it is very reaſonable according to the laws of Method, that I make the examination of the latter
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99541:38"/> (taken from the ſcandal of brethren) to be the proper ſubject of this preſent Chapter. In the fortification of which, the firſt thing they do, after the naked propoſition of it, is to prevent an anſwer: The <hi>Prolepſis</hi> is in theſe words; <hi>We are aware what the Doctors of</hi> Aberdeen <hi>ſaid of old, to prove that the ſcandal of Brethren weighs light, when put in the ſcale with the command of Authority. There may ſomething be ſaid for their Aſſertion, where the ſcandal is meerly paſſive, and hath no foundation in</hi> re; <hi>only men are offended, becauſe they are offended. But where the ſcandal is ſuch, as is ſo far allowed by Scripture, that a negative precept is given upon it,</hi> Eat it not; <hi>we are not of ſo eaſie a faith as to believe what they ſay when Gods Word ſaith, Do it not.</hi> To this I reply (1.) That no ſcandal hath a foundation <hi>in re;</hi> The foundation of ſcandal is the errour and weakneſſe of the Perſon ſcandalized: And we ought to be ſo far from reſpecting <hi>leaſt</hi> ſuch offended perſons, that ſeem to labour under the <hi>greateſt weakneſſe,</hi> that we are to reſpect them <hi>moſt.</hi> For to offend the little ones is worſe then to offend the <hi>Phariſees, Doctors,</hi> and <hi>Rabbies.</hi> But now generally thoſe which are offended at the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> as they do think themſelves the moſt able men and women, and accordingly declaim againſt the groſſe ignorance of others, yea even of the Clergy, making it their recreation to ſcoffe and ſcorn at them, and to contrive and tell ridiculous fables of them; ſo by the Authors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they are many times acknowledged to be the ableſt ſort of Chriſtians and Miniſters; and therefore they ought not to abſtain from conformity for fear of offending them, whoſe offence is rather counterfeit then real, having no foundation <hi>in re,</hi> that is, in weakneſſe, nor in any errour, which is not eaſily vincible, if they are of ſo great gifts as they have the credit of. (2.) Whereas they ſay, that the ſcandal alledged is ſuch, and ſo far allowed in Scripture, that a negative Precept is given upon it, <hi>Eat it not:</hi> I anſwer, that no ſcandal is <hi>allowed in Scripture,</hi> and no Sctipture doth ſo far <hi>allow a reſpect</hi> to the ſcandal taken at the Common-Prayer, as to ſay, <hi>uſe it not,</hi> eſpecially when the Laws both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil ſay, <hi>uſe it.</hi> For I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated in the Chapter fore-going a vaſt difference between the caſe of <hi>meats offered to Idols</hi> and the Liturgy. (3.) It is but juggling for thoſe perſons to uſe an Argument drawn from <hi>ſcandal,</hi> who believe the thing <hi>unlawful,</hi> though no
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:99541:38"/> offence were taken. For whoſoever ſaith, he he doth not an action becauſe people are offended, doth thereby confeſſe, that he thinks it an <hi>indifferent</hi> thing. As if a man ſhould ſay, <hi>I commit not adultery, becauſe if I did, I ſhould offend the Brethren:</hi> The hearer would conclude, that the ſpeaker either thinks, that adultery is otherwiſe lawful, or elſe doth hugely prevaricate. Therefore, ſeeing the Authors do think the uſe of the Common-prayer unlawful, though no body took offence at it, they ſhould have done ingenuouſly to cut ſhort the controverſie, and not mention ſcandal, that a ſpeedy iſſue might be procured. For I cannot ſee how I can argue with them upon the point of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, but by ſuppoſing that the perſons, who fear to give ſcandal, by doing the action, grant the action to be lawful, though they, whom they fear to ſcandalize, judge it unlawful. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am forced to proceed here on that ſuppoſition. (4.) Such Perſons cannot reaſonably pretend the ſcandal of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren as a Reaſon of their Non conformity, till they have uſed all means within their power to convince the ſcandalized Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that their offence is canſeleſſe, and the thing is lawful. But if they on the contrary by their actions, ſermons, and familiar conferences, beſide their writings, do labour to confirm them in that weakneſſe and errour, which cauſeth the ſcandal (as uſually they do) then this ſcandal is no more excuſe for their forbearance of conformity, then it would be for a child which comes not when called by his Father, to ſay, <hi>the dores were locked,</hi> when he had locked them himſelf. (5.) A man is to forbear many things, that he may nor give offence to others, in caſe he is left to his liberty; which yet he is bound not to forbear, but to do, in caſe he be commanded by Authority, which is the caſe in hand. (6.) This Argument (if it were of force) would evince it unlawful to uſe the <hi>Directory,</hi> as well as the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy.</hi> For there was never <hi>Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Directory</hi> made, nor can any be made, as things ſtand, but ſome will be offended at it. Therefore other circumſtances are to be conſidered, which have a power to render the offence in conſiderable; of which hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:99541:39"/>
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>(7.) <hi>The ſeveral Sects of</hi> Non-conformiſts <hi>make nothing of offending one another. An Inſtance in taking the</hi> Scandalous Tithes. (8.) <hi>An unanimous Eſſay of theſe Miniſters might remove the</hi> Scandal. <hi>What they count, ſcandal, is loſſe of</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what account it is better that ſome</hi> ſuffer, <hi>then that</hi> Forms <hi>ſhould be laid aſide.</hi> Perſecution <hi>lies at their own dores. Their little engaging againſt the known enemies of God, mens</hi> vices.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p n="7">(7.) THe ſeveral Sects of Non-conformiſts make nothing to offend one another. The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> the <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents,</hi> and they the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and they the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and ſo <hi>vice versâ,</hi> while every one of them doth what ſeems good in their own eyes. Why then do they ſcruple it in uſing a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Form of worſhip? May they offend the Brethren on their own heads, but not when commanded by Authority? If they anſwer, that thoſe things wherein they offend one another, are by each party counted <hi>neceſſarily good;</hi> but the uſe of the Liturgy they account a thing <hi>indifferent</hi> (for ſo we muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to ſpeak, if they argue upon ſcandal) and therefore, though they boldly offend one another in the former actions, they dare not in the latter: I reply, that they ought to account conformity <hi>neceſſarily good</hi> ſo long as it is required by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and they ought not to account thoſe actions neceſſarily good, by which they offend one another. As to inſtance, how many were offended at the Miniſters for taking <hi>Tithes?</hi> Yet I never knew any man who feared to give the offence, though it was not a <hi>neceſſary</hi> duty to take them. For why might not the Miniſter remit the Tithes of his Pariſh, as well as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did remit the contributions of the <hi>Corinthians?</hi> Nothing can be ſaid for taking Tithes, notwithſtanding the offence taken thereat; but the ſame may be ſaid in the defence of Conformity, for all the offence which is taken at it. Yea, and that which makes the caſe worſe, Tithes were as really offered to God in times of Idolatry, as the Prayers of the Liturgy; and their offended Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren uſually called them Antichriſtian Tithes for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But may be, the Authors make light of offending other Sects
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:99541:39"/> beſide their own; May be, they would uſe the Common Prayer, if only other Parties were offended: but they dare not offend their own Party. Therefore I anſwer. (8.) Laſtly, That there is no fear but that the Miniſters whoſe caſe is here pleaded, have ſo much Authority and influence upon their own party (whom I have found more ſubmiſſive to one ſentence quoted from their own Teachers, then to an hundred Reaſons in this caſe), that if they would, they might eaſily change the Peoples minds; eſpecially, if they were unanimouſly reſolved on the Eſſay, as they ſeem to be on the quite contrary. Yea thoſe who had ſo much power to bring them into the Error, cannot have much leſſe to bring them out; and they are the more bound to endeavour it. But in that they do not ſo much as attempt it, it is very probable even to the Judgment of charity it ſelf, that what they call ſcandal of the Brethren, is loſſe of Reputation among their own Sect; and the Biſhop of <hi>Exceters</hi> cenſure is eaſily reconcilable with that <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Candor</hi> which the Authors miſſe in the ſame, and complain thereof in theſe words; <hi>The Biſhop of</hi> Exceter <hi>is miſtaken therefore in ſuggeſting that we forbear the uſing of the Liturgy out of a little point of Reputation amongst ſome People rather weak then wiſe, and to be pittied more then imitated; and he ſhews little candor or charity in ſaying, we ſacrifice our Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to our credits, and out of a fear and lothneſs to offend ſome people, whom we may eaſily convince and ſatisfie as well by our examples as Arguments,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This is not ſpoken like a tender and good Chriſtian.</hi> Why not? For if the People are in an Error, and that ſuch an one which hath already done much miſchief in Church and State, and is likely to do the like again, except Gods great mercy prevent, and the Miniſters know it is an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror (for that muſt be ſuppoſed, if they expect the benefit of this Argument), and yet will not labour to undeceive their People, eſpecially if they have been means of bringing them into this Error themſelves; can Charity it ſelf imagine other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but that this tenderneſſe proceeds only out of a point of Reputation? Whether it be ſo, God only knows; to their own Maſter they muſt ſtand or fall: But ſo it appears. For though they oppoſe to this cenſure a profeſſion that they <hi>do not think Non-conformity to be now the way to credit;</hi> yet they muſt certainly mean only a Credit with <hi>ſome</hi> Perſons, <hi>whom</hi>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:99541:40"/> they care not for. But that Non-conformity is the way to get Credit with <hi>other</hi> Perſons, it is manifeſt by that which the Authors ſay in their <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> of their own obſervation, viz. <hi>That thoſe who have returned to the uſe of the Common Prayer, have made themſelves the ſcorn of ſome, and the grief of others.</hi> There is no ſuch Reputation to be gained by a Divine as to preach againſt that which is eſtabliſhed by Law, and to be the Head of a diſcontented Faction. For that cauſe which hath leaſt of the civil Power to maintain it, ſtands in moſt need of wit and abilities to defend it: And the abilities which are ſo uſed, ſhall be taken notice of and admired, when thoſe which defend the oppoſite cauſe ſhall be over-looked as needleſſe. Beſide that it is glorious in the Eyes of the vulgar, to out-face Authority, to go in a ſingular way; and for a man by his ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular actions to cenſure his Superiors as if he were above them. Upon which account the <hi>Cynicks</hi> of old, and the <hi>Quakers</hi> now, for all their pretences to humility, have deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly obtained from wiſe men the name of the proudeſt and moſt ambitious Sects that ever were.</p>
                  <p>The Authors ſtay moſt upon this Argument in their <hi>Poſtſcript;</hi> and therefore thither I muſt follow them when I have firſt left an animadverſion upon the exclamation they make in this chapter aganiſt certain perſons, who (they ſay) <hi>had rather their Brethren ſhould be perſecuted, and all the Chriſtian World ſcandalized, then that the forms of Prayer under queſtion ſhould be laid aſide.</hi> If there were any ſuch Perſons; I know not but others may be more blame-worthy, who had rather provoke thoſe perſecutions and pull them down on their own heads, beſides the ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of a far greater part of the Chriſtian World, then that that the ſaid forms of Prayer ſhould be uſed. But indeed I know no ſuch Perſons as thoſe whom they ſtigmatize with this deſcription. For neither are <hi>all the Chriſtians in the world</hi> ſcandalized with the Prayers; neither. do I know any that had rather their Brethren ſhould be perſecuted, then the Prayers laid aſide, the laying of them aſide being ſingly conſidered in the compariſon, and with abſtraction from thoſe things which are pretended as a Reaſon why they ſhould be laid aſide, or would follow there-from. The exacters of conformity exact their due; give them their due, &amp; then you may expect a diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation: otherwiſe the compariſon is unjuſtly made betwixt the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:99541:40"/> 
                     <hi>ſufferings</hi> of thoſe which ſubmit not, and the <hi>keeping up of the forms:</hi> The compariſon ſhould be made betwixt the ſaid <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi> and the keeping up of the Credit and Authority of the Laws. It were ſurely better that the Magiſtrate ſhould keep them up, then that the contempt of his Authority being grown ſo inſolent and mighty that he cannot maſter it, ſhould force them to lay them down. For the keeping them up notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſufferings which by accident of humane corruption are conſequent thereto, can prove only to the prejudice of ſome particular Perſons, who (while the Law is in force) deſerve to incur it by their own Act: But the laying them down upon ſuch an account, would be dangerous to the whole Church and Kingdom, by ſubmitting the diſcipline of both to the head-ſtrong outrage of the Subject. Suppoſe a Maſter command his ſervant ſome <hi>light</hi> matter upon pain of <hi>ſuffering:</hi> It is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed better that the ſervant ſhould ſuffer, then that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment ſhould be revoked, the terms of the compariſon being <hi>ſimply</hi> and <hi>abſtractly</hi> conſidered. But it is better that the commandment ſhould not be revoked, then that the ſervant ſhould get head over his Maſter. Let the ſervant ſhew his willingneſſe, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n he may expect his Maſters indulgence in remitting the command. Let the preſcriptions of the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy be never ſo light matters; yet certainly <hi>obedience</hi> is a matter of importance, and that is it which is contended for; and it were better that the Subject ſhould ſuffer, then that obedience ſhould be denied. By which note I may alſo anſwer another Argument which they bring in the 90. page of their Book: viz. <hi>That though the ceremonies were lawful, yet they are not expedient, becauſe they will bring ſo many ſcandals and ſufferings: and every thing which is not expedient, ſo far as it is not expedient, is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi> To which I anſwer (1.) A private mans <hi>uſing</hi> of theſe cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies cannot be inexpedient in neither of thoſe reſpect; neither in reſpect of <hi>ſcandal,</hi> nor in reſpect of <hi>ſufferings.</hi> For as for the former reſpect, The good of obedience doth overpoiſe the evil of ſcandal. And as for the latter, The uſe of them brings no ſufferings on him that uſeth them; neither doth his uſing them make another ſuffer who uſeth them not, but only as he who doth his duty by accident aggravateth the caſe of him who omits it. (2.) Suppoſe that the ceremonies were too light and inconſiderable to be impoſed by ſuch penal Laws; and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:99541:41"/> conſequently that the <hi>making</hi> of the Law was inexpedient, though the <hi>keeping</hi> of it be not; yet, if the Magiſtrate judge it expedient, he is bound to make it; and much more may he look for obedience to it, when it is already made, until it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, yea though he judged it inexpedient. Nay further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, the caſe may be, that the ſame Law, which was once inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to make, it may be no leſſe inexpedient to repeal, as I inſtanced before, when the repealing of it ſhall let looſe the reins to popular inſolency, and ſhall be interpreted as done out of fear of a mutiny and inſurrection. To conclude, the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings which are pretended, can at moſt be only an Argument to the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to <hi>alter</hi> the Law; but this can be no reaſon wherefore a <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhould not <hi>keep</hi> the Law while it is in force, which is the end it is alledged for in the Book. There is no man can be more againſt placing much moment in the light appurtenances of Religion then I am; or for Liberty to vary, ſo it be <hi>extra caſum contemptus:</hi> But to ſee men take this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, becauſe the Magiſtrate thinks not fit to give it; and while they expect his indulgence in things which they ſcruple, not to obey him ſo far as they can without ſcruple; and laſtly to ſee thoſe claiming that liberty as a due, which they would not grant to others as a Largeſſe, if they were in power, but would forbid things under as great pains as they are now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; I will ſay no more, but <hi>Quis tulerit</hi> — For that theſe rigid exactions of ſuch things, as the Authors call light and frivolous, is not the only fault of the Conformiſts, appears from hence, That when they had loſt their power, men were as ſeverely dealt with for not taking the Covenant, or for ſaying <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> or the <hi>Creed</hi> in their Churches. Therefore I can ſay an hearty <hi>Amen</hi> to the Authors wiſh, <hi>That men would uſe their heat againſt the known enemies of God, ſuch as drunkards, blaſphemers, unclean perſons, curſers, and ſwearers</hi> (or rather againſt their vices) <hi>then againſt the Servants of the living God.</hi> But here I find the Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts <hi>moſt</hi> at a fault, who (to my obſervation) preach leaſt againſt theſe vices; which makes their Auditors uſually to call ſuch a Miniſter as bends his ſtrength againſt them, a <hi>meer moral Preacher;</hi> and to account <hi>that</hi> the moſt <hi>Goſpel-preaching,</hi> which declaims more againſt the ſuppoſed faults of the Magiſtrate, then the real ones of the People; more againſt Biſhops, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:99541:41"/> Common-Prayer, and the like, then any of the vices fore-mentioned.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Their Queſtion anſwered, Whether the Magiſtrate may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ſuch things as are matter of</hi> ſcandal. (1.) <hi>He may if the</hi> good <hi>to be procured by them be greater then the</hi> evil <hi>of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal.</hi> (2.) <hi>If the offence be taken</hi> after <hi>the Command, he may continue it. This Queſtion is quite beſide the Queſtion. Their pretence [that the Magiſtrates command cannot juſtifie any man in breaking Gods Command] anſwered. That which was</hi> ſcandal <hi>before the Command, is none</hi> after: <hi>As that which is</hi> murder <hi>in a private man, is not ſo in a</hi> commiſſioned <hi>Officer.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THis Reaſon (as I ſaid before) is moſt largely inſiſted on in their Poſtſcript; where having quoted a multitude of Precepts, which forbid <hi>offending the weak Brethren,</hi> they take notice of an Anſwer which is uſually given, <hi>viz.</hi> That theſe Precepts only concern us where the command of our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors doth not make the thing neceſſary. Whereto they reply thus, <hi>We would gladly know, whether the Magiſtrate be not as much obliged not to command things indifferent, where ſuch a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal will ariſe, as the inferiours not to do them.</hi> I anſwer, (1.) If the things (though <hi>indifferent</hi> in themſelves) be <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> to procure a greater good, then the ſcandal which will ariſe from them be an evil, he may; and if he thinks that the ſcandal is not conſiderable or worthy to be reſpected, he is <hi>bound</hi> in ſuch a caſe to command the ſaid things. For he muſt be judge of his <hi>own</hi> Acts; otherwiſe he is in worſe caſe then a private Chriſtian, and muſt enact <hi>nothing,</hi> as I ſhewed in my firſt Chapter. (2.) For the ſame Reaſon (and with much more) if the Magiſtrate hath commanded an indifferent thing, and the offence be taken <hi>after</hi> the command, he may continue his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. For elſe it were in the power of the Subject to bind the Magiſtrate at pleaſure, to repeal all his Laws concerning indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things. As if he ſhould make a Law, that there ſhould be no traffick with a Nation that he is minded to make war with:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99541:42"/> The people miſliking the Law might ſay, they are offended therewith; and ſo make it his duty to reverſe that Law. And this is the caſe under queſtion. For the Authors themſelves cannot ſay, that the greateſt part of the better ſort were offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the uſe of the Common-prayer, when it was firſt impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; but on the contrary it was highly liked and approved by all, or moſt, except the Papiſts: and therefore a better Reaſon againſt the Common-prayer might be drawn from the offence which the Papiſts took at it, becauſe they were offended <hi>before</hi> it was eſtabliſhed by Law. But the offence, which is pleaded by the Authors, is an offence taken <hi>ſince;</hi> and ſo it is an offence taken at that which was made neceſſary in its uſe before, and therefore not to be regarded. (3.) Though it ſhould be granted, that the Magiſtrate himſelf is by the Law of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained from commanding any thing, by which weak Chriſtians may be offended; yet that is nothing to the Queſtion contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted: For the Queſtion is not, what the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> is forbid to do, but what the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ought to do. Now though the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> might not, for this Reaſon, <hi>impoſe</hi> the Liturgy; it doth not from thence follow, that the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may not uſe it.</p>
                  <p>Indeed in the ſame place the Authors frame an Argument to prove, that a man may not do any thing which ſhall ſcandalize his Brother, though he be commanded to do it by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. The Argument is in theſe following Termes. <hi>We ſuppoſe our Brethren will not ſay, that the Magiſtrates command can juſtifie any ſoul in violating the expreſſe Law of God. And as they themſelves would not interpret the Law of God thus, Thou ſhalt not ſteal, that is, except thy Superiour command thee; or, Thou ſhalt not commit adultery, that is, except thou beeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: ſo they muſt pardon us, if we cannot ſo interpret the Law of God in the caſe of ſcandal.</hi> To which I anſwer, That thoſe <hi>Material</hi> Actions, which would be tranſgreſſions of the Moral Law before they are commanded by the Civil Law, are ſometimes no ſuch tranſgreſſions after they are ſo commanded. And the reaſon is, becauſe theſe Actions have not the ſame <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality</hi> which they had before; and conſequently many times the change of their Nature is commonly owned and expreſſed by the change of their denomination, which will eaſily appear by particular Inſtances. For that very Action (for the matter of it) which would be Theft and a breach of the eighth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99541:42"/> before the act of humane Authority commanding it, or only permitting it, is not theft after ſuch an humane pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept or permiſſion, nor any breach of the eighth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And the ſelf-ſame Action (for the matter of it) which would be Murder before commanded by humane Authority, and a violation of the ſixth Command, is afterward neither Murder, nor any breach of that Command. And therefore by good proportion I may add, that the ſelf-ſame action, which was ſcandal in property of ſpeech before commanded by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authority, is no ſuch ſcandal afterward, nor any violation of thoſe precepts of the Apoſtle, which the Authors cite. The Reaſon is, becauſe that ſcandal, which is forbid by the Apoſtle, lies in an <hi>indifferent</hi> action: So it might be ſcandal before com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Magiſtrate, becauſe <hi>indifferent;</hi> but it is not ſcandal after commanded, becauſe made <hi>neceſſary</hi> by the divine Law requiring obedience to Rulers, which Law binds in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular upon the Emergency of an humane Law. To make this anſwer moſt plain: If I ſhould drive away my neighbours Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, and convert them to my own uſe, or to another mans, this were <hi>Theft,</hi> and a ſin againſt the eighth Commandment. But then there comes the command of a lawful Magiſtrate, which makes me a Conſtable or other Officer, and binds me to ſtrain them, and convert them to the uſe he preſcribeth: this is no <hi>theft,</hi> nor any breach of the eighth Command, though the Action be the ſame <hi>materially;</hi> for I drive away the ſame Cattel. Nay if there be no <hi>command,</hi> but only a <hi>Permiſſion,</hi> the caſe is the ſame: For if my Neighbours goods be confiſcated and given to me, I may do the ſame Action, and yet be guiltleſſe of theft. In like manner for <hi>John,</hi> being a <hi>private</hi> man, wittingly and willingly to kill <hi>Thomas,</hi> or to cauſe him to be killed, this is <hi>murder,</hi> and a ſin againſt the ſixth Command: But for <hi>John,</hi> being a <hi>Sheriff,</hi> and receiving a humane injunction to kill <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> ſo to do is no Murder, nor any breach of the ſixth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. So then I need not make ſuch a ſilly interpretation of the Precepts of the Moral Law, as the Authors ſuppoſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to defend my Cauſe. I need not argue thus; <hi>The Command ſaith, Thou ſhalt not ſteal,</hi> i. e. <hi>unleſſe thy Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour command thee.</hi> But rather thus, <hi>Thy Superiour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands thee to do that action, which would be ſtealing otherwiſe; but in that he commands it, it is no ſtealing.</hi> In this Inſtance
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99541:43"/> the very Appellation and name is altered with the Nature of the thing, meerly by the Magiſtrates Command, nothing elſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening <hi>de novo:</hi> But in other caſes alſo, though the name be retained, yet the nature of the Action is changed; ſo that whereas before it was contrary to the Moral Law, now it is made agreeable to it. For examples ſake, let us read the ſixth Commandement, as the laſt Tranſlation hath Engliſhed it; <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill:</hi> The Sheriff doth that Action, which is called <hi>killing,</hi> and yet breaks not that Commandment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe th s killing which he doth, is not of the ſame kind with that which is forbid in the ſixth Command. And wherein lyes the difference but in this? That the Moral Law forbids a private man to kill without publick Authority: But the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff kils by vertue of a power ſo to do, derived to him from humane Laws. In the caſe under hand, Do no action, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that may give offence: I am commanded by the Magiſtrate to do an action, which is otherwiſe lawful, but giveth offence; I do the action, and yet I break not the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles precept, becauſe it is not <hi>ſuch</hi> an offence as he means, though it go under the ſame general name, as the Act of the Sheriff and of the private man doe. For Saint <hi>Paul</hi> means (as the Authors Confeſſe) an offence taken from an action which in other reſpects and <hi>antecedently</hi> to the offence I might do or not do: But in this caſe my action is no ſuch; it is not an action which I might either do or leave undone <hi>antecedently</hi> to the offence; but I was bound in conſcience to do it, if no offence had been taken, and that by the Command of God, requiring obedience to the Magiſtrate, and therefore the duty being neceſſary <hi>antecedently</hi> to the offence in order of nature, yea and in order of time too, the falling out of the offence cannot <hi>warrant</hi> the omiſſion of it, much leſſe <hi>oblige</hi> to the ſaid omiſſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:99541:43"/>
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Conformity <hi>is not in its own Nature ſo</hi> ſcandalous <hi>as</hi> Diffor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, <hi>both in provoking</hi> Diſtaſt, <hi>and in laying</hi> ſtumbling-blocks <hi>in the way of the weak. The Miniſters</hi> Reaſons <hi>make as much againſt the Oath of</hi> Allegiance <hi>as the</hi> Common-prayer. <hi>It is abſurd to offend the</hi> Magiſtrate, <hi>that they may avoid the offence of</hi> private <hi>men. Their Reply to</hi> this <hi>is but a meer begging of the Queſtion, and betraying their cauſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>IN the next place they <hi>deſcribe</hi> the ſcandal which they ſay would be taken at their reading of the Common-Prayer, and make it conſiſt in two particulars. (1.) <hi>That people would ſcorn and vilifie them, and withdraw themſelves from communion with them;</hi> And (2.) <hi>That they would be encouraged by the examples of theſe Miniſters to do the like, although not convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the lawfulneſſe of ſo doing, and ſo ſin againſt their own conſciences.</hi> But I reply to them thus: As for the firſt part of the ſcandal, ſuppoſing that you are ſatisfied of the lawfulneſſe of uſing the Common-prayer, and have nothing to ſay againſt it but the ſcandal (as the ſuppoſition is made by your ſelves upon this Argument) I ſay, ſuppoſing your ſelves thus ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, then the people have more cauſe to vilifie you, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw themſelves from your communion on the other hand for diſobeying thoſe to whom God hath commanded you to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves. This hath evidently more appearance of evil in it then the other: I mean diſobedience hath much more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evil in it then obedience, and conſequently is much more ſcandalous in its natural tendency, and more apt to give offence of this firſt kind; that is, to procure a diſrepute and contempt among men who ſtand not on their heads, and have not their <hi>Opticks</hi> inverted. May be men will take a pretence from your conformity to call you <hi>Time-ſervers, Men pleaſers,</hi> and the like. But they may much more reaſonably take an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from your Non-conformity (ſuppoſing your ſelves are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied of the lawfulneſſe of conformity, were it not for the ſcorn which attends it) to accuſe you of a far greater ſin, which the Scripture parallels with that of <hi>Witchcraft.</hi> If therefore you ſtick on your credit, you ſhould rather fear a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:99541:44"/> to which you give not only a greater pretext, but alſo a real cauſe; then a leſſe reproach, to which you yield a leſſe pretence, and no real cauſe at all. For though people (at leaſt thoſe whoſe votes you moſt regard) are more apt to vilifie where there is leſſe cauſe, then where there is more; yet you ought more to fear the giving cauſe of reproach, then to be reproached: And beſides, who knows how ſoon their minds may be turned? For we ſee how men alter in their opinions about Religion; and then may be they will reproach you for omitting of that which now they would reproach you for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And as for the <hi>ſecond</hi> part of the ſcandal, you may by your example as much encourage ſome to ſin againſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, by not uſing of the Common Prayer as by uſing it: For why may they not be as well-emboldned to Non conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with a doubting conſcience by your example, as you think others will be encouraged to Conformity by the ſame example? In caſe they be, you lead them into a far greater ſin: For to conform purely in imitation of you, is their ſin only becauſe they do it with a doubting conſcience; But the contrary is a ſin without any reſpect to the ſaid doubts. If it be ſaid that there are none, or but a few of ſuch Perſons whom theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ought to regard that ſcruple the Lawfulneſſe of Non-conformity; and therefore that there is no danger they ſhould be led into ſin that way: I anſwer, that the Peoples Non-conformity is a ſin, whether they do it doubtingly or no; and the Miniſters practice doth confirm them in this ſin, and hinder them from doubting of it, that ſo they might leave it. Yea though the People think it lawful to diſobey the Act for the Common Prayer; yet they are very wild indeed, if they think without any ſcruple that they may violate other Acts: But now ſeeing their Miniſters to break one act as well as themſelves, they will the more eaſily be carried on in their Error, till they come to think they may break others alſo, And how the contempt of Laws hath proceeded by degrees from one to another, till the moſt fundamental Laws were overturned, we have ſeen by late and lamentable experience. And it is no wonder: For the very ſame Arguments which are brought againſt the uſe of Common Prayer, do ſerve as much againſt the taking of the <hi>Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance;</hi> For a <hi>Form of words in Prayer</hi> is there impoſed, ſince an oath is an invocation of God, and ſo are <hi>ſignificative cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies:</hi>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:99541:44"/> which the <hi>firſt</hi> Argument of this book, which I oppoſe, pronounceth unlawful. Again, <hi>ſuch words, actions and geſtures are there uſed in divine worſhip</hi> (for ſuch is an oath) <hi>which were uſed by Idolaters;</hi> and this is pronounced unlawful by their <hi>ſecond</hi> Argument. And laſtly, to take the Oath of Allegiance, is <hi>ſcandalous and offenſive</hi> to many of the weak Brethren which are offended at the Common Prayer; and therefore it ought not to be taken, if the <hi>third</hi> Reaſon was of any force, which is under my preſent <hi>examen.</hi> And I cannot let this paſſe without putting this queſtion, Should a man refuſe to take the Oath of Allegiance when required thereto, becauſe others are offended at it? I hope the Authors will allow ſuch an offence (how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or how good ſoever the Perſons are that are offended) to be inconſiderable. And yet it cannot be denied that the thing is indifferent in it ſelf, and only made neceſſary by humane Laws: For till the Law was made, no man was bound to take that Oath. Therefore, ſince humane Laws have force in this caſe to make that action lawful which many are offended with, they muſt needs have the like force in the caſe of the common Prayer, ſuppoſing it to be indifferent; ſave only for the ſcandal, which the Authors do ſuppoſe, and yet will not grant what is ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently inferred from the Hypotheſis.</p>
                  <p>With no better ſucceſſe do the Authors make an Eſſay to overthrow another anſwer, which is uſually given to this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of theirs, pag. 110. <hi>Whereas we are told that we offend many others, yea and thoſe our Superiours too, becauſe we do not do it; We anſwer, we are not willing to offend any, much leſs our Superiors: but if we be brought to this ſtrait, that we muſt either offend God or men, the choice is not difficult.</hi> By theſe words they muſt needs ſignifie, that to do it is to offend God; and ſo they beg the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and are gone quite beſide their preſent Argument, which ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the action indifferent, were it not for the offence which is taken at it, and that God is offended only becauſe men are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. Yea that is the Reaſon which themſelves give in their very next words, wherefore God would be offended by their uſe of the Common Prayer, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe ſome men would be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The queſtion is, whether God would be offended by the uſe of the Common Prayer: To prove he would, they urge the offence of ſome men: To this it is replied, that others more to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, are offended by their not uſing it: They anſwer its true;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:99541:45"/> But God is offended by the uſing of it: and that is the very queſtion, and ſo their Reaſon runs in a moſt ridiculous round. Therefore the compariſon which they make, is ſophiſtically ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted betwixt the offending of <hi>God</hi> by the uſe, and the offending of ſo me <hi>men</hi> and their <hi>Superiors</hi> by the Non-uſe. The compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon ſhould be made between the offending of ſome <hi>men</hi> by the uſe, and the offending of other <hi>men</hi> by the Non-uſe; yea between the offending of <hi>Private</hi> men by the uſe, and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of our <hi>Superiors</hi> by the Non-uſe. And thus the force of arguing in thoſe words which the Authors pretend to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, ſtands firm. For how can it be ſuppoſed that God ſhould be offended with their offending of <hi>ſome</hi> by reading the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, rather then that he ſhould be offended at their offending of others by not reading it? Yea who can conceive that God ſhould be offended at their offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>private</hi> men by uſing the Common Prayer, and not be offended rather at their offending of <hi>Superiors</hi> by not uſing it, ſuppoſing the thing otherwiſe indifferent, as they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in this Argument: So that the only thing to be conſidered, is, which of the two offences is the moſt weighty; that of ſome, or that of others; that of private men, or that of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate: For look which offence is moſt conſiderable, God is moſt offended with that offence. And no doubt it is a greater offence for a Servant to offend his Maſter by not doing an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different action which his Maſter bids him do, then to offend a fellow-ſervant by doing it: And there is the ſame Reaſon of offending a Magiſtrate, rather then a fellow-ſubject. Therefore the compariſon which they make betwixt offending God and offending the Magiſtrate, will be much more odious, if it be made betwixt the offending of God who requires obedience to the Magiſtrate, and the offending of ſome inferiour Perſons who diſlike this obedience in this caſe. Thus the Authors have underpropt this their third Reaſon taken from ſcandal, till they have made it fall down. They confeſſe their Argument cannot be made good without ſuppoſing that God is offended at the uſe of the Common-Prayer as well as men: They confeſſe that men are offended on one ſide, as well as on the other; and ſo the caſe is at leaſt equal on both ſides: They are forced for their laſt refuge to fly to the unlawfulneſs of uſing the common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>whoſoever be offended;</hi> and ſo they fly from this Argument, by
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99541:45"/> which they undertook to prove <hi>that the Liturgy is not to be uſed becauſe of ſcandal, though in all other reſpects it were never ſo law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful:</hi> ſince therefore themſelves have relinquiſhed the <hi>Fort,</hi> I may well withdraw my <hi>Battery.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Their</hi> fourth Reaſon <hi>from the</hi> Covenant, <hi>anſwered,</hi> (1.) <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that Oath a</hi> lawful <hi>one, it can at</hi> moſt <hi>but bind them to endeavour the</hi> repeal <hi>of the Act for Common prayer, and that only by</hi> lawful <hi>means; But it doth not free them from the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of it while in force.</hi> (2.) <hi>Conformity is not inconſiſtent with endeavours to root out Superſtition, or</hi> (3.) <hi>To promote the power of Godlineſs. Thetr</hi> Oath <hi>could not make Forms</hi> unlawful, <hi>if they were</hi> indifferent <hi>before. The</hi> New <hi>light they talk of, not comparable to the</hi> old. <hi>Their Argument</hi> [<hi>That the eſtabliſhment of the Liturgy by Law is not pleadable againſt the Covenant</hi>] <hi>anſwered. And what they urge from</hi> Numb. 30.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Title of their Fourth Reaſon, in the tenth chapter of their book, is this, <hi>Becauſe they have ſworn to endeavour a Reformation in worſhip, and to endeavour to extirpase ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and what hindreth the Power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</hi> Suppoſe that Oath wete lawful to be taken, why may they not keep ſo much of it as here is recited, notwithſtanding the uſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer? For (1.) If it were granted that the worſhip preſcribed in the Liturgy did need a Reformation; yet they may <hi>endeavour</hi> ſuch a <hi>Reformation,</hi> and uſe the worſhip pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed as it is, till it be altered; ſince nothing unlawful is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99541:46"/> though we ſuppoſe a Reformation might make it more expedient: Even as the Judges and Lawyers may <hi>endeavour a Reformation</hi> of the Laws, and yet <hi>proceed</hi> according to the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally ſetled courſe, till it be legally altered. Their Oath on ſuch a ſuppoſition binds them to <hi>endeavour</hi> that they may be <hi>free</hi> (and yet to endeavour by the uſe of <hi>lawful</hi> means only) from the impoſition which lies on them: But it doth not remit or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe them while they ſtand <hi>bound.</hi> (2.) They may <hi>endeavour to root our Superſtition,</hi> and yet uſe the Common Prayer, ſince no ſuperſtition needs to be committted in the uſe of it. For if there did, ſure theſe Authors would have proved it; which they do not, as hath been made to appear already. Yea their main charge with this weapon amounts to no more but this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous and partial ſuppoſition; <hi>Nor poſſibly is it clear to every one, that there is nothing in thoſe Forms of worſhip ſavouring of Superſtition.</hi> But I may retort, nor poſſibly is it clear to every one, that there is nothing ſavouring of Superſtition in the Directory made by the <hi>Aſſembly;</hi> or in any other that can be made. And when they queſtion whether there be <hi>Nothing</hi> ſavouring of Superſtition in the Common Prayer, they ſeem to confeſſe that <hi>all things</hi> there ſavour not of Superſtition. If then they would uſe <hi>ſo much</hi> of it, omitting that <hi>one thing which poſſibly</hi> ſome <hi>doubt</hi> to be ſuperſtitious, they would expreſſe a more moderate and peaceable Spirit. Neither (3.) Is the uſe inconſiſtent with the third point of their oath, <hi>to endeavour to promote the Power of Godlineſs:</hi> ſince obedience to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate in lawful things, is ſo far from being inconſiſtent with it, that it is moſt neceſſary thereto.</p>
                  <p>They proceed in the ſame page to tell us that if heretofore they looked on the uſe of thoſe forms as <hi>indifferent,</hi> ſurely the <hi>oath</hi> which they have taken, puts it into <hi>another</hi> capacity. But that cannot be, both becauſe in the former Section I proved it conſiſtent with their Oath ſo far as they quote it; and alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that which was before the oath thought by themſelves <hi>indifferent</hi> in it <hi>ſelf,</hi> was at the ſame time <hi>neceſſary</hi> in its <hi>uſe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commanded by Act of Parliament; and therefore being in <hi>truth</hi> neceſſary, and not then <hi>apprehended</hi> by themſelves as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, it could not be <hi>diſpenſed</hi> with, much leſs rendred <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful</hi> by the following Oath. For if it could, a man might evade every Act of Parliament about indifferent things with a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99541:46"/> ſafe conſcience: It is but ſwearing that he will not do what the Act requires; and ſo according to this doctrine that which is commanded, though lawful before the Oath, is put into another capacity after. They add, <hi>It is no wonder though their judgements be altered, and they hold the uſe now to be unlawful, conſidering how much Light hath ſhone into the World in that ſpace of time.</hi> But I wonder in what Horizon that Light dwells, ſince for ought I can find by my beſt enquiry, the ancient Divines were more moderate and clear in their poſitions; and the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Divinity</hi> (like the Book which goes under that name) hath only ſtrained the ſeveral Points of our Religion into ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd extremities; and run out of one Errour into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>In the ſixth Section of the Chapter under animadverſion, they ſay that the eſtabliſhment of the Common Prayer by Law, <hi>is not pleadable againſt the Covenant agreed upon by Lords and Commons legally aſſembled in Parliament; though contrary to ſome former Act of Parliament.</hi> But let the <hi>Lawyers</hi> ſay, whether the Lords and Commons without the Kings conſent can bind by oath (or give permiſſion) to do any thing contrary to a former Act of Parliament, while it is not repealed. For whereas they add, <hi>that the Covenant was ſo far ratified by the King, as unqueſtionably in conſcience would ſuffice to diſcharge any that ſhall keep it:</hi> I know what <hi>Ratification</hi> they mean. Indeed in their next Section they ſeem ſomewhat to explain their mind, urging <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. where they ſay, <hi>God expreſly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines the Oath eſtabliſhed for ever, if the Husband of the Wife, or Father of the child, either at firſt conſented, or did not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſſent, but hold his peace.</hi> But let Hiſtories and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of men ſpeak, whether the King conſented, or did not diſſent, but held his Peace. Beſides, his conſent might warrant an Oath taken to do ſomething that was lawful before, which is the caſe in <hi>Numbers:</hi> but if the Wife, or Child, or Subject ſwear to do any thing contrary to any Law in force, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Husband, Father, or Soveraign cannot ratifie that Oath, but it is diſſolved by its own Principles. Now ſuch is the Covenant, if it were contrary to any former Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the Authors themſelves make the ſuppoſition in this caſe; and therefore ſo far as I could ever learn, the Lords and Commons with the conſent of the King could not ratifie it
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99541:47"/> without an Act diſannulling the former Act, to which it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be contrary. But I diſmiſs this their Fourth Reaſon, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that the Burning of the Covenant ſince hath ſaved me the labour of any further exanimation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Their</hi> Other <hi>Reaſons anſwered.</hi> (1.) <hi>Their pretence againſt the</hi> perfection <hi>of the Common prayer, ſince it is more perfect then the</hi> Directory. None <hi>can be</hi> perfect. <hi>And it is lawful to uſe an</hi> imperfect <hi>Good.</hi> (2.) <hi>what they except againſt the</hi> Matter <hi>of the Liturgy. And</hi> (3.) <hi>againſt</hi> Particular <hi>prayers for every day,</hi> dividing <hi>the Service between Miniſter and People, and the Number of</hi> ſhort <hi>prayers.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>I Shall add as an Appendix to this Chapter, a Reply to the Authors <hi>eleventh</hi> Chapter, containing <hi>other Reaſons why di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Miniſters are not ſatisfied concerning the uſe of the Common Prayer,</hi> and to their <hi>twelfth,</hi> entituled, <hi>A ſummary recapitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Miniſters Reaſons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And firſt they accuſe the Common Prayer of <hi>imperfection</hi> thus: <hi>Surely none can ſay that take the Ordinary Prayers appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be read every morning-Prayer or Evening-Prayer, they do contain all things requiſite to be confeſſed or petitioned for.</hi> But a little uſe of unbiaſſed conſideration would have eaſily promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them with this triple ſolution. (1.) The Prayers appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for every Morning and Evening Prayer are palpably more perfect then any appointed for thoſe times by the <hi>Directory:</hi> For that preſcribes none at all to be uſed <hi>every Morning and Evening.</hi> And beſides, the <hi>Letany</hi> which is appointed to be read thrice a week, is a more perfect prayer then I believe ever was any put up <hi>extempore.</hi> For I will appeal to any man, how ſeldom he hath heard this moſt neceſſary Petition uſed in an <hi>extempore</hi> Prayer, which yet is in the Liturgy, viz. <hi>Forgive our Enemies, Perſecutors, and ſlanderers, and turn their hearts.</hi> (2.) If they would have every particular ſin confeſſed, and good thing petitioned for explicitly and expreſly in prayer, they would allow no room for Preaching, which they declaim againſt in others: For to utter ſuch a Prayer, would take up a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:99541:47"/> whole day. Wherefore then do they argue from the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Common Prayer, that it is unlawful to uſe it? ſince their own prayers are more imperfect then it; and though a Prayer may be made more perfect, yet ſtill it muſt be imperfect, except it ſhoulder out Preaching. (3.) What though the Common Prayer be not perfect? what is that to prove a man may not uſe it? May not a man uſe a Bible where much is torn out? or make a Petition for his Life, except he ſays all which can be ſaid, and forgets or omits nothing? A good thing may be uſed, though it be imperfect; as an hand which hath loſt a finger. Otherwiſe theſe Miniſters ſhould diſcard their own Sermons; ſince they muſt confeſſe with <hi>Paul,</hi> that they <hi>propheſie but inpart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) They next argue from the Matters of ſome things in the Liturgy, <hi>which in their judgement is not ſo approveable.</hi> But I wonder where they ever heard or ſpake a Prayer wherein were not ſome things not approveable in their own judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, at leaſt in the judgements of others. Take the beſt <hi>extempore</hi> prayer that they have ever made, and let it be copied out and publiſhed, and be extant an hundred years together, and in all mens hands for every body to pick a fault in it; and let it be the intereſt of the examiners to find it faulty: and no doubt but they will find many things not ſo approveable in their Judgements. But let us ſee the particulars of the Liturgy, which in their Judgement are not ſo approveable. They name two. (1.) <hi>That they underſtand not how they can ſay to God eight days together, that he ſent his Son to redeem us as upon that day, nor yet as to any particular day.</hi> For ſatisfaction in this point, let us make uſe of the <hi>Method</hi> ſo much commended by <hi>Socrates</hi> in <hi>Plato,</hi> who ſaith, That comparing, and as it were <hi>colliding</hi> two <hi>parallel</hi> caſes, we may eaſily make the juſtice of that which is under enquiry, to flaſh forth as light from the attrition of two flints. And the <hi>Parallel</hi> which I ſhall preſent to this purpoſe, is the <hi>Jewiſh Paſſover.</hi> Let it be ſuppoſed firſt (what the objection ſeems to intimate) that <hi>Chriſt-maſs day</hi> (when the words are to be uſed which are diſliked) hath not exactly the ſame place in the <hi>Revolution</hi> of the <hi>Solar year</hi> which the <hi>day</hi> on which <hi>Chriſt</hi> was born, had. No more (ſome years) did the <hi>day</hi> on which the <hi>Jews</hi> began the <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſover,</hi> agree with that whoſe deliverances occaſioned it, as
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99541:48"/> any man will grant, who holds Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> reaſon to be good, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Ecclipſe</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> at the <hi>death</hi> of our <hi>Saviour</hi> was in the Time of the <hi>Paſſover; ergo</hi> in the full <hi>moon.</hi> And as our <hi>Liturgy</hi> annexeth to the twenty fifth of <hi>December</hi> ſeven ſuceeding dayes to make up the ſame <hi>Feaſt;</hi> ſo beſides the night wherein the <hi>Paſchal Lamb</hi> was killed, when <hi>unleavened</hi> bread <hi>began</hi> to be uſed, The <hi>Feaſt</hi> of <hi>unleavened bread</hi> continued ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven dayes in remembrance of thoſe deliverances which were wrought for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the night of the fourteenth day of the Moneth <hi>Abib:</hi> All which days being appointed for one <hi>ſolemnity,</hi> may be well termed one day of <hi>thanksgiving.</hi> For how elſe could that <hi>ſelf ſame day</hi> wherein the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were brought out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> be poſſibly obſerved <hi>ſeven days</hi> together, as it is commanded <hi>Exod</hi> 12.17. Theſe things being conſidered, let any reaſonable man judge whether the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> (not only on the firſt night, but alſo on the ſeven fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing dayes) might not very lawfully ſay in their <hi>Anniverſary Thanksgivings, Lord, we thank thee for delivering us from the deſtroying Angel, and from Egypt, as upon this day.</hi> For the ſenſe is notoriouſly known to be <hi>figurative,</hi> if there had been never a <hi>quaſi</hi> expreſt. Now that which is falſe in one ſenſe, is not only true in another, but it hath not as much as the ſhew of an <hi>Aequivocation</hi> to ſpeak it, if the ſenſe be notoriouſly known. Beſides, it may as well be ſaid, that God ſent his <hi>ſon</hi> for eight dayes together, as that his Mother was <hi>puerpera,</hi> for a moneth. (2.) <hi>That they underſtand not how we can pray in Faith to be delivered from lightning, and tempeſt, and ſudden death:</hi> And yet they add, <hi>that they can underſtand how we may pray for deliverance from theſe Judgements, if it be the Lords will;</hi> and ſo in the ſame breath they grant what they deny. For that condition is as notoriouſly included in all prayers for temporal bleſſings, as <hi>homo</hi> is underſtood in <hi>quidam.</hi> Did not the Saints in the Old Teſtament pray for children? and is it not uſual in <hi>extempore</hi> prayers to beg temporal bleſſings without expreſſing the condition? But any Argument will ſerve them to delude ſilly people, though it make as much againſt themſelves.</p>
                  <p n="3">(3.) They add, <hi>that the ſpirits of ſober People are no wayes Reconcileable to the Liturgy, who cannot underſtand what founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is either in Scripture or right Reaſon for uſing particular
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99541:48"/> prayers for every day, or dividing the entire ſervice of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Miniſters and People, or for uſing ſo many ſhreds or ends of Prayer, or repeating the Lords Prayer ſo often.</hi> But theſe <hi>ſober</hi> People give no teſtimony of their <hi>ſobriety</hi> by their <hi>irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs</hi> to that which it good, meerly becauſe their <hi>own</hi> Eyes cannot ſee any ground for it in Scripture or Reaſon. If they were wiſe to ſobriety, they would conclude that thoſe who have greater abilities, and have more ſtudied the caſe alone, and debated it in Convocation, may ſee Reaſon for thoſe things which they ſee no Reaſon for. And as for the <hi>Particulars</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt, thoſe who uſe <hi>extempore</hi> prayers, do the ſame things whether they ſee a ground for it or no, as will appear by running over the four things inſtanced in. For (1.) as for <hi>uſing particular prayers for every day,</hi> it is accounted the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the <hi>extempore</hi> faculty to bring a particular Prayer for every day, and not to be guilty of ſaying the ſame Prayer any two days. And (2.) as for <hi>dividing of the entire ſervice of God betwixt Miniſters and People,</hi> this is uſuallly done in private meetings, where Miniſters and Lay-men pray <hi>alternis:</hi> Yea and in publick too, ſince the People ſing Praiſes in the meeters of <hi>Thomas Sternhold,</hi> as well as the Miniſter, and not only Praiſes but Prayers too. And as in ſome places of the Liturgy the People are enjoyned to ſay after the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> ſo in the foreſaid ſinging they ſay after the <hi>Clerk.</hi> (3.) I know not what they mean by the ſhreds or ends of Prayer which they ſpeak of, except it be the <hi>ſeveral</hi> Prayers appointed to be read in the Liturgy; which poſſibly they would have put all into one long and continued Prayer. If that be their mind, they ſeem to forget themſelves. For <hi>pag.</hi> 44. they commended <hi>Variety of prayers.</hi> And why may not many Prayers be ſaid at one and the ſame aſſembly, as well as at ſeveral? And yet they are very earneſt for this laſt. Yea they themſelves if they follow the <hi>Directory,</hi> uſe three prayers at the <hi>ſame</hi> aſſembly; one before they read, another before they preach, and a third after. And in extraordinary daies one Miniſter comes with one Prayer, another with a ſecond, and a third with a third, and ſo forth. Yea the ſeveral Petitions put up in every prayer, may as well be called <hi>ſhreds and ends of prayer,</hi> as the ſeveral collects and ſhort ejaculations of Morning and Evening-Prayer, Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or Communion-ſervice. (4.) As for the <hi>repeating of the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99541:49"/> Lords prayer ſo often,</hi> it is repeated <hi>twice</hi> in ſome Churches at the ſame Aſſembly where no Common Prayer is admitted. Now if it be lawful to repeat it <hi>twice,</hi> why not <hi>thrice?</hi> Yea where the Lords Prayer it ſelf is ejected, thete are frequent iterations of new-coyned Petitions. We know it is ſo where but <hi>one</hi> man is the ſpeaker eſpecially in a long prayer; but much more in a <hi>Faſt,</hi> when four or five ſucceed one another, not only in long Prayers, but for one and the ſame thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>(4.) <hi>They aggravate their Argument from</hi> ſcandal; <hi>from the</hi> looſeneſſe <hi>of many of the Perſons who are for the Liturgy. Four Anſwers given to this charge.</hi> (5.) <hi>Another of their conſiderations is, that the Liturgy is made an</hi> Idol, <hi>which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted on their own Party. Thoſe which have a true eſteem for the Liturgy, cannot diſeſteem</hi> Preaching.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p n="4">(4.) THey next aggravate their Argument from <hi>ſcandal</hi> by this conſideration; <hi>Many of the perſons offended at our forbearance of the Liturgy, are not of the ſtricter, but looſer ſort of Prefeſſors, ſuch at his Majeſty hath ſtigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in his Proclamation, as vitious, profane and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucht perſons, Drunkards, Tavern-haunters, Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</hi> But I anſwer (1.) That the Qualifications of the Champions or Aſſertors, are but a deceitful Rule to try a <hi>cauſe</hi> by. For ſometimes good men may have a private inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt againſt a duty, and bad men none. Sometimes thoſe who are under an habit of general vitiouſneſſe, may do ſomething right; yea <hi>Herod</hi> did many things: And on the other hand a ſanctified perſon may do ſomething wrong. If we ſhould judge of a <hi>cauſe</hi> by the <hi>Adherents,</hi> Chriſt himſelf ſhould be condemned, ſince owned by the <hi>Devil,</hi> and denied by <hi>Peter.</hi> The receiving of the Sacrament at <hi>night</hi> ſhould be the moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provable celebration, ſince practiſed by the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and not by the <hi>Papiſts:</hi> except theſe Miniſters prefer a <hi>Papiſt</hi> before an <hi>Anabaptiſt.</hi> There are many high and <hi>Heroick</hi> pieces of juſtice, clemency, and fidelity acted by the Heathens, which many that have the name of <hi>precious Chriſtians</hi> are impatient
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:99541:49"/> of: Are theſe things the worſe for that? In like manner, if the foreſaid ſtigmatized perſons yeild a better obedience to the Magiſtrate then others of a contrary quality, the difference of the perſons is impertinent to the Queſtion, The Authors ſhould <hi>Parcere perſon is, dicere de vitiis;</hi> not ſpeak of the <hi>viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> of the perſons, which are for the Common-prayer, but whether it be a <hi>vice</hi> to be for it; nor of the <hi>vertues</hi> of thoſe which are againſt it, but whether that oppoſition be any of their vertues. (2.) <hi>Deſinant maledicere, malefacta ne noſcant ſua.</hi> They ſay, that <hi>many, who are for the Liturgy, are Drunkards,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo are many which are offended at the uſe of it, and ſome ſuch as curſe and ſwear againſt it in the open Church. (3.) A very great, if not the greateſt part which are againſt it, if they are not <hi>drunkards, &amp;c.</hi> yet they are much worſe, and ſuch as blaſpheme their vertues by entertaining them in a den of moſt beaſtly vices; of whom I may ſay, <hi>Horum temperantia male habitat.</hi> Perſons which are notoriouſly malicious, and envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſeditious, traytours, heady, high minded, Quakers, Ranters, and the like, it is theſe mens cauſe which this book patronizeth. I will not add into the catalogue the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> though ſome of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Brethren have publickly charged the more ſober Sect of the two to have done more hurt then all the Drunkards and debaucht perſons in the Land. But methinks this Argument of theirs was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently retorted by that horrible <hi>Inſurrection,</hi> which was made at <hi>London</hi> laſt <hi>Chriſtmas.</hi> For if it be asked, Who were thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane and diabolical perſons, who roſe up to murder man, woman, and child, in ſuch a manner, that no ink is black enough to repreſent it! the anſwer muſt be, that theſe were ſome of thoſe, which are ſo <hi>impatient</hi> of the Common-prayer. (4.) Let thoſe which are for the Liturgy be never ſo bad, and their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites never ſo good, yet ſince the uſe of it upon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Magiſtrate is a neceſſary duty, it ought not to be forborn out of fear of offending, no not the better ſort, as hath been ſufficiently evinced. And therefore this concluſion of theirs is a very frivolous one, <hi>viz We cannot think it lawful for us to ſcandalize the far greater number of ſtrict Chriſtians, that we may gratifie a few others,</hi> &amp;c. For it is not to gratifie others, but the Magiſtrate and the Laws; or rather to gratifie right reaſon and conſcience, in complyance with that plain Command
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:99541:50"/> of God, <hi>Obey thoſe that rule over you in the Lord, and ſubmit your ſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. They add another conſideration to the like purpoſe, <hi>That that ſort of people, who are moſt zealous for the Liturgy, do ſo dote upon it, that it is clearly become their Idol.</hi> Poſſibly it may be ſo with ſome: For every one is for their <hi>own</hi> form and way of worſhip, and need the counſel of Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> to <hi>Monica,</hi> to follow the cuſtome of the Church ſhe comes to. But are not the Non-conformiſts as much for their way, and make as much an Idol of <hi>extempore Prayers</hi> (many of them thinking a mans prayers cannot be accepted, unleſſe not premeditated) yea and with much leſſe reaſon, ſince thoſe Prayers are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times forbidden, but the Liturgy is ſometimes commanded? But I cannot believe what they ſubjoyn, ſince both my obſervation and reaſon evidence the contrary, <hi>viz. With many people we ſee it demonſtrably true, that if a Miniſter did never preach the Word of God, yet if he did but read the Common-prayer, it would be enough.</hi> My <hi>reaſon</hi> wherefore I believe not this teſtimony (to ſay nothing of my <hi>experience,</hi> which is quite contrary) is this, becauſe the Liturgy preſcribes Sermons, and therefore whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hath an high eſteem of the Liturgy, muſt needs care for Sermons. But however it be with many people in that reſpect, what doth the Miniſter contribute to all this by reading the Common-prayer? which is the thing they ſhould have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated. Certainly no more then he, who ſets <hi>two</hi> diſhes of wholeſome meat before a man that likes <hi>one</hi> better, is the Reaſon why the <hi>other</hi> is neglected or poſſibly not touched. I would fain know, how the joyning of Prayer with Preaching, according to the Liturgy, doth nurſe the people up in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that preaching is needleſſe?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:99541:50"/>
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Both</hi> Precept <hi>and</hi> Example <hi>are alledged for</hi> Forms, <hi>though neither is neceſſary. Their Reaſons</hi> [<hi>wherefore its lawful to uſe the</hi> Lords Prayer, <hi>and yet not the <hi>Common-prayer</hi>] refelled.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>I Now proceed to the twelfth Chapter, entituled, <hi>A ſummary recapitulation of the Miniſters Reaſons;</hi> where they argue againſt <hi>limiting our ſelves to a form of Prayer, becauſe they can find no precept for it in the word of God.</hi> But that is notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly falſe. For the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Take unto you words and return unto the Lord, and ſay unto him, Take away iniquity,</hi> &amp;c. And I have already proved the ſame from the titles of <hi>Davids</hi> Prayers, which clearly ſpeak them appointed, for the uſe of others. Yea I have proved alſo, that if the uſe of a Form be not <hi>forbid</hi> in Scripture, it is lawful, though there were no <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> for it, nor <hi>example</hi> neither. But I muſt needs deny what follows, <hi>That there is no pattern of it in Scripture, but the Lords Prayer.</hi> For I have already produced a Form uſed by the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Diſciples. As for the Lords Prayer, they ſay, that <hi>they doubt whether it were intended for a form of Prayer or no, and rather think it a Direction for the matter of Prayer; one Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt ſaying no more then</hi> After this manner. But that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not, but that it might be intended to be ſaid in termes: For he that ſaith the expreſſe words, ſaith <hi>After this manner;</hi> though he that ſaith <hi>after this manner,</hi> doth not alway ſay the ſame words. So then he that ſaith the words, hath both Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts to warrant him; he that doth not, hath but one. And what though <hi>Chriſt and his Apoſtles leave no record of their uſing of this form,</hi> which is another thing they urge, where do they leave record of their not uſing it? which if it were <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded,</hi> would never the more prove the uſe unlawful. For where do they leave any record of ſinging Pſalms in Rime and Meeter, and other forms of worſhip, which yet are thought
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:99541:51"/> lawful? Indeed this is the Antiſabbatarians argument, <hi>If the ſeventh day was ſanctified from the creation, then the celebration and keeping of it by the Patriarchs before the giving of the Law would have been recorded.</hi> But they have been anſwered by theſe Authors, Brethren in non-conformity, <hi>That many things may have been done which are not recorded.</hi> For all this they add, <hi>Yet we doubt not but we may uſe it in the form;</hi> and ſo put it to an uſe for which God never intended it. Their Reaſons are, (1.) <hi>Becauſe it is holy Scripture.</hi> But I would fain know a reaſon why a form of words which are not holy Scripture, may not as lawfully be uſed as thoſe which are. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſure all the phraſes or forms of ſpeech, which are uſed in <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers, are not <hi>holy Scripture.</hi> (2.) Becauſe (ſay they) <hi>it is ſo ſhort, that we may eaſily get it by heart, and not employ our ſouls at our eyes by reading, while they ſhould be wreſtling with God</hi> It ſeems then, that (whatſoever they ſaid before) though there be no precept or pattern in the Word of God, yet a man may uſe a ſet form of Prayer, if it be ſo ſhort that it may be eaſily remembred; and that one thing, which they have againſt the Common-prayer, is, that it cannot be remembred, but muſt be read. But I anſwer, that the <hi>reading</hi> of the <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> which they diſallow, is not ſuch a <hi>diverſion of the ſoul from wreſtling with God,</hi> as the <hi>remembring</hi> of the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> the uſe whereof without book they allow. I never knew a man in <hi>reading</hi> of a Prayer frequently to skip what he intended to ſay: but I have been told of a man, and that of very great parts, who never offered to ſay the Lords Prayer in publick but he was out. The employing of the ſoul at the <hi>eye</hi> in reading, is nothing ſo much as her employment in that part of the <hi>brain</hi> which is the ſhop of memory, ſince the characters imprinted on the book are not ſo eaſily obliterated and defaced as thoſe inſtamped on the brain. Let any man tell me, whether his thoughts be not leſſe roving from the ſubject, while he is read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a book which he remembers not, then while he is remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring a ſpeech got by heart? or whether the ſoul be not put to more labour by ſaying it <hi>memoriter,</hi> then by reading it in a plain print. (3.) They ſay, that they can uſe the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> becauſe <hi>the divine authority of it is ſuch, as it hath another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:99541:51"/> of influence on their ſpirits in uſing, as all the Scripture hath, then can be pretended for any other forms.</hi> But if they mean by this divine Authority they ſpeak of, a divine inſtitution, this cannot be pleaded by them, except they will grant, that Chriſt appointed us to uſe theſe words in prayer, which before they denyed; and therefore I think that not to be their meaning. If by this divine authority they allow to the Lords Prayer, they underſtand only that the form of words came out of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Mint, not excogitated by man, but dictated by the Spirit of God; then the ſame influence may be expected from ſome other forms, being of divine authority as well as the Lords Prayer, as thoſe in the Liturgy, <hi>O Lord open our Lips, ſave thy people, bleſſe thine inheritance.</hi> But if the Reaſon wherefore they can lawfully utter the Lord Prayer before God, be the divine authority of it, then ſomething (at leaſt) <hi>tantamount</hi> to divine authority muſt be found in the Prayers which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent themſelves, that they think it lawful to vent them. For it ſeems, if the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> were not of divine authority, they would not uſe it. By the ſame Reaſon they would not uſe their own Prayers, if they were not of <hi>divine authority,</hi> or were not endowed with ſomething of an <hi>equivalent</hi> credit with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine authority. But now their own Prayers are not of divine authority; therefore without doubt the Authors believe ſome excellency to be in them, which renders them as good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as if they were. And what is that, but clearly the <hi>extempore</hi> uttering of them? This is laid in the ſcales with divine autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and out-ballanceth it too, as will appear by theſe two caſes compared together. Theſe Authors would not uſe the Lords Prayer ſo as to utter the expreſſe words, if it were not of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine authority; but becauſe it is of divine authority, therefore they will. In like manner theſe Authors would not utter thoſe words, which uſually they do in prayer (beſides the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi>) if they were not invented <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore,</hi> but dictated by another, or by themſelves before-hand; but becauſe they are invented <hi>extempore,</hi> therefore they will. So that you ſee <hi>extempore</hi> invention is as much preferred before divine authority, as their own invented prayers are infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the Lords Prayer. And now no marvel, though men
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:99541:52"/> ſtickle ſo much for the liberty of the <hi>extempore</hi> vein; for ſo did <hi>Alexander</hi> for divine honours. How otherwiſe ſhall they be deified by the people? If you take away the divine authority of their Prayers, they may complain with <hi>Micah, What have we more?</hi> (4.) They give this as their laſt Reaſon, wherefore though they cannot uſe other forms, yet the Lords Prayer they can; Becauſe, ſay they, <hi>By the length of it we eaſily underſtand, that it was never intended to be uſed without any other Prayer.</hi> But that, which they eaſily underſtand, will not enter into the head of a rigid Non conformiſt whom I know; who, while he ſtayed in his place, was wont very often to begin at Church with the Lords Prayer, and to joyn no other Prayer with it. Yet if they were all of as eaſie a conception as theſe Authors, and agreed in the premiſes, that the Lords Prayer was never intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be uſed alone; yet how doth the concluſion follow thence, that therefore the Lords Prayer may be uſed, though not the Common Prayer? By this Reaſon they might more lawfully uſe the Common Prayer, if they might be ſuffered to joyn their <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers with it: But who can conceive that it ſhould be lawful to uſe a ſet form, ſo that it be in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with ſome other Prayers of their own framing, and yet it ſhould be unlawful to uſe it alone! For that Prayer, which is bad when alone, can make no better a ſound among a pack of good ones then a Gooſe among Swans. But it ſeems they compare forms of prayer, as the <hi>Wag</hi> did the <hi>Committee men</hi> to Fidlers, as if they were Rogues when ſingle, but in conſort with <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers were Gentlemen-Muſicians.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:99541:52"/>
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Their pretence, that no</hi> Forms <hi>were in uſe till four hundred years after Chriſt, anſwered. Their Arguments from the</hi> uſeleſneſs <hi>of</hi> Forms, <hi>from the</hi> Hereſies, Perſecutions, <hi>and</hi> ſeparations, <hi>which they cauſe, and from peoples reſting in them, conſidered and retorted.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THeir next Argument againſt the Common-prayer is this; <hi>Becauſe we cannot find, that there was ever any Forms of prayer uſed in the Church till four hundred years, or very nigh after Chriſt.</hi> But (1.) they muſt needs except the Lords Prayer, and many other Scripture Forms. (2.) As for other formes, I have noted at firſt, that it were needleſſe to rake into Antiquity for a Solution of this Queſtion, ſince they will not ſtand to the judgement of Antiquity. And therefore I thought it fitter to argue with them upon common and agreed Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, then upon an Authority which muſt be demonſtrated to them.</p>
                  <p>They argue thus in their following Section, <hi>Becauſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine any uſe at all of them, or any good they ever did, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when impoſed.</hi> This Argumentation is frequently incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated; <hi>We ſee no need. What good do they? What uſe is there?</hi> and the like. But take this Argument ſingly, as it is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in their Book, and it ſounds nothing. For this Argument cannot prove, that a Miniſter ought not to uſe the Common-prayer, except it be ſuppoſed that he muſt do nothing (though otherwiſe lawful) but what himſelf ſeeth to be uſeful and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; and by conſequence he ought not to conform to the <hi>Directory,</hi> except he ſhould ſee the uſefulneſſe of the ſeveral Directions; and ſo it ſeems that the <hi>Directory</hi> bound men not only to a conformity of <hi>practice,</hi> but alſo of <hi>judgement,</hi> which is a much more Tyrannical impoſition then that which theſe Authors ſo much complain of. But I wonder to ſee, that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:99541:53"/> thoſe who would be left to the liberty of <hi>Practice</hi> to do what themſelves think beſt, will not allow others the liberty of their <hi>conſciences,</hi> but would have all men not only to act like them in things lawful, but alſo to think like them touching the expediency of lawful things. A man knowing it lawful to conform to the Liturgy may do it, and yet keep his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment free, thinking that it might be much bettered and mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſo that though he be bound in his practice, he is left to the liberty of his thoughts. But when a man is required to ſubſcribe the long Confeſſion made by the Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, he is bound not only to do what he thinks might bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be undone, but to think that to be true which he thinks to be falſe. There is no compariſon betwixt the impoſing of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and the impoſing of a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of Faith. A man may diſlike the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and yet uſe them; as he that ſaid he would preach with a pair of horns on his head, rather then not at all: But a man that ſubſcribes a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of Faith, is at no liberty to diſlike it. Now my Obſervation is this, That thoſe men who are moſt againſt the impoſing of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> are moſt for the impoſition of <hi>Confeſſions</hi> of Faith, and complain againſt the Articles of our Church, becauſe there is not enough cramd into them to choak the ſwallow of an <hi>Arminian.</hi> Thoſe who think themſelves highly injured, when they are required to wear ſuch a white Garment as others do, in the mean time have the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to expect that all men ſhould be of the ſame mind that they are of. But to return to what I ſaid at firſt, A Miniſter may lawfully do ſome things which he knows no uſe of, were it only to conform to <hi>cuſtom,</hi> or to gratifie ſome <hi>private</hi> perſons; ſuppoſing that as he knows no good it doth, ſo he knows no hurt by it neither. But now when a thing of an innocent quality is <hi>commanded,</hi> there is this <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of it, if there were none elſe, that by doing this thing we render obedience to our Rulers, which is an high part of our Religion. It is for them to judge, <hi>what uſe and need there is of it,</hi> and <hi>what good it doth:</hi> It belongs to us to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire only whether it be lawful. He is a naughty Son or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, who will not do a lawful thing commanded by his Father
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:99541:53"/> or Maſter, except himſelf be informed <hi>what good it will do,</hi> or <hi>what uſe there be thereof.</hi> The Queſtion is, what <hi>hurt</hi> the uſe of Liturgies hath done, or is likely to do. And indeed in that place I am now upon, the Authors ſpeak ſomething to this pertinent point, aſſerting that <hi>Liturgies have been the Mothers of Hereſies, cauſing ſeparations, and dreadfull perſecutions, and will do ſo ſtill in Reaſon.</hi> But (1.) How have they cauſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations any more then Chriſt (if you underſtand it of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies in the <hi>general,</hi> and not only of <hi>naughty</hi> ones) only by accident? They ſhould prove that there is in a Liturgy <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus</hi> a Liturgy, a natural and proper tendency of it ſelf to cauſe ſeparations and Hereſies, or elſe they do nothing but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the Goſpel it ſelf. Who have made the greateſt Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Hereſies among us? thoſe who uſed the Liturgy, or they who forſook it? Ask the Quakers and Ranters where they began, and they will tell you. (2.) As for Perſecutions, what the <hi>impoſing</hi> of Liturgies hath done to raiſe them, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Queſtion: For the Authors pretend to give Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons wherefore a <hi>Miniſter</hi> may not <hi>uſe</hi> them when impoſed, not wherefore <hi>Rulers</hi> may not impoſe them. Now a Miniſter may uſe that which a Magiſtrate may not impoſe; as I have ſhewed already, &amp; could do it in an hundred undeniable inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. It is moſt certain indeed that ſome men have been perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the <hi>uſe</hi> of the Liturgy: but without their fault, and only by men of the ſame mind with the Authors. If any others have been perſecuted for <hi>not uſing it,</hi> ſuch inſtances aſſiſt not this their Argument, but make againſt it: For they ſhould ſhew how the <hi>uſing</hi> of it, and not how the <hi>not uſing</hi> of it doth raiſe perſecutions. But for my part I cannot ſee how ſuch Perſons who uſe it not, can be ſaid to be perſecuted while no other Mulcts are inflicted on them, then what are eſtabliſhed by the ſanction of the Laws; unleſſe by <hi>Perſecution</hi> we underſtand <hi>Proſecution:</hi> For ſo I confeſſe, not only they, but many a Thief and other Law-breakers have been perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
                  <p>The next Argument which hath not been already fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, is in their eighth Section; <hi>Becauſe the Generality of thoſe given up to all manner of looſneſs, are impatient for it, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:99541:54"/> reſt in it; it is as the Papiſts beads to them, and they care for no other worſhip of God: and we conceive it far from our duty to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den any in what we know is their ſin and wickedneſs.</hi> To which I anſwer, That any perſons care for no other worſhip of God, then what is preſcribed in the Common-prayer-Book, it is no wonder; ſince all is there preſcribed, Prayer, Reading, Singing, Preaching, Sacraments. If they mean that they care only for the Prayers, and not for the preaching: what they ſay, cannot enter into my faith, no not in a dream; and I have given the Reaſon of my diſbelief already. If any reſt in the common prayer, they ſhould be taught better; as thoſe which reſt in afternoon Sermons, or <hi>extempore</hi> prayers, who place their Religion in them, and think that a man cannot pray in the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> if he pray by a <hi>Form.</hi> Why do not the Authors fear <hi>to harden ſuch Perſons in their ſin</hi> by their example? Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe which think the Common-prayer may lawfully be uſed, ſaving for fear of ſcandal, ought ſometimes to uſe it, were it only for this Reaſon, that their Example might not tempt weak Chriſtians to think Religion conſiſts in Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, as many do, reſtraining the name of Chriſtians, the Godly, the Brethren, to the Non-conformiſts. For ſuch an opinion wrought or confirmed by ſuch an Example, would prove by much a more grievous ſcandal, then that which the Authors pretend to be ſo tender of; ſince there is more Reaſon for a man to reſt in conformity, then in Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity: For the former is a piece of obedience performed to the Moral Law, <hi>Honour thy Father;</hi> but the latter is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience thereto.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:99541:54"/>
                  <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The impertinency of pleading that the Liturgy is preſſed on them out of Malice. Such a</hi> ſuppoſition <hi>makes ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for</hi> Conformity. <hi>Their ſcruple at the</hi> obſolete words, dubious phraſes, <hi>and</hi> antique Reſponds, <hi>anſwered. Their</hi> Concluſion, <hi>and</hi> mine.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THey produce another Reaſon wherefore they cannot uſe the Common Prayer in the next Section, in theſe words, <hi>Becauſe we are aſſured in our conſciences that very many of thoſe who are earneſt for it, preſſe the uſe of it upon no other account, then from a principle of Malice againſt Gods Miniſters and People.</hi> But I think there was never ſeen a more feeble objection brought in a caſe of ſo much moment. For may not good and neceſſary duties be <hi>preſſed</hi> out of <hi>Malice?</hi> Was not the ſolemn League and Covenant accounted a good and neceſſary duty? and yet upon many a man was it preſſed out of <hi>Malice</hi> by thoſe who thought he would not take it, and ſo they ſhould have advantage againſt him. Is not the taking of the Oath of Allegiance a good and neceſſary duty? and yet poſſibly it may be preſſed upon ſome out of <hi>Malice.</hi> The truth is, this Argument taken from <hi>Malice</hi> is ſo far from making againſt conformity, that it makes ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for it. For by how much the more the Enemies of theſe Miniſters watch for their fall, and deſire a <hi>juſt</hi> occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt them; ſo much the more careful they ſhould be to give them none, but conform to the Laws, and ſtop the mouths of their ill-willers by an orderly and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able converſation.</p>
                  <p>In their next Section they ſay they cannot uſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, <hi>becauſe it is full of obſolete words, dubious phraſes, antick Reſponds.</hi> But (1.) As for the <hi>Obſolete
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:99541:55"/> words,</hi> I have heard that there is an intention of reforming them. However there are the like in <hi>Sternholds</hi> and <hi>Hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> tranſlation, and yet probably theſe Authors do <hi>ſing</hi> them with their People. Beſides, theſe obſolete words are not ſo hard to be underſtood, as many which the Aſſembly hath put down in their childrens Catechiſm; and may be all interpreted to the meaneſt capacity in one Sermon, and the hour better ſpent then often it is. And ſo may (2.) <hi>The Dubious phraſes,</hi> though I believe there is hardly made an <hi>extempore</hi> prayer which for the length of it hath not as many dubious phraſes; eſpecially if capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly examined as long as our Liturgy hath been. (3.) If by <hi>Antick</hi> Reſponds they mean <hi>Ancient;</hi> what hurt is there in that? Can theſe Authors uſe nothing that is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient? why then do they quarrel at <hi>Innovations?</hi> If by <hi>Antick</hi> they mean <hi>fooliſh</hi> and <hi>ridiculous;</hi> they ſhould remember that it is with modes, forms, faſhions, and ceremonies, as it is with other things: <hi>ſecundum modum Recipientis,</hi> ſalves all. That which is fooliſh and ridiculous to one, is grave and wiſe to another. Broad-brim'd Hats are ridiculous generally, when out of faſhion, and ſo are narrow ones when the others have been uſed awhile. If the Authors and the reſt of their minds would but unanimouſly uſe theſe <hi>Reſponds,</hi> the ſeeming <hi>antickneſs</hi> and ridiculouſneſſe in the Eyes of ſome at preſent would <hi>quickly</hi> be worn out. But therefore men think the faſhion ridiculous, becauſe it is not worn by ſuch Perſons as they moſt eſteem.</p>
                  <p>The Authors add in the ſame Section, that <hi>the Method of the Common Prayer (through the whole) is like to none in any reformed Church in the World.</hi> But I wonder that the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be ſo inconſiderable a part of the Chriſtian world, that ſhe muſt go to other Churches, and not they rather come to her. I am ſorry that Divines of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral forraign Churches have ſpoken much more reverently of our Liturgy, then the Authors.</p>
                  <p>They conclude, <hi>This is the ſum of our Apology: alway re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to our ſelves further liberty of adding any further Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments or Exceptions.</hi> Indeed they had need to reſerve
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:99541:55"/> that liberty; otherwiſe they have left their cauſe in a very poor condition. But we may eaſily ſee that they are ſo far from ſeeking ſatisfaction in theſe diſputes to their preſent doubts and ſcruples; that they are purpoſed to ſtudy and deviſe new Cavils, when theſe are anſwer'd. And therefore I ſadly prognoſticate, that neither this of mine, nor any other more able attempt will prevail with many ſuch perſons; that are rather active then paſſive in their doubts, and that ſtudy more how to fortifie their own Objections, then how to confute them. But if this undertaking may be but ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful, as to preſerve other more indifferent Readers fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> being miſled by the Reaſons whoſe ſophiſtry I have detect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I am infinitely recompenced for my pains, and can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly wait on the divine <hi>Suada</hi> to give a ſatisfactory an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Reſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
